<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss 
version="2.0" xmlns:iffy="http://tech.interfluidity.com/xml/iffy/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>drafts — interfluidity</title>
    <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/index.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[Feed for blog 'drafts — interfluidity', generated by unstatic]]></description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 8 May 2025 10:41:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>https://github.com/swaldman/unstatic</generator>
    <docs>https://cyber.harvard.edu/rss/rss.html</docs>
    <atom:link
    type="application/rss+xml" rel="self" href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/07/19/trump-v-united-states-greatest-hits/index.rss"/>
    <iffy:curation>
      <iffy:single/>
    </iffy:curation>
    <iffy:completeness>Content</iffy:completeness>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 20:05:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">
        https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/07/19/trump-v-united-states-greatest-hits/index.html
      </guid>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[It's a fraught time. Last night we endured a ranting lunatic allege that the nearly 80,000 alleged gang members El Salvador's President Bukele has detained without process have been dumped onto America's streets, contributing to a US crime wave that simply does not exist over the relevant time frame. (The crime wave that did exist emerged only during the ranting lunatic's presidency, years before, and has been subsiding ever since.) In the meantime, we still haven't settled on an alternative to...]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/07/19/trump-v-united-states-greatest-hits/index.html</link>
      <title>Trump v. United States: Greatest Hits</title>
      <dc:creator><![CDATA[Steve Randy Waldman]]></dc:creator>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header-body-footer">
  <div class="entry-header">
  </div>
  <div class="entry-body">
   <div class="flexmark markdown">
    <p>It's a fraught time.</p>
    <p>Last night we endured a ranting lunatic allege that the nearly 80,000 alleged gang members El Salvador's President Bukele has detained without process have been dumped onto America's streets, contributing to a US crime wave that simply does not exist over the relevant time frame. (The crime wave that did exist <a href="https://www.yahoo.com/news/opinion-ted-cruzs-fearmongering-rnc-105151488.html">emerged only</a> during the ranting lunatic's presidency, years before, and has been subsiding ever since.)</p>
    <p>In the meantime, we still haven't settled on an alternative to the ranting lunatic that sane people might vote for.</p>
    <p>Nevertheless, I'm stuck in a news cycle three-weeks old. Remember that one? The one that marked the <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/07/03/no-longer-a-liberal-democracy/index.html">end of liberal democracy</a> in the United States by providing a road map for how a US President can wield the vast powers of the American state without He or His <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/07/05/if-the-issue-was-the-lawfare/index.html">suboordinates</a> facing any practical risk of accountability to the law?</p>
    <p>I mean, I know there has been a <a href="https://marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2024/07/the-changes-in-vibes-why-did-they-happen.html">vibe shift</a>. But I'm having a hard time letting go of the whole liberal democracy thing. I guess it's pretty cringe.</p>
    <p>Anyway, this piece won't be an essay. It will mostly be exceprts of the Supreme Court decision, concurrences, and dissents. I've discussed <a href="https://www.supremecourt.gov/opinions/23pdf/23-939_e2pg.pdf"><em>Trump v. United States</em></a> a lot over the last few weeks, and I just want to keep some of the most prominent bits around to refer to.</p>
    <p>Before delving into the effluent from the Injustices of our Supreme Coup, I want to reproduce a sketch from Asha Rangappa. (Click for full size.)</p>
    <p><a class="bracketless" href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/07/19/trump-v-united-states-greatest-hits/asha-rangappa-flow-chart_1146x896.png"><img width="100%" src="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/07/19/trump-v-united-states-greatest-hits/asha-rangappa-flow-chart_1146x896.png" alt="Flowchart of determinations under Trump v. United States immunity tests"></a></p>
    <p>I think it's a very helpful summary. Please do read the <a href="https://asharangappa.substack.com/p/the-bloodless-coup-has-startedwith">excellent essay</a> from which I have stolen it. Rangappa writes:</p>
    <blockquote>
     <p>What you might notice if you follow the lines above carefully is that the question of motive — the reason that an action was taken — doesn’t even enter the equation until <em>after</em> the determination of whether the actions was official or unofficial has been made. Indeed, the Court explicitly states that <strong>"In dividing official from unofficial conduct, courts may not inquire into the President’s motives."</strong></p>
     <p>This is an astonishing statement, because it effectively means that <strong>it does not matter if a President uses the official levers of power with corrupt intent, for personal gain, or as retribution.</strong> In other words, the Court engages a sleight of hand where a critical distinction between <em>lawful and unlawful conduct</em> — the heart of criminal law, which rests on whether a person acted with a specific state of mind, or <em>mens rea</em> — ceases to exist when it comes to the President.</p>
    </blockquote>
    <p>Let's go now to some selections from the decision. I'll refrain from commenting. I'm just excerpting for posterity. I may add to the collection over time.</p>
    <hr>
    <h3><a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/07/19/trump-v-united-states-greatest-hits/#excerpts-from-opinion-of-the-court-by-john-roberts" id="excerpts-from-opinion-of-the-court-by-john-roberts" name="excerpts-from-opinion-of-the-court-by-john-roberts" class="anchorlink"></a>Excerpts from Opinion of the Court, by John Roberts</h3>
    <p><em>From Opinion of the Court, <strong>John Roberts</strong>, p. 4:</em></p>
    <blockquote>
     <p>Citing <em>Marbury</em> v. <em>Madison</em>, 1 Cranch 137 (1803), the [D.C. Circuit] court distinguished between two kinds of official acts: discretionary and ministerial. 91 F. 4th, at 1189–1190. It observed that “although discretionary acts are ‘only politically examinable,’ the judiciary has the power to hear cases” involving ministerial acts that an officer is directed to perform by the legislature. <em>Ibid.</em> (quoting <em>Marbury,</em> 1 Cranch, at 166). From this distinction, the D. C. Circuit concluded that the “separation of powers doctrine, as expounded in Marbury and its progeny, necessarily permits the Judiciary to oversee the federal criminal prosecution of a former President for his official acts because the fact of the prosecution means that the former President has allegedly acted in defiance of the Congress’s laws.” 91 F. 4th, at 1191. In the court’s view, the fact that Trump’s actions “allegedly violated generally applicable criminal laws” meant that those actions “were not properly within the scope of his lawful discretion.” <em>Id.</em>, at 1192. The D. C. Circuit thus concluded that Trump had “no structural immunity from the charges in the Indictment.” <em>Ibid.</em></p>
    </blockquote>
    <p><em>From Opinion of the Court, <strong>John Roberts</strong>, p. 7:</em></p>
    <blockquote>
     <p>No matter the context, the President’s authority to act necessarily "stem[s] either from an act of Congress or from the Constitution itself." <em>Youngstown,</em> 343 U. S., at 585. In the latter case, the President’s authority is sometimes "conclusive and preclusive." <em>Id.,</em> at 638 (Jackson, J., concurring). When the President exercises such authority, he may act even when the measures he takes are "incompatible with the expressed or implied will of Congress." <em>Id.,</em> at 637. The exclusive constitutional authority of the President "disabl[es] the Congress from acting upon the subject." <em>Id.,</em> at 637–638. And the courts have "no power to control [the President’s] discretion" when he acts pursuant to the powers invested exclusively in him by the Constitution. Marbury, 1 Cranch, at 166.</p>
     <p>If the President claims authority to act but in fact exercises mere “individual will” and “authority without law,” the courts may say so. <em>Youngstown,</em> 343 U. S., at 655 (Jackson, J., concurring). In <em>Youngstown,</em> for instance, we held that President Truman exceeded his constitutional authority when he seized most of the Nation’s steel mills. See <em>id.,</em> at 582–589 (majority opinion). But once it is determined that the President acted within the scope of his exclusive authority, his discretion in exercising such authority cannot be subject to further judicial examination.</p>
    </blockquote>
    <p><em>From Opinion of the Court, <strong>John Roberts</strong>, p. 8:</em></p>
    <blockquote>
     <p>“To the executive alone is intrusted the power of pardon,” and the “legislature cannot change the effect of such a pardon any more than the executive can change a law.” <em>Id.,</em> at 147–148. The President’s authority to pardon, in other words, is “conclusive and preclusive,” “disabling the Congress from acting upon the subject.” <em>Youngstown,</em> 343 U. S., at 637–638 (Jackson, J., concurring).</p>
    </blockquote>
    <p><em>From Opinion of the Court, <strong>John Roberts</strong>, pp. 8-9:</em></p>
    <blockquote>
     <p>Congress cannot act on, and courts cannot examine, the President’s actions on subjects within his “conclusive and preclusive” constitutional authority. It follows that an Act of Congress—either a specific one targeted at the President or a generally applicable one—may not criminalize the President’s actions within his exclusive constitutional power. Neither may the courts adjudicate a criminal prosecution that examines such Presidential actions. We thus conclude that the President is absolutely immune from criminal prosecution for conduct within his exclusive sphere of constitutional authority.</p>
    </blockquote>
    <p><em>From Opinion of the Court, <strong>John Roberts</strong>, p. 14:</em></p>
    <blockquote>
     <p>we conclude that the separation of powers principles explicated in our precedent necessitate at least a <em>presumptive</em> immunity from criminal prosecution for a President’s acts within the outer perimeter of his official responsibility. Such an immunity is required to safeguard the independence and effective functioning of the Executive Branch, and to enable the President to carry out his constitutional duties without undue caution. Indeed, if presumptive protection for the President is necessary to enable the “effective discharge” of his powers when a prosecutor merely seeks evidence of his official papers and communications, <em>id.,</em> at 711, it is certainly necessary when the prosecutor seeks to charge, try, and imprison the President himself for his official actions. At a minimum, the President must therefore be immune from prosecution for an official act unless the Government can show that applying a criminal prohibition to that act would pose no “dangers of intrusion on the authority and functions of the Executive Branch.” <em>Fitzgerald,</em> 457 U. S., at 754.</p>
     <p>But as we explain below, the current stage of the proceedings in this case does not require us to decide whether this immunity is presumptive or absolute</p>
    </blockquote>
    <p><em>From Opinion of the Court, <strong>John Roberts</strong>, p. 17:</em></p>
    <blockquote>
     <p>In dividing official from unofficial conduct, courts may not inquire into the President’s motives.</p>
    </blockquote>
    <p><em>From Opinion of the Court, <strong>John Roberts</strong>, p. 17:</em></p>
    <blockquote>
     <p>Nor may courts deem an action unofficial merely because it allegedly violates a generally applicable law.</p>
    </blockquote>
    <p><em>From Opinion of the Court, <strong>John Roberts</strong>, pp. 20-21:</em></p>
    <blockquote>
     <p>the Executive Branch has “exclusive authority and absolute discretion” to decide which crimes to investigate and prosecute, including with respect to allegations of election crime. <em>Nixon,</em> 418 U. S., at 693; see <em>United States</em> v. <em>Texas</em>, 599 U. S. 670, 678–679 (2023) (“Under Article II, the Executive Branch possesses authority to decide ‘how to prioritize and how aggressively to pursue legal actions against defendants who violate the law.’” (quoting <em>TransUnion LLC</em> v. <em>Ramirez</em>, 594 U. S. 413, 429 (2021))). The President may discuss potential investigations and prosecutions with his Attorney General and other Justice Department officials to carry out his constitutional duty to “take Care that the Laws be faithfully executed.” Art. II, §3. And the Attorney General, as head of the Justice Department, acts as the President’s “chief law enforcement officer” who “provides vital assistance to [him] in the performance of [his] constitutional duty to ‘preserve, protect, and defend the Constitution.’” <em>Mitchell</em> v. <em>Forsyth</em>, 472 U. S. 511, 520 (1985) (quoting Art. II, §1, cl. 8).</p>
     <p>Investigative and prosecutorial decisionmaking is “the special province of the Executive Branch,” <em>Heckler</em> v. <em>Chaney</em>, 470 U. S. 821, 832 (1985), and the Constitution vests the entirety of the executive power in the President, Art. II, §1. For that reason, Trump’s threatened removal of the Acting Attorney General likewise implicates “conclusive and preclusive” Presidential authority. As we have explained, the President’s power to remove “executive officers of the United States whom he has appointed” may not be regulated by Congress or reviewed by the courts. Myers, 272 U. S., at 106, 176; see supra, at 8. The President’s “management of the Executive Branch” requires him to have “unrestricted power to remove the most important of his subordinates”—such as the Attorney General—“in their most important duties.” <em>Fitzgerald,</em> 457 U. S., at 750 (internal quotation marks and alteration omitted).</p>
     <p>The indictment’s allegations that the requested investigations were “sham[s]” or proposed for an improper purpose do not divest the President of exclusive authority over the investigative and prosecutorial functions of the Justice Department and its officials. App. 186–187, Indictment ¶10(c). And the President cannot be prosecuted for conduct within his exclusive constitutional authority. Trump is therefore absolutely immune from prosecution for the alleged conduct involving his discussions with Justice Department officials.</p>
    </blockquote>
    <p><em>From Opinion of the Court, <strong>John Roberts</strong>, p. 31:</em></p>
    <blockquote>
     <p>If official conduct for which the President is immune may be scrutinized to help secure his conviction, even on charges that purport to be based only on his unofficial conduct, the “intended effect” of immunity would be defeated. Fitzgerald, 457 U. S., at 756. The President’s immune conduct would be subject to examination by a jury on the basis of generally applicable criminal laws. Use of evidence about such conduct, even when an indictment alleges only unofficial conduct, would thereby heighten the prospect that the President’s official decisionmaking will be distorted. See <em>Clinton,</em> 520 U. S., at 694, n. 19.</p>
    </blockquote>
    <p><em>From Opinion of the Court, <strong>John Roberts</strong>, p. 37:</em></p>
    <blockquote>
     <p>We do not ordinarily decline to decide significant constitutional questions based on the Government’s promises of good faith. See <em>United States</em> v. <em>Stevens</em>, 559 U. S. 460, 480 (2010) (“We would not uphold an unconstitutional statute merely because the Government promised to use it responsibly.”). Nor do we do so today.</p>
    </blockquote>
    <p><em>From Opinion of the Court, <strong>John Roberts</strong>, p. 40:</em></p>
    <blockquote>
     <p>The dissents’ positions in the end boil down to ignoring the Constitution’s separation of powers and the Court’s precedent and instead fear mongering on the basis of extreme hypotheticals about a future where the President “feels empowered to violate federal criminal law.” <em>Post,</em> at 18 (opinion of SOTOMAYOR, J.); see <em>post,</em> at 26, 29–30; <em>post,</em> at 8–9, 10, 12, 16, 20–21 (opinion of JACKSON, J.). The dissents overlook the more likely prospect of an Executive Branch that cannibalizes itself, with each successive President free to prosecute his predecessors, yet unable to boldly and fearlessly carry out his duties for fear that he may be next.</p>
    </blockquote>
    <p><em>From Opinion of the Court, <strong>John Roberts</strong>, p. 42:</em></p>
    <blockquote>
     <p>The judgment of the Court of Appeals for the D. C. Circuit is vacated</p>
    </blockquote>
    <hr>
    <h3><a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/07/19/trump-v-united-states-greatest-hits/#excerpts-from-clarence-thomas-concurring" id="excerpts-from-clarence-thomas-concurring" name="excerpts-from-clarence-thomas-concurring" class="anchorlink"></a>Excerpts from Clarence Thomas, concurring</h3>
    <p><em>From <strong>Clarence Thomas</strong>, concurring, p. 8:</em></p>
    <blockquote>
     <p>In this case, there has been much discussion about ensuring that a President “is not above the law.” But, as the Court explains, the President’s immunity from prosecution for his official acts is the law.</p>
    </blockquote>
    <hr>
    <h3><a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/07/19/trump-v-united-states-greatest-hits/#excerpts-from-amy-coney-barrett-concurring-in-part" id="excerpts-from-amy-coney-barrett-concurring-in-part" name="excerpts-from-amy-coney-barrett-concurring-in-part" class="anchorlink"></a>Excerpts from Amy Coney Barrett, concurring in part</h3>
    <p><em>From <strong>Amy Coney Barrett</strong>, concurring in part, p. 6:</em></p>
    <blockquote>
     <p>The Constitution does not require blinding juries to the circumstances surrounding conduct for which Presidents can be held liable. Consider a bribery prosecution—a charge not at issue here but one that provides a useful example. The federal bribery statute forbids any public official to seek or accept a thing of value “for or because of any official act.” 18 U. S. C. §201(c). The Constitution, of course, does not authorize a President to seek or accept bribes, so the Government may prosecute him if he does so. See Art. II, §4 (listing “Bribery” as an impeachable offense); see also Memorandum from L. Silberman, Deputy Atty. Gen., to R. Burress, Office of the President, Re: Conflict of Interest Problems Arising Out of the President’s Nomination of Nelson A. Rockefeller To Be Vice President Under the Twenty-Fifth Amendment to the Constitution 5 (Aug. 28, 1974) (suggesting that the federal bribery statute applies to the President). Yet excluding from trial any mention of the official act connected to the bribe would hamstring the prosecution. To make sense of charges alleging a <em>quid pro quo</em>, the jury must be allowed to hear about both the <em>quid</em> and the <em>quo</em>, even if the quo, standing alone, could not be a basis for the President’s criminal liability.</p>
    </blockquote>
    <hr>
    <h3><a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/07/19/trump-v-united-states-greatest-hits/#excerpts-from-sonia-sotomayor-dissenting" id="excerpts-from-sonia-sotomayor-dissenting" name="excerpts-from-sonia-sotomayor-dissenting" class="anchorlink"></a>Excerpts from Sonia Sotomayor, dissenting</h3>
    <p><em>From <strong>Sonia Sotomayor</strong>, dissenting, pp. 10-11:</em></p>
    <blockquote>
     <p>The majority purports to keep us in suspense as to whether this immunity is absolute or presumptive, but it quickly gives up the game. It explains that, “[a]t a minimum, the President must . . . be immune from prosecution for an official act unless the Government can show that applying a criminal prohibition to that act would pose no ‘dangers of intrusion on the authority and functions of the Executive Branch.’” <em>Ibid.</em> (emphasis added). No dangers, none at all. It is hard to imagine a criminal prosecution for a President’s official acts that would pose no dangers of intrusion on Presidential authority in the majority’s eyes.</p>
    </blockquote>
    <hr>
    <p><em>From <strong>Sonia Sotomayor</strong>, dissenting, p. 12:</em></p>
    <blockquote>
     <p>the majority’s dividing line between “official” and “unofficial” conduct narrows the conduct considered “unofficial” almost to a nullity. It says that whenever the President acts in a way that is “‘not manifestly or palpably beyond [his] authority,’” he is taking official action. <em>Ante,</em> at 17 (quoting <em>Blassingame</em> v. <em>Trump</em>, 87 F. 4th 1, 13 (CADC 2023)). It then goes a step further: “In dividing official from unofficial conduct, courts may not inquire into the President’s motives.” <em>Ante,</em> at 18. It is one thing to say that motive is irrelevant to questions regarding the scope of civil liability, but it is quite another to make it irrelevant to questions regarding criminal liability. Under that rule, any use of official power for any purpose, even the most corrupt purpose indicated by objective evidence of the most corrupt motives and intent, remains official and immune. Under the majority’s test, if it can be called a test, the category of Presidential action that can be deemed “unofficial” is destined to be vanishingly small.</p>
    </blockquote>
    <p><em>From <strong>Sonia Sotomayor</strong>, dissenting, pp. 29-30:</em></p>
    <blockquote>
     <p>Looking beyond the fate of this particular prosecution, the long-term consequences of today’s decision are stark. The Court effectively creates a law-free zone around the President, upsetting the status quo that has existed since the Founding. This new official-acts immunity now “lies about like a loaded weapon” for any President that wishes to place his own interests, his own political survival, or his own financial gain, above the interests of the Nation. <em>Korematsu</em> v. <em>United States</em>, 323 U. S. 214, 246 (1944) (Jackson, J., dissenting). The President of the United States is the most powerful person in the country, and possibly the world. When he uses his official powers in any way, under the majority’s reasoning, he now will be insulated from criminal prosecution. Orders the Navy’s Seal Team 6 to assassinate a political rival? Immune. Organizes a military coup to hold onto power? Immune. Takes a bribe in exchange for a pardon? Immune. Immune, immune, immune.</p>
     <p>Let the President violate the law, let him exploit the trappings of his office for personal gain, let him use his official power for evil ends. Because if he knew that he may one day face liability for breaking the law, he might not be as bold and fearless as we would like him to be. That is the majority’s message today.</p>
    </blockquote>
    <p><em>From <strong>Sonia Sotomayor</strong>, dissenting, p. 30:</em></p>
    <blockquote>
     <p>With fear for our democracy, I dissent</p>
    </blockquote>
    <hr>
    <h3><a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/07/19/trump-v-united-states-greatest-hits/#excerpts-from-ketanji-brown-jackson-dissenting" id="excerpts-from-ketanji-brown-jackson-dissenting" name="excerpts-from-ketanji-brown-jackson-dissenting" class="anchorlink"></a>Excerpts from Ketanji Brown Jackson, dissenting</h3>
    <p><em>From <strong>Ketanji Brown Jackson</strong>, dissenting, pp. 9-10:</em></p>
    <blockquote>
     <p>Immunity can issue for Presidents under the majority’s model even for unquestionably and intentionally egregious criminal behavior. Regardless of the nature or the impact of the President’s criminal conduct, so long as he is committing crimes “pursuant to the powers invested exclusively in him by the Constitution,” <em>ante</em>, at 7, or as needed “to carry out his constitutional duties without undue caution,” <em>ante</em>, at 14, he is likely to be deemed immune from prosecution.</p>
     <p>Ultimately, the majority’s model simply sets the criminal law to one side when it comes to crimes allegedly committed by the President. Before accountability can be sought or rendered, the Judiciary serves as a newfound special gatekeeper, charged not merely with interpreting the law but with policing whether it applies to the President <em>at all</em>. Also, under the new Presidential accountability model, the starting presumption is that the criminal law does <em>not</em> apply to Presidents, no matter how obviously illegal, harmful, or unacceptable a President’s official behavior might be. Regardless of all that, courts must now ensure that a former President is <em>not</em> held accountable for any criminal conduct he engages in while he is on duty, unless his conduct consists primarily (and perhaps solely) of unofficial acts.</p>
    </blockquote>
    <p><em>From <strong>Ketanji Brown Jackson</strong>, dissenting, p. 10:</em></p>
    <blockquote>
     <p>To fully appreciate the oddity of making the criminal immunity determination turn on the character of the President’s responsibilities, consider what the majority says is one of the President’s “conclusive and preclusive” prerogatives: “ ‘[t]he President’s power to remove . . . those who wield executive power on his behalf.’ ” <em>Ante,</em> at 8 (quoting <em>Seila Law LLC</em> v. <em>Consumer Financial Protection Bureau</em>, 591 U. S. 197, 204 (2020)). While the President may have the authority to decide to remove the Attorney General, for example, the question here is whether the President has the option to remove the Attorney General by, say, poisoning him to death. Put another way, the issue here is not whether the President has exclusive removal power, but whether a generally applicable criminal law prohibiting murder can restrict how the President exercises that authority.</p>
    </blockquote>
    <p><em>From <strong>Ketanji Brown Jackson</strong>, dissenting, p. 11:</em></p>
    <blockquote>
     <p>under the individual accountability model, an indicted former President can raise an affirmative defense just like any other criminal defendant. This means that the President remains answerable to the law, insofar as he must show that he was justified in committing a criminal act while in office under the given circumstances. In other words, while the President might indeed be privileged to commit a crime in the course of his official duties, any such privilege exists only when the People (acting either through their elected representatives or as members of a jury) determine that the former President’s conduct was in fact justified, notwithstanding the general criminal prohibition.</p>
     <p>Under the majority’s immunity regime, by contrast, the President can commit crimes in the course of his job even under circumstances <em>in which no one thinks he has any excuse</em>; the law simply does not apply to him. Unlike a defendant who invokes an affirmative defense and relies on a legal determination that there was a good reason for his otherwise unlawful conduct, a former President invoking immunity relies on the premise that he can do whatever he wants, however he wants, so long as he uses his “‘official power’” in doing so. <em>Ante,</em> at 19. In the former paradigm, the President remains subject to law; in the latter, he is above it.</p>
    </blockquote>
    <p><em>From <strong>Ketanji Brown Jackson</strong>, dissenting, pp. 13-14:</em></p>
    <blockquote>
     <p>whatever additional power the majority’s new Presidential accountability model gives to the Presidency, it gives doubly to the Court itself, for the majority provides no meaningful guidance about how to apply this new paradigm or how to categorize a President’s conduct. For instance, its opinion lists some examples of the “core” constitutional powers with respect to which the President is now entitled to absolute immunity—a list that apparently includes the removal power, the power to recognize foreign nations, and the pardon power. <em>Ante,</em> at 6–9. However, the majority does not—and likely cannot—supply any useful or administrable definition of the scope of that “core.” For what it’s worth, the Constitution’s text is no help either; Article II does not contain a Core Powers Clause. So the actual metes and bounds of the “core” Presidential powers are really anyone’s guess.</p>
     <p>Nor does the majority explain how to consistently distinguish between official and unofficial acts. Quite the opposite, in fact. While acknowledging that this is a critical line that courts must draw in order for its new accountability model to work properly, the majority simultaneously cautions that making this distinction “can be difficult”—likely a gross understatement given the recognized “breadth of the President’s ‘discretionary responsibilities’ under the Constitution and laws of the United States.” <em>Ante,</em> at 17.</p>
    </blockquote>
    <p><em>From <strong>Ketanji Brown Jackson</strong>, dissenting, p. 15:</em></p>
    <blockquote>
     <p>while Congress (the branch of our Government most accountable to the People) is the entity our Constitution tasks with deciding, as a general matter, what conduct is on or off limits, the Court has now arrogated that power unto itself when that question pertains to the President. In essence, the Court has now imposed its own preclearance requirement on the application of Congress’s laws to a former President alleged to have committed crimes while in office. Who will be responsible for drawing the crucial “‘line between [the President’s] personal and official affairs’”? <em>Ante,</em> at 29. To ask the question is to know the answer. A majority of this Court, applying an indeterminate test, will pick and choose which laws apply to which Presidents, by labeling his various allegedly criminal acts as “core,” “official,” or “manifestly or palpably” beyond the President’s authority.</p>
    </blockquote>
   </div>
  </div>
  <div class="entry-footer">
   <div class="post-metainfo">
    <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/07/19/trump-v-united-states-greatest-hits/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b>
    <br>
     2024-07-19 @ 08:05 PM EDT
   </div>
  </div>
 </div><!-- entry-header-body-footer -->
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
