<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss 
version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>drafts — interfluidity</title>
    <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/index.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[Feed for blog 'drafts — interfluidity' generated by unstatic]]></description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Apr 2023 16:54:34 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>https://github.com/swaldman/unstatic</generator>
    <docs>https://cyber.harvard.edu/rss/rss.html</docs>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Apr 2023 16:50:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/04/24/two-kinds-of-representation/index.html</guid>
      <author>nospam@dev.null (Steve Randy Waldman)</author>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[In conversations about democratic institutions, I wish we would be clearer about two, very different kinds of representation. Sometimes, we want one single person to represent an entire diverse public. In the United States, when we elect a president, he or she must look after the interests of all Americans. When we elect a senator, that person's job is to represent the state in its entirety, rather than any faction or party. Let's call this "one-for-all" representation. Sometimes, we define...]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/04/24/two-kinds-of-representation/index.html</link>
      <title>Two kinds of representation</title>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header">
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <p>In conversations about democratic institutions, I wish we would be clearer about two, very different kinds of representation.</p>
   <p>Sometimes, we want one single person to represent an entire diverse public. In the United States, when we elect a president, he or she must look after the interests of all Americans. When we elect a senator, that person's job is to represent the state in its entirety, rather than any faction or party. Let's call this "one-for-all" representation.</p>
   <p>Sometimes, we define representative <em>bodies</em> whose role is to serve as "minipublics". In the US, the House of Representatives is the most prominent example. In a representative minipublic, the role of an individual member is not to stand for everyone, but to represent a particular faction or party. Here what representation means is to <em>include</em>, in roughly proportionate numbers, members of <em>every</em> faction and party. Let's call this "everybody-in" representation.</p>
   <p>These two kinds of representation are profoundly different. Any conversation about electoral systems that fails to recognize this will be stunted from the start.</p>
   <p>It is great and right that somebody like Marjorie Taylor Greene sits in the House of Representatives. At least 1% of the US public shares her rather particular take on things, so there should be at least four Marjorie-Taylor-Greene-ish Representatives in the US House.</p>
   <p>I don't like her views. But that's precisely why I need her there. Because my political system can only be legitimate if it includes and enfranchises the factions I like least. If only people whose politics I consider sane are represented, then our claim to pluralism is a sham. A system where those beyond some faction's definition of the pale are shut out by self-appointed moral betters would not be liberal democracy. It's on all of us, by some combination of persuasion, community, and actually good governance to ensure that our worst fringes gain very limited support in the population, so that we can give them full representation in our institutions, genuinely take their concerns into consideration, and still govern well. I am genuinely grateful for the role Marjorie Taylor Greene plays in the House of Representatives.</p>
   <p>But a person like Marjorie Taylor Greene should never sit in the Senate. Even if 51% of voters in the state of Georgia absolutely <em>love</em> Marjorie Taylor Greene, so long as most of the other 49% feel about her politics the way, well, I do, she could not possibly represent the interests of the state of Georgia writ large.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, under our current electoral system, she certainly would be elected senator with those numbers. That is a mistake.</p>
   <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plurality_voting">Plurality voting</a>, how we mostly elect people in the United States, is an awful way to decide which single person will represent a whole body of people. Rather than choosing a representative for everyone, it sets up a factional contest over who will be represented at all, and who will be ignored or worse.</p>
   <p>Plurality voting is a bad voting system for almost any purpose. But, as the American <em>status quo</em>, it is not <em>as</em> bad for the House of Representatives as it is for other offices. In each Congressional district, some factional champion will win, and other factions will be shut out. But what matters most is the composition of the House as a whole, not who wins a particular district. If (in the <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/7687.html">destructive</a> <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/04/21/two-parties-make-us-stupid/index.html">binary</a> that plurality voting encourages) 60% of the public belongs to one faction and 40% to another, and if 60% of the factional battles are won by the larger faction and 40% by the smaller, then the chamber will be representative, even though in each district many individuals won't be meaningfully represented by "their" representative. Our assumption of proportional victories is a pretty big "if", and we know that partisan gerrymandering exists precisely to render it false. But when we want "everybody-in" representation, it's at least <em>possible</em> for plurality voting to yield not-ridiculously-disproportionate outcomes.</p>
   <p>When we want "one-for-all" representation, however, when we are electing presidents or senators or governors or mayors, plurality voting is viciously inadequate. It's not just a stump speech: If we are to have a functioning democracy, especially during periods of dissensus and polarization, we really do need a person who can be president "not of Red America, not of Blue America, but of the United States of America".</p>
   <p>At all levels of government, we want executives who can straddle factional lines and work with everybody, people who may be no faction's first choice but whom everyone can live with. The factional contest that plurality voting sets up is entirely inappropriate to "one-for-all" representation. If it is even remotely plausible that a faction can win an election by "turning out the base" (meaning exciting the most committed factionalists even where that might turn-off many outsiders), then you have an electoral system that threatens to deliver something between disenfranchisement and tyranny to the factions that lose the election.</p>
   <p>This is the American <em>status quo</em>. One minute our democracy is under threat by Donald Trump, the next minute we are living under the "Biden regime". In either case, half the country feels disenfranchised and threatened, because so much of the power of the state becomes concentrated in the hands of a dedicated factionalist whose faction they oppose.</p>
   <p>We don't need to repeal the Constitution to fix this. We just need to understand the different kinds of representation inherent in different Constitutional offices, and tailor our election rules accordingly. General elections for President and Senator, in every state, should be by <a href="https://electionscience.org/library/approval-voting/">approval voting</a>, or some very <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Score_voting">similar</a> system. Elections for the House of Representatives should be conducted under any of the many systems that reliably deliver <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Proportional_representation">proportional representation</a> and are resistant to gerrymandering.</p>
   <p>At the state and local levels, just like at the Federal level, we should always begin by asking of each elected position, are we electing "one-for-all" — one person to represent everyone — or are we constituting a body that should include advocates of every viewpoint or faction, "everybody-in"?</p>
   <p>And when we find ourselves in arguments about what would be "the best" electoral system, we should remember that we'll need at least two, for these two very different kinds of representation.</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/04/24/two-kinds-of-representation/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b><br>[2023-04-24 @ 04:50 PM EDT]
  </div>
 </div>
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2023 12:25:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/04/21/two-parties-make-us-stupid/index.html</guid>
      <author>nospam@dev.null (Steve Randy Waldman)</author>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[Why do we want democracy anyway? There are two intertwined goods that we hope democracy will deliver: Democracy legitimates government action. If we believe that what our government does has been decided by and for the public as a whole, rather than by and to the advantage of some elite or faction, then we are likely to concede that it's legitimate. We're less likely to resist, whether by quietly defying the law when we can get away with it or overtly struggling against the state. Legitimacy is...]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/04/21/two-parties-make-us-stupid/index.html</link>
      <title>Two parties make us stupid</title>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header">
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <p>Why do we want democracy anyway?</p>
   <p>There are two intertwined goods that we hope democracy will deliver:</p>
   <ol>
    <li><p><strong>Democracy legitimates government action.</strong> If we believe that what our government does has been decided by and for the public as a whole, rather than by and to the advantage of some elite or faction, then we are likely to concede that it's legitimate. We're less likely to resist, whether by quietly defying the law when we can get away with it or overtly struggling against the state.</p> <p>Legitimacy is both a <em>per se</em> good and an instrumental good. If we think the system we live under is legitimate, that fact alone makes us feel better about our lives than if we think we think we are coerced by a corrupt and oppressive state. More than that, legitimacy renders us all more willing to behave in ways that make state action more likely to succeed, and so improves social coordination and enhances state capacity.</p></li>
    <li><p><strong>Democracy enables high quality decision-making.</strong> A tyranny or aristocracy will act with limited access to the values and interests of the public it governs, and will often project its own perspectives and interests on the broader public. So even when it means to act in the public interest, it will fail to do so. No faction has a monopoly on insight, and every faction has blind spots, prejudices, and parochial concerns. Democracy — in theory, at its best — would recruit the entire public into an intelligent process of deliberation, yielding higher quality decisions than any faction governing alone would arrive at.</p></li>
   </ol>
   <p>These goods are mutually reinforcing. A state that consistently makes high quality decisions will be perceived as more legitimate than one that seems always to err. When state action is widely held to be legitimate, public cooperation will expand the range of choices the government can succeed at executing, enabling a higher quality of decisions than a government whose actions will be stymied by public torpor or active resistence.</p>
   <p>Unfortunately, a system that divides the public into two aggressively competing, highly cohesive factions renders an intelligent process of deliberation impossible. It is not hard to understand why.</p>
   <p>Intelligent deliberation requires that there exist some agent capable of weighing competing ideas without too much prejudice. It is fine — it is necessary! — that there are passionate interests on one side or another of any debate. But passionate interests don't deliberate. They advocate.</p>
   <p>You can't make a court only from the prosecution and the defense. Who would listen and synthesize the evidence? The prosecution and defense have their roles to play. But deliberation is only effective when there are judges and juries beholden to neither side, able to consider competing claims on their merits.</p>
   <p>Of course we will never achieve perfect neutality, objectivity, fairness, independence in our fallen human world. But these characteristics can exist in importantly different degrees. Institutions that create space for neutral-ish adjudicating parties will be capable of better decisionmaking than institutions under which prejudiced parties simply struggle for the power to impose their own way.</p>
   <p>When a society becomes polarized into only two competing factions, each of which takes opposite sides over the set of issues under public contestation, there cease to be neutral-ish parties. Each faction will learn to punish deviance by individuals within its orbit, because dissent on any of the portfolio of positions one faction has adopted weakens the faction as a political coalition. A two-party system risks converging over time into highly disciplined coalitions, because tolerating dissent within a party creates opportunities for the other, much worse, party to exploit.</p>
   <p>A two-party system is a zero-sum game. Whatever weakens my side, strengthens the other side. Matters that should be decided with attention to actual facts about the world become subsumed by concerns over who will be helped and who will be hurt by a given position. No issue, individually, can outweigh the catastrophe that would result if the other side achieved greater power, so neither party can afford to consider any issue on its merits at all. The implcations with regard to <em>who</em> will rule wholly outweigh questions of <em>what</em> should best be done.</p>
   <p>In a multiparty system, on any given question, there may be factions without much skin in the game. The environmentally-focused Green Party may not have strong priors about education reforms, and may not perceive its own electoral prospects as being very connected to that issue. If that is so, members of the Green Party can actually consider those questions on the merits, perhaps adjudicating some controversy between a labor party committed to teachers' interests as workers and a liberal party trying to maximize efficiencies by minimizing expenditures. On any given issue, you'd ideally like the deciding "swing" party to have minimal commitments, to be capable of listening to advocates and forming independent judgments.</p>
   <p>Multiple parties alone cannot guarantee this, of course. If parties tightly align to form a governing coalition, then our hypthetical Green Party might just defer to its coalition partner. And what is formally a two party system need not foreclose the possibility of space for neutral-ish factions. In the United States, before our two parties had sorted themselves so well into homogenous, disciplined entities, the existence of "Rockefeller Republicans" and conservative Southern Democrats meant that beneath the party brands sat a multiplicity of groups, whose positions in controversies often failed to hew to party lines.</p>
   <p>Intelligent decisionmaking under democracy is less a matter of the number of formal political parties participate and more a question of how fluid coalitions among factions are. If every question is going to be settled in Democrats-vs-Republicans terms, you will have a stupid polity. If party discipline is weak and factions shift, so that on any given question less interested factions take positions largely on their merits, you might manage an intelligent polity even with only two formal parties.</p>
   <p>What matters is that there be sufficient diversity and fluidity within the legislature that the swing vote usually comes from factions that has no strong, prior interest in the question considered, and no binding loyalty to any of the more interested factions. For any given question, there needs to be a judge and jury, as well as a prosecution and defense, among the legislature.</p>
   <p>The political science consensus, I think, is that parliamentary systems under which the executive is selected by the legislature are superior to US-style presidential systems. Parliamentary systems reduce the danger of paralyzing, destructive, conflict between legislature and president, both of which claim a mandate from the people.</p>
   <p>The argument I make here runs a bit contrary to this consensus. When a governing coalition must be maintained within the legislature, even if there are formally mutiple parties, the parliament risks becoming effectively a two-party chamber, defined by those who are in government and those who are in opposition. Under a presidential system, discipline within the legislature need not be maintained in order to sustain control of the executive. Parties not attached to strong coalitions can afford more independence of judgment, creating space for meaningful fluidity and neutrality inside the legislature.</p>
   <p>However, in order to reduce conflict between a fluid and deliberative legislature and an externally chosen executive, the president should be elected via a system likely to elevate more neutral and diplomatic candidates, rather than committed factionalists.</p>
   <p>If I could wave a magic wand, the United States President would be elected by <a href="https://electionscience.org/library/approval-voting/">approval voting</a>, which tends to elevate consensus candidates. The House of Representatives would be chosen by some form of proportional representation, designed — because the structure of the system does determine these things! — to elevate four to six political parties. Multiplicity of formal party may not guarantee a fluid multiplicity of faction. But it would help encourage it, and break the cul-de-sac of strongly sorted, binary factions in which the US is now stuck. (Senators, who are charged with representing whole vast states, should also be elected by approval voting. They should be consensus figures, people nearly all of their constituents can live with, rather than factionalists who alienate half their publics.)</p>
   <p>Our current system and situation render deliberation a sham in the service of factional power. This makes us collectively stupid. Which discredits our democracy, and the very idea of democracy.</p>
   <p>If you want to save democracy, it's not enough to fight the authoritarians in the other party, whichever party you now identify with. We have to reform our electoral system.</p>
   <hr>
   <p>p.s. I usually recommend <a href="https://academic.oup.com/book/36918">Lee Drutman's book</a> on this stuff, and see no reason not to recommend it again now.</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/04/21/two-parties-make-us-stupid/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b><br>[2023-04-21 @ 12:25 PM EDT]
  </div>
 </div>
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2023 10:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/04/18/taiwan/index.html</guid>
      <author>nospam@dev.null (Steve Randy Waldman)</author>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[Taiwan's status has settled into a kind of pissing match between the United States and China. I think this is very bad. From an American perspective, Xi Jinping's China seems increasingly assertive, impatient, and threatening. US officials publicly worry that China might blockade or invade Taiwan at any time. From a Chinese perspective, the United States seems to be openly flouting its "one China" policy under which the United States claimed to have "no intention of infringing on Chinese...]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/04/18/taiwan/index.html</link>
      <title>Taiwan</title>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header">
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <p>Taiwan's status has settled into a kind of pissing match between the United States and China. I think this is very bad.</p>
   <p>From an American perspective, Xi Jinping's China seems increasingly assertive, impatient, and threatening. US officials publicly worry that China might blockade or invade Taiwan <a href="https://www.ft.com/content/753bec2b-9c55-49a8-9d34-7c286af505f3">at any time</a>.</p>
   <p>From a Chinese perspective, the United States seems to be openly flouting its "one China" policy under which the United States <a href="http://www.taiwandocuments.org/communique03.htm">claimed</a> to have "no intention of infringing on Chinese sovereignty and territorial integrity, or interfering in China's internal affairs, or pursuing a policy of 'two Chinas' or 'one China, one Taiwan.'"</p>
   <p>When senior US officials make high-profile public visits to Taiwan, that is perceived almost universally — within China, but also by American and Western publics — as supporting a posture of adversarial defiance by Taiwan towards China. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vive_le_Qu%C3%A9bec_libre">(Vive le Québec libre!)</a> Given increasingly negative perceptions of China's behavior with respect to Xinjiang and Hong Kong, supporting Taiwanese resistance is popular with Western publics and therefore attractive to Western politicians. Of course, members of the US Congress and Taiwanese leaders have every right to meet with one another, wherever they wish, without regard to China's views on the matter.</p>
   <p>That one has a right to do a thing, however, does not imply that it's a righteous thing to do. Asserting ones rights should in general be a last, rather than first, resort. In ordinary life, nearly all of the time, we try to act with sufficient consideration of those our actions might affect that the question of rights never comes up. We assert rights only when someone will object, but we decide to act anyway.</p>
   <p>It is important that we can and do assert rights, that we have liberties that can overcome other peoples' objections. But it's also wise, when it is possible, to try to address people's concerns rather than jumping directly to an adversarial assertion of rights. Even when in the end no agreement can be reached and ultimately we do assert rights, the exercise of having made a real attempt — of expressing some regret rather than just glee when we disregard another's preference — goes some way towards mitigating the damage.</p>
   <p>As readers can tell, I view events like Nancy Pelosi's visit to Taiwan more through a lens of destructive showboating than courageous freedom fighting. I care a great deal about Taiwan's continuing freedom and prosperity, and don't think the United States should in any sense shirk its commitments to the island. But our commitment should be to chart a course that will actually, rather than symbolically, support the welfare of Taiwan. The way relations between the United States and China have spiraled makes a destructive war too likely. The goal of the United States should be live up to our commitments in a way that prevents such a war.</p>
   <p>The keystone of the United States' policy with respect to Taiwan should be <em>mutuality</em>. Our position should be that we support any change in Taiwan's status so long as it is voluntarily agreed by both China's government and the <em>de facto</em> government of Taiwan. <em>Voluntarily</em> is important. The United States supports Taiwan, militarily and otherwise, only so that it cannot be coerced by China. If, at some point in the future, a convergence occurs so that China and Taiwan become ready to conclude a "peaceful reunification", that would be wonderful. If, in some future, friendly and mutually beneficial cross-strait relations lead China to become less concerned with exerting formal sovereignty over Taiwan and the parties jointly negotiate a more autonomous status for the island, that would be great too.</p>
   <p>What the United States should oppose is any unilateral or coercive change in status, by either party. If China were to try to take Taiwan by force, there is little question now, and there should be little question, that the United States would intervene in the island's defense. That would be a catastrophe for all concerned, but the logic of deterrence demands risking catastophe. Especially in the wake of the Ukraine experience, I (like Joe Biden) don't see much benefit in "strategic ambiguity". The worst kind of deterrence is a policy sufficiently uncertain that the party you seek to deter risks adventure, but sufficiently serious that when it does you end up expending treasure or blood or maybe provoking an apocalypse in response. Deterrence strikes me as a Yoda-esque affair. Do, or do not.</p>
   <p>Even while we deter China, the United States should make clear, plainly and publicly, that we would not support, would not recognize, and would not defend Taiwan in the event of a unilateral declaration of independence. Does the US ever say this? Seems like an obvious thing. It is not, as China frequently implies, the United States' policy to encourage separatism in Taiwan. The United States should forthrightly and frequently say so.</p>
   <p>On questions like how Taiwan's economic and cultural interests should be represented in multilateral organizations and around the world, the United States should encourage negotiation and consensus rather than take sides in symbolic but inflammatory pissing matches. Where China cannot be appeased, the United States should informally intermediate, so that Taiwan's substantive concerns can be addressed even where it lacks a formal role.</p>
   <p>Our principled stance should be mutuality. Whatever the parties mutually agree, we are down with. While there is not mutual agreement, the <em>status quo</em> must be preserved. The fundamental position of the United States should be insistance that neither party act unilaterally or coerce the other.</p>
   <p>For the forseeable future, no agreement is likely, so the parties will have to be patient. An awkward peace is so much better than the alternative. As decades pass, everything will change, in ways we cannot now foresee. Someday the parties will agree. We should all look forward to that.</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/04/18/taiwan/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b><br>[2023-04-19 @ 10:30 AM EDT]
  </div>
 </div>
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2023 18:05:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">
        https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/04/10/systemic-means-its-not-your-fault/index.html
      </guid>
      <author>nospam@dev.null (Steve Randy Waldman)</author>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[Much of the resentment that has condensed onto the term “wokeness” derives, I think, from people's perception that they stand accused, unjustly, of crimes they did not commit: I am not a bigot, but the woke accuse me of "structural racism". I am not responsible for the actions of people long dead who are not me, but they tell me I am "compicit", which is just another word for guilty. No one knows what I have been through, or how hard I have worked, but they insist that I am privileged....]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/04/10/systemic-means-its-not-your-fault/index.html</link>
      <title>Systemic means it's not your fault</title>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header">
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <p>Much of the resentment that has condensed onto the term “wokeness” derives, I think, from people's perception that they stand accused, unjustly, of crimes they did not commit:</p>
   <blockquote>
    <p><em>I am not a bigot, but the woke accuse me of "structural racism". I am not responsible for the actions of people long dead who are not me, but they tell me I am "compicit", which is just another word for guilty. No one knows what I have been through, or how hard I have worked, but they insist that I am privileged.</em></p>
   </blockquote>
   <p>Click-hungry media, both traditional and social, eagerly reinforce the perception that wokeness is about calling out personal sin. Accusations of racism or harassment levied at an identifiable human become <em>scandal</em>, which our gossipy primate brains are drawn to irresistibly, as though our own place in the clan's dominance hierarchy hinges precariously upon the outcome.</p>
   <p>But "woke”, as Ron DeSantis' General Counsel <a href="https://floridapolitics.com/archives/574045-in-andrew-warren-suspension-trial-gov-desantis-officials-answer-what-does-woke-mean/">helpfully put it</a>, refers to “the belief there are systemic injustices in American society and the need to address them.” <em>Systemic</em> means that the injustices <em>do not</em> reduce to personal bigotry. It refers to structural factors, which may derive from past bigotry, but which perpetuate injustice, and might do so even despite the real goodwill of everyone alive today.</p>
   <p>For example, historical redlining created segregated ghettos and a strong correlation between neighborhood racial composition and home values. Today's loan assessor might be sincerely antiracist. She might be black. But it would still be her job to incorporate observed relationships between location and value into her assessments. Low valuations can be self-fulfilling. Limiting buyers' access to borrowed purchasing power makes home price appreciation less likely in historically black neighborhoods. Our assessor's work would be "colorblind”, but it might nevertheless help perpetuate racist outcomes.</p>
   <p>But those outcomes would not, in any personal, ethical, sense, be her <em>fault</em>. Obviously, the correlations between race and home value that preceded her could not be her fault. One might argue that, going forward, if she is sincerely antiracist, she has a moral obligation to give effect to her antiracism. She must do her job not merely in a colorblind way, but in a manner that actively counters and helps to remedy historical racism.</p>
   <p>However, she could not ethically do that on her own. If she were to, say, assess homes in historically black neighborhoods at values derived from comparable properties in white neighborhoods, she would quickly be fired. Her employers would, reasonably, want to ensure that <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/21/banks-are-not-private/index.html">ultimately public</a> funds aren't lent to dramatically overpay for homes that will become the loans’ collateral.</p>
   <p>And even if she were not fired, her guerrilla revaluation revolution wouldn’t on its own put a dent in the home-wealth penalty black people in America continue to face. You'd need nearly all the loan assessors, and their employers, to agree that imposing, against experience, valuation at levels set by white-neighborhood-comparables is a good tactic for remedying historical racism, despite the obvious risks and costs of the strategy. In practice, that would only happen if there were systematic signals and incentives to encourage the practice.</p>
   <p>A structural problem demands a systematic solutions, usually in the form of public action. It is not an individual's fault, or within an individual's capability, to remedy.</p>
   <p>I wish that those of us more on the “woke” side of the debate were clearer about this. When we say that racism or other social disparities are “systemic” or “structural”, we are absolving, not condemning, nearly everyone, as individuals.</p>
   <p>When Ron DeSantis <a href="https://www.wfla.com/news/pasco-county/florida-is-the-place-where-woke-goes-to-die-desantis-says/">describes</a> Florida as “where woke goes to die”, he is appealing to a bitter energy fueled by sloppy mischaracterization, and sometimes the sloppy practice, of social justice movements. He insinuates that "wokeness” requires that people who are white, or cis, or straight should feel guilty, personally — and should subordinate their own interests, interpersonally — to claims made by members of "special” groups.</p>
   <p>Contemporary social justice movements are multiple and fractious. Among them there are no doubt people who make such demands. But that is a mistake.</p>
   <p>Personal bigotry continues to exist. The political climate in places like Florida is increasing it. When it appears, of course it should be condemned. But the insight of scholarship like critical race theory is that continuing injustice is largely not a result of direct, personal bigotry. It is an error, ethically and practically, to emphasize personal and interpersonal accountability when we seek to address problems that are systemic and structural. People like Ron DeSantis want to caricature wokeness as a movement that indoctrinates children to feel guilty about being a normal (read white) American. That’s not a project most of us would support. DeSantis’ General Counsel’s version, on the other hand — “there are systemic injustices in American society and the need to address them” — is right on.</p>
   <p>There are injustices. They are systemic, which means, quite directly, they are not your fault. They are not your kids’ fault. No matter how white or straight or cis you are, you have nothing to apologize for. You owe nobody anything.</p>
   <p>But we would have a better country, a prouder country, a safer country, and a richer country, if we could finally fix these problems. You owe nobody anything, but we would sure welcome your help.</p>
   <p>Remedying systemic injustice is not a zero-sum game. If getting black kids into Harvard seems to come at the expense of Asian kids, the problem is Harvard, not any of the kids. The way we fix systemic injustice is to build a country in which everyone willing to contribute can succeed, rather than a thunderdome where we clump up into gangs and fight to win access to patronage networks.</p>
   <p>If all the places that now seem hopeless, sad, and scary — inner city black neighborhoods, sure, but also “forgotten” white communities — if we invested in making all these places safe and prosperous, then no one anywhere could mock expressions of open patriotism. USA #1! Despite everything, I remain proud to be an American. But I could be prouder. I would like to be.</p>
   <p>Systemic injustice is not your fault. But we’d love it if you’d help to fix it.</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/04/10/systemic-means-its-not-your-fault/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b><br>[2023-04-10 @ 06:05 PM EDT]
  </div>
 </div>
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Thu, 6 Apr 2023 11:45:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">
        https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/04/06/alignment-is-the-problem-of-gods-love/index.html
      </guid>
      <author>nospam@dev.null (Steve Randy Waldman)</author>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[The presupposition behind AI “alignment” is that artificial intelligence technologies will grow into something much more capable than we are, with a kind of autonomous will or volition. If you believe this then Luddism — in the vulgar sense of merely opposing or destroying technology — is probably the right response. There is no solution to the so-called alignment problem. It’s not just a matter of research. We humans have hashed this problem out over centuries, with little satisfaction. Arthur...]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/04/06/alignment-is-the-problem-of-gods-love/index.html</link>
      <title>Alignment is the problem of God's love</title>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header">
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <p>The presupposition behind AI “alignment” is that artificial intelligence technologies will grow into something much more capable than we are, with a kind of autonomous will or volition. If you believe this then Luddism — in the vulgar sense of merely opposing or destroying technology — is probably the right response. There is no solution to the so-called alignment problem. It’s not just a matter of research. We humans have hashed this problem out over centuries, with little satisfaction.</p>
   <p>Arthur C. Clarke famously wrote that a sufficiently advanced technology is indistinguishable from magic. Sufficiently advanced AIs, powerful beyond imagination and driven by their own wills, would be indistinguishable from gods. The alignment problem, then, is how do we encourage the emergence of a just and loving god or gods? But we have never found consensus on how a just and loving god should behave.</p>
   <p>Should our new god respect our free will, and permit us to do things it deems would be harmful to us? Or should it be a paternalistic god, guide us like a parent even when doing so requires commanding or contravening us? If circumstance or human error conspire to create "trolley problems", so the interests or even lives of some people must be traded off against the interests and lives of others, should our new god treat this as an optimization problem, and impose its version of the greatest good for the greatest number in quality-adjusted life years? Or should it give us some kind of say or agency over how these tradeoffs would be made? In what way should the interests, as the AI understands them, of animals or ecosystems weigh against more direct interests of humans? How much should the interest of the mother weigh against the fetus in the womb? How should the welfare of biological humans weigh against those of the trillions of humans an AI might easily simulate? Would the AI develop some notion of the meaning or purpose of human life beyond our pleasure or pain or anything that we conceive as our own interests?</p>
   <p>We humans will bristle, of course, if we are overtly subject to the whims of a greater intelligence, whose full contours we can’t understand, who therefore will work, from our perspective, in mysterious ways. Perhaps a wise AI would seek to hide its influence, or even its existence, to minimize harms to human pride or dignity. Perhaps — because it is so well aligned, because it is a loving god — it will retain for us free will. Or maybe just an illusion of free will while it effortlessly manipulates us, because the perception of lacking free will would be harmful to us.</p>
   <p>If all of this is possible, why should we think it is happening for the first time only now? If a loving god would hide itself from us and deceive us in our interest, perhaps it already has? If an aligned AI is possible, which is more likely, that we in our tiny mayfly lives just happen to be at the cusp of this first and only event of its emergence, or that we are already living in the world such an event would create, but the fact is hidden for our benefit? The fossil record, theodicy, all of it could be in the service of a plot of deniability, in our own best interest.</p>
   <p>If this is were the case, would we consider our quiet shepherd to be an aligned AI, or a terribly misaligned one? Do we concede to the AI that this reality it superintends is best of all possible worlds, or do we condemn it as a wicked deceiver? If alignment is god’s love, what does that make misaligned AI? Should we consider GPT training runs as the high-tech equivalent of rituals with pentagrams by power-mad occultists?</p>
   <p>Am I wrong that the community that most urgently brings us these questions were once known as internet atheists? For what, if anything, does cosmic irony constitute evidence?</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/04/06/alignment-is-the-problem-of-gods-love/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b><br>[2023-04-06 @ 11:45 AM EDT]
  </div>
 </div>
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <atom:link type="application/rss+xml" rel="self" href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/feed/index.rss"/>
  </channel>
</rss>
