<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss 
version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>drafts — interfluidity</title>
    <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/index.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[Feed for blog 'drafts — interfluidity' generated by unstatic]]></description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Mar 2024 18:36:35 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>https://github.com/swaldman/unstatic</generator>
    <docs>https://cyber.harvard.edu/rss/rss.html</docs>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Mar 2024 14:35:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">
        https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/03/20/a-simple-theory-of-the-stock-market/index.html
      </guid>
      <author>nospam@dev.null (Steve Randy Waldman)</author>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[Why has the stock market been so ebullient? Even by very forgiving measures like price-to-earnings, which presupposes extraordinary profit margins will be permanent, stocks are overvalued. The question is academic to me now. The recent rally has wiped me out, replacing my short position with a shirtless one. Still, why does valuation seem more definitively and durably than ever before simply not to matter? I present for your consideration a graph: The denominator here is "Federal Debt Held By...]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/03/20/a-simple-theory-of-the-stock-market/index.html</link>
      <title>A simple theory of the stock market</title>
      <dc:creator><![CDATA[Steve Randy Waldman]]></dc:creator>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header">
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <p>Why has the stock market been so ebullient?</p>
   <p>Even by very forgiving measures like price-to-earnings, which presupposes <a href="https://fred.stlouisfed.org/series/A466RD3Q052SBEA">extraordinary profit margins</a> will be permanent, stocks are <a href="https://twitter.com/jessefelder/status/1768625428292599882">overvalued</a>.</p>
   <p>The question is academic to me now. The recent rally has wiped me out, replacing my short position with a shirtless one. Still, why does valuation seem more definitively and durably than ever before simply not to matter?</p>
   <p>I present for your consideration <a href="https://fred.stlouisfed.org/graph/?g=1gpS4#">a graph</a>:</p><img src="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/03/20/a-simple-theory-of-the-stock-market/balsht-equity-to-public-debt.png" style="width: 100%;">
   <p>The denominator here is "Federal Debt Held By The Public", which is a good measure of US government paper issued, whether as US Treasuries directly, or as Treasury debt transformed by the Fed into bank reserves or currency. ("The public" in this measure includes the Federal Reserve, but the Federal Reserve's holdings of government debt are transformed into currency and reserves in the hands of the non-government public.)</p>
   <p>The numerator is the market value of corporate equities, held directly or via mutual funds, held by US households.</p>
   <p>Since the 2008 financial crisis, this ratio has stayed approximately constant. Basically, the total value of corporate equities gravitates around 1.4 times the quantity of Federal paper held by the public.</p>
   <p>This is quite different from the prior era, during which this ratio fluctuated widely.</p>
   <p>My explanation for this is very simple. Prior to 2008, equity holders as a class were engaging in speculations — or investments if you prefer — based volatile expectations surrounding corporate cash flows. There were periods of optimism (the late 1990s tech boom, the "democratization of credit" era that preceded the 2008 crisis), and periods of relative pessimism about corporate fortunes, all of which had little to do with the Federal government's debt position.</p>
   <p>2008 began an era of asset-allocation dominance. Equity holders, as a class, are no longer engaged in speculations — or investments if you prefer — in cash flow outcomes. They had been taught, for <a href="https://isbn.nu/9780070580435">at least a decade</a> by 2008, that evaluating cash flows like a classic investor is a mug's game. Since stocks are riskier than other securities, some natural law of the universe would always ensure they eventually return more than anything else. Old-fashioned ideas like "valuation" could only mislead investors into foolish exercises like market timing. Just think of equities writ large as an asset that will always yield higher returns than other asset classes, at the cost that you must tolerate greater fluctuations in value. Then divide your wealth between this "risky" class and other assets — like cash and bonds — in order to titrate your risk and maintain a cushion in case you need liquidity during one of the bad fluctuations.</p>
   <p>Obviously, asset-holders are heterogeneous, and not everybody behaves this way. People still do speculate on individual companies, evaluate growth prospects and cash flows, all of that. <em>Relative</em> performance within the broad class of equities still reflects expectations of firm-level analysts.</p>
   <p>But in aggregate, the public simply seeks a portfolio with a ratio of $1.40 of diversified equity for every $1 it holds of goverment paper, treating the precise composition of the equity as a secondary question.</p>
   <p>The price of government paper is largely pinned. There is some play in longer-term bonds, where investor behavior can muck with the term premium a bit, but for the most part, the value of government paper is set by face value, duration, and expectations surrounding the Fed. The price of equities, on the other hand, fluctuates freely.</p>
   <p>So what happens is pretty simple. Suppose we start at "equilibrium", investors hold $1.40 of equity for every $1 of US paper. Suddenly, the government spends some money, or just pays interest on its existing debt.</p>
   <p>Now the aggregate investment community is out of equilibrium. Cash (which, for our purposes, is just Federal paper in any form) is now a "hot potato", in the traditional metaphor. People have too much government paper, which they try to exchange for equities, but that just creates a hot potato in someone else's hands, unless and until the phrenetic equity-seeking bids up the price of existing equity in proportion to the new injection of government paper. Investors want their $1.4 in equities for every $1 of US paper. To a first approximation, the only thing that can adjust is the price of equities. So it does.</p>
   <p>The behavior that drives this — valuation independent "investment" into "diversified equities" as a black-box asset class — enjoys a great deal of elite-intellectual and policy support. It is what good upstanding prosperous professionals are told they are <em>supposed</em> to do with their savings. Once upon a time, equity investing was understood to be a high information, potentially quite dangerous activity that a relatively small fraction of the public would engage in. Now, among prosperous professionals, <em>failing</em> to be long equities is a mark of laziness, stupidity, or some form of financial dissidence. Being invested in equities "blindly" — by which I mean without picking stocks or using valuation to time exposure — is what conventional, smart, politically enfranchised people do.</p>
   <p>Inevitably, a policy apparatus evolves to stabilize whatever conventional, smart, politically enfranchised people do. Post-crisis, the Obama administration openly gauged the quality of the plans it would have Tim Geithner announce by the reaction of the stock market in the days following. Trump crowed about his stock market and <a href="https://thehill.com/homenews/administration/487588-trump-signs-chart-showing-stock-market-rally-after-he-declared/">autographed</a> ascending charts that he thought he could take credit for. There has long been perceived to be a "<a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/posts/1196599083.shtml">Fed put</a>". Economists like <a href="https://global.oup.com/academic/product/prosperity-for-all-9780190621438?cc=us&amp;lang=en&amp;">Roger Farmer</a> have made stabilizing an ascending equity price path ever more acceptable in policy circles.</p>
   <p>Valuation-independent investor behavior forms a <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/uploads/2015/03/cryptoasset-valuation.pdf">Nash equilibrium around equity price expectations</a>, in the same way and by the same dynamics as cryptocurrency booms. Unlike cryptocurrency, for equities the equilibrium is also stabilized by a wide variety of policy actors and instruments. Disproportonately enfranchised affluent professionals — call them the "top 30%" — are equity holders who have come to rely upon high equity returns regardless of the timing or valuation of their purchases. Equities fluctuate, sometimes wildly, but the most enfranchised citizens now expect an upward ratchet over a five to ten year horizon. Speculators' own self-fulfilling behavior joins forces with tacit but determined state support to deliver on that expectation.</p>
   <p>As a normative matter, we'd be better off if "equities" were just some arbitrary token or cryptocurrency. Perhaps the state could offer EquityCoin in fixed quantity, or with some precommitted, demand-independent, issuance path. Wise men and talking heads could encourage conventional professionals to divide their wealth between government paper and holdings of EquityCoin, rather than buying actual corporate equities.</p>
   <p>People like to imagine that by purchasing corporate equity, they are "investing" in the economy, allocating capital, making resources available to enhance future production of the goods and services that make us all prosperous. But bidding up the prices of existing corporate equities mostly does nothing like this. To a certain degree, okay. As share prices grow, firms are able to compensate employees cash-cheaply with options. They can borrow to finance new projects more easily. They can acquire conservatively valued private firms in exchange for just a few of their own overpriced shares. Firms do find circuitous means to take advantage of high stock prices, so, in very limited ways, mere share price appreciation can contribute to production.</p>
   <p>But as long as there remains some pretense — however tenuous or residual — that equity prices represent capitalizations of future cash flows, high share prices also impose costs and obligations on firms that may be socially counterproductive. To support share prices, firms repurchase their own expensive stock, which <em>drains</em> companies of cash, and <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/159.html">concentrates losses</a> on long-term shareholders should valuations ever revert. Even if equity prices in aggregate are continually growing, at individual firms, managers struggle desperately to maintain the ratchet, to ensure whatever today's share price is, tomorrow's should be higher. Or at the very least — God help us — no lower.</p>
   <p>I <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/5031.html">have</a> <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/9713.html">argued</a> <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/06/04/quietly-expensive-desperation/index.html">before</a> that we should think of "greed" as something structural, institutional, rather than an innate, individual characteristic. High share prices render firms insecure and rapacious as managers seek to ratify and support nosebleed prices with actual cash flows. When current profits comfortably justify their share price, managers might be content to grow by expanding quantity-produced at existing margins. But when the share price they must defend is not so justified, the pressure for profit growth may compel the same human managers to aggressively seek means of gaining market power and expanding margins at the expense of customers, vendors, and workers.</p>
   <p>High share valuations are both a cause and effect of our terribly unequal, greed-inducing, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matthew_effect">Matthew-effect-ridden</a> social arrangements. They are an <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/07/10/cornering-the-future/index.html">ethical catastrophe</a>. We should not want them, but it is hard for people whose 401(k)s are long the S&amp;P 500 to want to see them to disappear.</p>
   <p>Equity-invested affluent professionals tend stereotypically to be "fiscally conservative". If the dynamic I conjecture above is correct, well, careful what you wish for.</p>
   <p>Share prices and government deficits are connected conventionally via the <a href="https://www.levyforecast.com/assets/Profits.pdf">Levy-Kalecki profit equation</a>. (ht <a href="https://nathantankus.substack.com/p/where-do-profits-come-from">Nathan Tankus</a>) But that effect produces no expansion of valuation: share prices grow because profits grow. The dynamic described here leaves deficits not only padding corporate profits, but also supercharging multiples, whenever government debt is growing faster than earnings. Deficit restraint would both impair corporate cash flows, and reduce cash injections that investors now rely upon to deliver share price increases via portfolio composition effects.</p>
   <p>One puzzle (to me at least) has been why high share valuations have been so resilient as we've transitioned from near-zero interest rates to short-term rates above 5%. I had, calamitously, expected share prices would not be so resilient. But if portfolio composition trumps valuation, then we should expect high interest rates to be good for share prices over the long run, despite short-term declines when raises are first announced. Interest rate cuts, by reducing fiscal injections, should be bad for stock prices over time, despite price spikes when markets first anticipate them.</p>
   <p>David Andolfatto has <a href="https://andolfatto.blogspot.com/2024/02/does-high-interest-policy-constitute.html">recently pointed out</a> that the short-run and long-run effects of interest rate changes can be quite distinct. Perhaps <em>ex ante</em> the stock market reacts through a zombie reflex discounted-cash-flow valuation channel, but <em>ex post</em>, once the cash actually flows — or does not! — the aggregate investor's thirst to conjure its desired asset allocation wins out.</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/03/20/a-simple-theory-of-the-stock-market/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b>
   <br>
    [2024-03-20 @ 02:35 PM EDT]
  </div>
 </div>
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 10:50:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/02/29/what-you-are-doing-right-now/index.html</guid>
      <author>nospam@dev.null (Steve Randy Waldman)</author>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[Since not long after Donald Trump was elected in 2016, there has been this meme going 'round among liberals, something to the effect of "If you've ever wondered what you would do during the rise of Nazi Germany, it is what you are doing right now." The implication, of course, is that Trumpism and the fascism lurking just beneath it places us in a position analogous to Germans in say 1933. I have no argument with the point. There is something to it. However, it is at best a kind of loose...]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/02/29/what-you-are-doing-right-now/index.html</link>
      <title>What you are doing right now</title>
      <dc:creator><![CDATA[Steve Randy Waldman]]></dc:creator>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header">
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <p>Since not long after Donald Trump was elected in 2016, there has been this <a href="https://www.democraticunderground.com/?com=view_post&amp;forum=1002&amp;pid=10905966">meme</a> <a href="https://www.benjaminlcorey.com/who-would-you-have-been-in-nazi-germany-the-same-person-you-are-now/">going</a> <a href="https://www.facebook.com/WeActRadio/posts/if-youve-ever-wondered-what-you-would-do-during-the-rise-of-nazi-germany-well-no/2854473587935899/">'round</a> among liberals, something to the effect of "If you've ever wondered what you would do during the rise of Nazi Germany, it is what you are doing right now."</p>
   <p>The implication, of course, is that Trumpism and the fascism lurking just beneath it places us in a position analogous to Germans in say 1933.</p>
   <p>I have no argument with the point. There is something to it.</p>
   <p>However, it is at best a kind of loose analogy. It's pattern matching deployed to persuade people of the moral stakes of our situation, and to identify which actors are right, and which are much worse than merely wrong.</p>
   <p>Germany (or German-occupied Poland) in <em>1943</em> rather than 1933 presents an even more morally evocative touchstone for comparisons.</p>
   <p><em>If you've ever wondered what you would do during the rise of Nazi Germany, it is what you are doing right now.</em></p>
   <p>In Gaza, trapped innocents are being killed in large numbers.</p>
   <p>Perhaps the comparison is unfair. The Nazis never tried to warn their victims with pamphlets and "roof knocking" to get out of harms way. Hamas provoked the current conflict with mass atrocity in ways the Jews of Germany never did. No country could be expected simply to tolerate an enclave ruled by terrorists who openly promise to repeat their atrocities again and again and again.</p>
   <p>All of that is true.</p>
   <p>Trumpists of course can also draw a lot of true and important distinctions between their movement and the actual literal Nazis of Germany 1933.</p>
   <p>The power of the analogy is to cut through the nuance and expose it as sophistry. This will always seem unfair when you are on the side whose defense requires nuance.</p>
   <p>Whether in God's eye the nuanced position is right or wrong, here on Earth moral intuitions are blunt instruments. Generally people will side with a penned-in defenseless population getting murdered, regardless of the bigger picture. As a heuristic, that doesn't seem so terrible.</p>
   <p><em>If you've ever wondered what you would do during the rise of Nazi Germany, it is what you are doing right now.</em></p>
   <p>People who make these kinds of remarks seem so certain they know who the Nazis are. But it could be us, too. The Nazis didn't think they were the Nazis, in the way we mean it now. Whenever we consider ourselves part of a group so inherently righteous we are immune, we become particularly susceptible to slipping into the role.</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/02/29/what-you-are-doing-right-now/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b>
   <br>
    [2024-02-29 @ 10:50 AM EST]
  </div>
 </div>
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2024 14:10:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">
        https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/02/11/situated-versus-unsituated-virtues/index.html
      </guid>
      <author>nospam@dev.null (Steve Randy Waldman)</author>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[Why is the world like it is right now? Why does it seem that we are putting more of ourselves than ever before into efforts to help, to make the world a better place, but we seem collectively to be growing only more incompetent? We are, as individuals, the largest, best educated cohort of human beings that have ever lived on Plant Earth. Sure, maybe Harvard teaches more woke stuff, or maybe we are manipulated by TikTok and Fox News or whatever. There have, nonetheless, never been more humans...]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/02/11/situated-versus-unsituated-virtues/index.html</link>
      <title>Situated versus unsituated virtues</title>
      <dc:creator><![CDATA[Steve Randy Waldman]]></dc:creator>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header">
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <p>Why is the world like it is right now?</p>
   <p>Why does it seem that we are putting more of ourselves than ever before into efforts to help, to make the world a better place, but we seem collectively to be growing only more incompetent?</p>
   <p>We are, as individuals, the largest, best educated cohort of human beings that have ever lived on Plant Earth. Sure, maybe Harvard teaches more woke stuff, or maybe we are manipulated by TikTok and Fox News or whatever. There have, nonetheless, never been more humans more capable and skilled at any other moment in human history. Todays' graduates of Harvard — and today's graduates of every State U — can read and write, perform mathematics, and make use of unprecedented technical tools more capably than any generation in history. If you are into IQ, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flynn_effect">Flynn Effect</a> means we are about as smart as we have ever been.</p>
   <p>Yet collectively, we are fucking idiots. If I may <a href="https://www.azquotes.com/quote/1407287">quote</a> Larry Summers, look around.</p>
   <p>I want to posit a very simple explanation for much of our aggregate incapacity. We now devote ourselves much more to <em>unsituated</em> rather than to <em>situated</em> virtues. But constructive action depends primarily on accomplishing situated activities, which the extremity of our dedication to unsituated virtues now undermines.</p>
   <p>What do I mean by "situated" and "unsituated" virtues? Unsituated virtues are virtues we can all recognize based on widely shared information and values. Situated virtues, on the other hand, are legible only within the context of specific institutions or circumstances. Only insiders, suffused in real-time institutional knowledge that would be difficult to formalize or communicate broadly, even perceive the choice set under which some actions would be virtuous and others destructive. Situated virtues encourage action that would further the mission of an institution in ways too indirect or internal or intuitive to easily communicate, let alone justify, to outsiders.</p>
   <p>Racial justice is an unsituated virtue. We all understand why racial justice would be a good thing and is a goal worth striving towards, or conversely how it is a shibboleth that woke elites abuse in order to subjugate working people and then legitimate that usurpation with tokenistic "diversity". You don't need to actually work in admissions at some specific university to understand or participate in this debate. The director of admissions at an elite college, the (now deposed) board of the San Francisco Unified School District that devoted pandemic year to an ill-starred renaming project, the HR director of any major corporation, all understand the project of racial justice on similar terms.</p>
   <p>Chris Rufo <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2023/03/new-college-florida-ron-desantis-takeover/673556/">famously understood nothing</a> about my <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/02/27/new-college/index.html">alma matter</a> before making it a battleground over "DEI". He didn't need to. His project is a "long march through" the institutions to counter what he perceives as the same long march through from the other side. His worldview leaves no room for the day-to-day, invisible-problems-solved, particular-goals-accomplished lifeblood of each institution. They are all just pieces on a vast chessboard, enacting a contest legible to all of us who let "politics" become our vocation and entertainment.</p>
   <p>"Woke" and "anti-woke" both are pursuits motivated by unsituated virtues. Obviously, to activists within each of these projects, the other is not motivated by any virtue at all, but by vice. Whoever is right, whoever is wrong, they share the same fundamental characteristic: They are driven by an "idealism" — or a "grift", whatever — that is not tightly tethered to the particularities of the institutions they seek to alter. Their project is overarching. It supercedes little details. They may eventually have to attend to idiosynchracies in order to bend those institutions to their will, but the direction of the bending is determined long prior to that attention.</p>
   <p>Another unsituated virtue is making money. Like woke and antiwoke, whether in some broad sense you consider making money virtuous or vicious is besides the point. It is a virtue in the sense that it is a thing many of us individually and collaboratively pursue. We behave as though making money, and making more money, would be a good thing. We certainly try to achieve it.</p>
   <p>The "shareholder value revolution" that took root in the 1970s was explicitly and proudly a project intended to subordinate situated virtues (which economists disparaged as "agency costs") to the unsituated virtue of profit maximization. The theory was that profit maximization promotes economic efficiency and social good, so whatever firms do that is not conspicuously profit maximization — any way they attend unnecessarily to internal, invisible projects and concerns — can only constitute waste. By incentivizing managers to focus solely on externally legible shareholder value — and ripping away cash flows that might otherwise "burn a hole in managers' pockets" — the revolutionaries sought to make the real world fit a simple economic model under which perfectly competitive profit maximization yields at least Pareto optimal outcomes, if not a true maximization of <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/5149.html">welfare</a>.</p>
   <p>This project was rich with an irony its protagonists mostly failed to notice. Politically they allied themselves with the Friedrich Hayeks of the world. But Hayek's enthusiasm for market mechanisms was <a href="https://www.econlib.org/library/Essays/hykKnw.html">based precisely on humility</a> about what disembodied wise outsiders could possibly know about a world in which welfare-relevant information is radically and illegibly dispersed.</p>
   <p>The shareholder value revolutionaries were not driven by humility. They were sure that an absurdly stylized model connecting immaculate profit-maximizing firms, share prices, and social welfare was all they needed to understand. They had no compunction about imposing the crudest incentives as strongly as possible for precisely the purpose of overwhelming any invisible, illegible, particular concerns that might interfere with the project of maximizing near-term — and therefore long-term, because our protagonists believed markets "efficient" — share prices. And so we emerged with leaner, more efficient, firms. Like <a href="https://www.vox.com/money/24052245/boeing-corporate-culture-737-airplane-safety-door-plug">Boeing</a>.</p>
   <p>Our poisonous overdedication to unsituated virtues is now structural. It is inseparable from the very transactional kind of society we've let usurp the banner of liberalism. Which was the chicken and which was the egg I don't know. But employers no longer offer anything like a lifetime career ladder, while the most skilled professionals often defer, or indeed never take on, very long-term institutional commitments. At a personal level, I'm deeply attached to continual reinvention and nomadism. But into what kind of institutions, what kind of societies, do all we nomads compose? And how does that liberty <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/8392.html">affect those less well-placed</a> to pick-up stakes and reinvent themselves when things go awry?</p>
   <p>The incentives of the portable professional are quite different than those of a dedicated lifer. Our careers flit between many firms in the private sector, or many roles and positions in nonprofits or public service. Skills we develop pursuing situated virtues aren't necessarily portable. They don't translate easily into resumé items. Whatever deep institutional know-how we acquire is rendered obsolete with our next pivot. A school board member can use her racial justice activism as a springboard for all kinds of other roles. It constitutes achievement legible to sympathetic outsiders. If she devotes the same energy to quietly organizing conversations, resolving internal disputes, facilitating consensus, all of which contributes to excellences in education provision that may or may not show up in standardized testing? From the outside all she has been is a faceless bureaucrat. She might receive a glowing reference, from a crony.</p>
   <p>So individually, rationally, we look for overlaps between whatever our organizational roles might be and externally legible, unsituated virtues. But by seeking the kinds of achievements that help build our personal brands, we quietly deform institutions that we constitute, and starve them of the kind of work whose dividends are more subtle and collective. We end up with very brilliant people occupying all the roles of very dysfunctional organizations. Increasingly we find ourselves quite explicitly letting pursuit of unsituated virtues override the more specific purposes and goals of the institutions we participate in. (See <a href="https://www.tampabay.com/opinion/2023/03/04/florida-new-college-what-we-lose-when-we-ignore-stewardship-competence-column/">New College</a>, the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2020/11/12/audubon-society-claims-intimidation-threats-436215">Audubon Society</a>, etc.)</p>
   <p>This story has a lot of parallels, and touches on a lot of themes I've written about before.</p>
   <ul>
    <li>
     <p>"Situated versus unsituated virtues" is an institutional analog to <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/8511.html">extrinsic vs intrinsic motivation</a> at an individual level.</p></li>
    <li>
     <p>I think increasing reliance on <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/26/banks-should-fail-much-more-often/index.html">hard information rather than soft information has destroyed the unique role</a> banks used to play in economic and social development. Abjuring soft information in pursuit of scale has rendered banks little more than crony-capitalist, too-big-to-fail gatekeepers between citizens and the use of state money. Soft information is information that cannot easily be made universally legible and verifiable. Acting on soft-information is necessarily a situated virtue.</p></li>
    <li>
     <p>The financial analog of a very transactional social liberalism is the cult of liquidity, which is the <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/posts/1209978923.shtml">antithesis of investor commitment</a>. Perhaps firms are better run and managed with investors who must devote some attention and voice to the management of firms they invest in, rather than investors all of whom imagine they can costlessly exit if the firm is mismanaged, or who simply diversify away any care.</p></li>
   </ul>
   <p>Sometime in the 1980s, I think, David Letterman had on some MENSA person who was allegedly the smartest person in the world. So, he asked, why haven't you cured cancer?</p>
   <p>We have all become that person. More or better education, always the liberal cure-all, is beside the point. It's our institutions that are illiterate, not the individuals who people them.</p>
   <p>Garett Jones wrote a tweet that, more than a decade ago, I <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/4218.html">characterized</a> as "the single most insightful economics tweet of all time". He wrote</p>
   <blockquote>
    <p>Workers mostly build organizational capital, not final output. This explains high productivity per ‘worker’ during recessions.</p>
   </blockquote>
   <p>Jones has since deleted this tweet. It was probably already out of date when he penned it. Times have changed, and not for the better.</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/02/11/situated-versus-unsituated-virtues/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b>
   <br>
    [2024-02-11 @ 02:10 PM EST]
  </div>
 </div>
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Tue, 6 Feb 2024 11:10:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">
        https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/02/06/demographic-transition-is-just-specialization-and-trade/index.html
      </guid>
      <author>nospam@dev.null (Steve Randy Waldman)</author>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[On The New York Times' "Matter of Opinion" podcast, Ross Douthat worries about collapsing birth rates: I am interested in the problem of birthrates worldwide and in the developed world, and concerned about the consequences of demographic decline. Modest demographic decline leads to slower economic growth, even potentially negative economic growth. It leads to incredible burdens on old-age pension systems because you don’t have enough younger workers paying into them. And it leads to a lot of...]]>
      </description>
      <link>
        https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/02/06/demographic-transition-is-just-specialization-and-trade/index.html
      </link>
      <title>Demographic transition is just specialization and trade</title>
      <dc:creator><![CDATA[Steve Randy Waldman]]></dc:creator>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header">
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <p>On <em>The New York Times'</em> "Matter of Opinion" podcast, Ross Douthat <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/02/02/opinion/gen-z-gender-political-ideology.html?showTranscript=1">worries</a> about collapsing birth rates:</p>
   <blockquote>
    <p>I am interested in the problem of birthrates worldwide and in the developed world, and concerned about the consequences of demographic decline. Modest demographic decline leads to slower economic growth, even potentially negative economic growth. It leads to incredible burdens on old-age pension systems because you don’t have enough younger workers paying into them. And it leads to a lot of alienation and literal physical isolation.</p>
    <p>So if you look, though, at cases, like South Korea — and there are other countries headed rapidly in that direction — we aren’t talking about something an interesting sociological and economic question of, Well, what does society look like as it ages and has fewer kids? We’re looking at the potential for actual crisis and actual collapse.</p>
    <p>South Korea’s fertility rate is in the 0.7s right now, which means roughly for every two people, there is 0.7-ish offspring. If you just project that trend forward, South Korea’s population doesn’t just diminish. It starts to actually collapse over a two-generation time scale.</p>
    <p>...</p>
    <p>[W]hen the problem is, your birth rate is 1.5, and it would be better if it was 2, then it’s a somewhat-normal policy problem. And you can argue about what kind of social safety net you should have. And in those arguments, I have sympathies with liberals.</p>
    <p>I’m one of the conservatives who favors the new child-tax-credit provisions that Congress is considering this week. Those things have the potential to make it economically easier to have and rear kids. And they can affect the birth rate on the margins.</p>
    <p>But there are clearly just deeper, profound cultural forces at work here, which is why this trend shows up everywhere.</p>
   </blockquote>
   <p>Does neoliberalism count as a deeper cultural force?</p>
   <p>A simple definition of neoliberalism is expanding the scope of market logics in regulating human affairs, even into spheres that were traditionally the province of other institutions, like state, church, or family.</p>
   <p>The first result of market logics, the one <a href="https://www.gutenberg.org/files/3300/3300-h/3300-h.htm">extolled by Adam Smith</a>, is division of labor. Each worker should focus and become expert in one very specific aspect of production and then exchange the thing they produce most abundantly and excellently for other things. In aggregate we will then produce much more than if each of us made amateur attempts to produce for ourselves all that we require. "Cottage production", whereby an individual craftsmen artisanally produces all of the stages of a thing — let alone all of the stages of all of the things they might require! — is an epithet in economics. Even the production of pins, Smith famously described, is best meted out to specialists in a variety of tiny steps.</p>
   <p>From an economic perspctive, childrearing is a form of cottage production whose opportunity cost is gargantuan in the form of time misspent by specialists who could be producing valuable things.</p>
   <p>Child-rearing may not be quite as divisible as pin-making. We farm out aspects of education and health care to specialists, but it may be the case that shepherding infants into productive adulthood requires intense, indivisible, relationships with just a few consistent caregivers. Nevertheless, the most basic economic reasoning suggests that these caregivers should be specialists who devote themselves solely to caregiving, who trade the results of their caregiving excellence for the other goods and services they require.</p>
   <p>Market logics are not learned by catechism. They impose themselves invisibly, "naturally", via rewards and punishments embedded in the apparently disjoint choices of people who do or don't transact with us. The inefficient are left alone, and to be left alone is to be left to die. As Karl Marx famously <a href="https://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1845/german-ideology/ch01a.htm">put it</a>:</p>
   <blockquote>
    <p>For as soon as the distribution of labour comes into being, each man has a particular, exclusive sphere of activity, which is forced upon him and from which he cannot escape. He is a hunter, a fisherman, a herdsman, or a critical critic, and must remain so if he does not want to lose his means of livelihood; while in communist society, where nobody has one exclusive sphere of activity but each can become accomplished in any branch he wishes, society regulates the general production and thus makes it possible for me to do one thing today and another tomorrow, to hunt in the morning, fish in the afternoon, rear cattle in the evening, criticise after dinner, just as I have a mind, without ever becoming hunter, fisherman, herdsman or critic.</p>
   </blockquote>
   <p>How then, "if he does not want to lose his means of livelihood", in our capitalist and far-from communist societies, should we expect him to be a hunter in the morning and a parent in the evening?</p>
   <p>Demographic transition — collapsing birth rates — is not the puzzle. The puzzle is the continued pervasiveness of cottage parenting despite its inefficiency and cost. Why don't we leave parenting to lower-cost specialists in the developing world and then purchase the workers they produce with nice wages?</p>
   <p>Contra Douthat, precisely becuase the trend shows up everywhere, "deep, profound cultural forces" seem unlikely. Douthat and his colleagues lament that birth rates have collapsed even in European countries with generous "safety nets", and especially in culturally quite distinct South Korea. But neoliberalism broadly construed and the "high-tech late modernity" that constitutes Douthat's antinatal everywhere are the same place.</p>
   <p>Elsewhere I have written that <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/5031.html">"'incentives to produce' are incentives to rig the game"</a>. They are equally incentives not to have children. The level of outcome dispersion we've invited in the name of "incentives to produce" means that a child tax credit of one or two or five thousand dollars per child doesn't begin to put a dent in the opportunity cost of raising the child.</p>
   <p>Even the Nordics — the best arranged countries on Earth — can't overcome this. The Nordics do an excellent job of clipping the downside of social outcomes. The state covers many of the basics of childrearing. Nordic countries <a href="https://www.euronews.com/health/2023/03/17/fertility-in-europe-which-countries-have-the-highest-and-lowest-numbers-of-live-births-per">do pretty well on birth rates</a> relative to peers of similar wealth. But not well enough to replace their own populations. Neoliberalism suffers also from its upside, from the outsize lives it delivers to those who devote themselves to its games and win.</p>
   <p>The relationship between wealth and natality is nuanced. When wealth is certain, its increase is likely pronatal, as people can bank on greater resources to cover the burdens of childrearing. But when wealth is uncertain, when it is delivered via tournaments that deliver outsize rewards to winners, then increases in "expected" (meaning average) wealth likely translate to <em>decreases</em> in natality. The bigger the prize, the greater the cost of anything that will reduce your chance of winning.</p>
   <p>American conservatives (I'm not accusing Douthat here!) love to sexualize everything. If only we could shove women back into the kitchen, they'd become bored enough to find meaning again in raising a bunch of kids. Maybe so! But that's just a specific case of a general proposition. To the degree that we can clip the opportunities available to households outside of raising kids, then households will choose to raise more kids.</p>
   <p>Instead of insisting women stay home, we might just impose steep levels of taxation at incomes just above what a single devoted earner might achieve. That would end the <a href="https://isbn.nu/0465090907">"two income trap"</a> for upper-middle class families. Affluent households would face little penalty for letting one parent specialize in market income and the other parent focus on childrearing, homemaking, and community-building. Choosing the location of the tax threshold would involve tradeoffs between how broadly in the population we wish to encourage natality versus neoliberal concerns about incentives to produce.</p>
   <p>Alternatively — preferably I think — rather than reducing the opportunity cost of childrearing by putting a tight ceiling on other opportunities, we could increase the payout associated with childrearing. The cost of raising a child well, in direct expenses and the opportunity cost of time, is tens of thousands of dollars per year. Policy encouragements that have been tried and mostly failed are simply nowhere near the relevant magnitudes.</p>
   <p>Adam Smith's ghost still haunts us. If we did compensate child rearing at levels roughly commensurate with its costs, there'd be more kids all around, but a disproportionate share of the new children would likely come from households that efficiently specialize in child rearing rather than seek other forms of market income. I suspect that, for contestable social reasons, we'd dislike that market logic and limit the number of compensated kids per household, or phase-in compensation only with other forms of income.</p>
   <p>But there really is no mystery. In our thoroughly marketized societies, we don't find it odd that other goods and services whose remuneration is lower than the opportunity cost of the inputs they require are meagerly supplied. We don't like to talk that way about children, but it is precisely the same situation. Various social institutions once encouraged childrearing anyway. Neoliberalism is just the project of demoting and eclipsing those.</p>
   <p>To their credit, many social conservatives have now reckoned with the inconsistency between their values and the neoliberal project. However, many of the most prominent contemporary pronatalists come from the tech/crypto/VC space, and have not grappled with or even recognized the contradictions among their allegiances. They have invented a new dialectic — <em>synthesis, antithesis, optimism</em> — and it is enough for them.</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/02/06/demographic-transition-is-just-specialization-and-trade/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b>
   <br>
    [2024-02-06 @ 11:10 AM EST]
  </div>
 </div>
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Fri, 2 Feb 2024 12:30:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">
        https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/02/02/nimble-nationality-will-define-state-capacity/index.html
      </guid>
      <author>nospam@dev.null (Steve Randy Waldman)</author>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[One thing perhaps we can agree is that Israel/Palestine serves as a cautionary tale. Israel/Palestine is the story of a failed state. Two populations, which define and distinguish themselves in terms of identities deemed immutable by virtue of history and religion and ethnicity, have failed now for decades to come to some accommodation under which they might peacefully coexist and jointly govern the small sliver of land they occupy between the Jordan River and Mediterranean Sea. If it weren’t...]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/02/02/nimble-nationality-will-define-state-capacity/index.html</link>
      <title>Nimble nationality will define state capacity</title>
      <dc:creator><![CDATA[Steve Randy Waldman]]></dc:creator>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header">
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <p>One thing perhaps we can agree is that Israel/Palestine serves as a cautionary tale.</p>
   <p>Israel/Palestine is the story of a failed state. Two populations, which define and distinguish themselves in terms of identities deemed immutable by virtue of history and religion and ethnicity, have failed now for decades to come to some accommodation under which they might peacefully coexist and jointly govern the small sliver of land they occupy between the Jordan River and Mediterranean Sea.</p>
   <p>If it weren’t for the all the dead bodies, it would almost be farcical. All of these big words — “rights” of national self-determination, of return, claims to history and indogeneity — just obscure and perpetuate and justify failures to address the most basic prerequisites of human flourishing on a territory the size of a postage stamp. It’s like academic politics are so bitter because the stakes are so small. Only now with murder.</p>
   <p>People live in places. People’s welfare is determined much more by the quality of the communities that occupy those places than by anything they can do as individuals. You may be very good at your work. You wouldn’t have done well in Somalia.</p>
   <p>The first prerequisite of flourishing for any geographically situated human community is peace. But peace, Thomas Hobbes <a href="https://www.gutenberg.org/files/3207/3207-h/3207-h.htm">reminds us</a>, is not the human default. We are quarrelsome creatures. Peace only obtains when some form of <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/6970.html">authority</a> emerges that serves as a basis for coordinating punishment of freelance banditry within a territory, and for coordinating defense against marauders from without.</p>
   <p>Both “nation" and "state” are names we give to this kind of coordinating authority. But the two words suggest quite distinct approaches. A “nation” is a community of people inculcated with some shared sense of who they are and how communal life should be arranged, who generally act in accordance with that sense. Members of a nation discourage violations of that shared understanding almost instinctually. Those who act in accordance with the shared understanding are welcomed in the collaborations that render a community prosperous and lively, while those who defy them face exclusion and stigma, and, for severe violations, improvisationally organized vigilanteism. A "state" is quite different. States are made of formal institutions and laws, written codification of how people are to behave, superintended by a hierarchical body which enforces its authority via a near monopoly in practice over coercive violence.</p>
   <p>The "nation-state" is the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rTTixlelryY">Reese’s Peanut Butter Cup</a> of human coordination at scale. It takes from nation a commonality of understanding that renders authority largely self-enforcing. It takes from state the stabilizing backstop of coercive enforcement, and also the dynamism that centralized codification — and therefore a centralized capacity for recodification — can engender.</p>
   <p>There are tensions between the two approaches. Laws can change faster than shared understandings. The shared understandings of a nation constitute the sacred. Nation-states must sacralize the everchanging law itself, must inculcate not just an understanding of how we live, but a meta-understanding that how we live is mutably governed. Today’s laws are owed the same reverence today that yesterday’s were owed yesterday, even when they are mutually contradictory. Conversely, the formal bureaucracy of the state must be attentive to and not outstrip the nation’s capacity to make sense of itself. The nation must be able to recognize in the changing law adaptations and improvements of how the community understands itself, rather than its undoing.</p>
   <p>Beyond peace, the quality of a geographically situated community is a function of how effectively and adaptively it can coordinate, and at what scale. A geographically situated community different elements of which are at war (however literally or figuratively) with one another, or are simply not mutually intercoordinating among one another, will be weaker and less prosperous than a community capable of recruiting its full population into coordination with little internal contestation. Holding constant the quality of internal coordination, larger nation-states will enjoy greater prosperity and military power than smaller nation-states. (Small nation-state that seem to defy this logic usually have some much larger patron with which they are deeply integrated in trade and which attends to their defense.) In practice, there are often tradeoffs between scale and quality of coordination. But when those can be overcome, bigger is better.</p>
   <p>So a nation-state is a natural monopoly subject to economies of scale. The essence of a state is a near monopoly in practice over coercive violence. The essence of a nation is a shared understanding that promotes effective coordination across the community. For economies of scale to be realized, mutually compatible, if not identical, understandings of how to act must be widely held. If a nation-state means to prosper and defend itself, it must cultivate some form of national identity that its population will almost universally adopt.</p>
   <p>Historically, the main solution to this problem is assimilation. France becomes a nation-state when it erases its historic provinces, to which grand stories and identities once attached, and replaces them with bureaucratic departments. This was <a href="https://www.gouvernement.fr/partage/9898-83-departements">openly a project</a> to supplant provincial identities with a new understanding of self and community that would be shared across the full territory of the French state. To this day, the French nation is evangelical and assimilative, willing to make equal citizens of all who enthusiastically adopt its shared self-understanding, discouraging to the point of persecution communities on its territory that insist upon understandings which the larger polity does not deem compatible.</p>
   <p>Ethnostates, on the other hand, are disfavored by the logic I have described. When there exists some prior ethnic group whose traditional self-understanding will serve as the national complement to a formal state, the scale of the nation-state is limited by the scale of that <em>ethnos</em> in the borders of some territory that it dominates.</p>
   <p>Ethnicity is not usually conceived as very permeable. You are of our tribe, or you are not. In a world (our real world) where self-perceived ethnic communities are not well sorted geographically, ethnostates cannot achieve the universality of shared identity that an effective nation-state requires. It will necessarily govern subpopulations not of the nation, for whom coordinating authority will derive primarily from the ungloved fist of the state.</p>
   <p>Hard power without soft power is always fragile power. Repression and especially conflict are costly — in a fiscal sense, but more importantly in potential coordination foregone. Repression and conflict are constant, when people inhabit territory a state claims but are excluded from the nation, from the shared understanding and identity under which citizens conform to state authority even without any proximate threat of coercive violence.</p>
   <p>It is one of history’s typical ironies that “the Jews” and “the Palestinians” have a great deal in common while they murder one another. Both are “nations” whose self-conceptions are incompatible with an inclusive, and therefore effective, state. As long as the narrative that binds each group is membership based on shared history and grievance, each of the nations is necessarily exclusive of the other. The “self-determination” of one in the form of an ethostate requires the continual oppression of the other, poisoning the lives of victor and vanquished alike, unless and until near complete separation or elimination can be achieved. Both Israel and Palestine, as they conceive themselves, are bad projects, practically and ethically. They rot from their seeds.</p>
   <p>But the rest of us ought not rest on our laurels. As the Israelis point out when they complain about “double standards”, there is a little bit of ethnostate in most contemporary nation-states. On the one hand, modern liberal states promise to be states for all their citizens, to provide equal rights and equal dignity to all. On the other hand, the same states privilege language and cultural practices historically associated with one demographically dominant ethnicity.</p>
   <p>Unlike Israel, however, most liberal states tolerate and encourage assimilation by outsiders. Only Jews can be Jews in Israel. Anyone who moves to France or Germany, who adopts and embraces the language or culture, can become German. The United States is so new, and the provenance of its population is so mixed, that its national identity is openly synthetic and syncretic. But the United States has nevertheless constructed a strong national identity, despite little anchoring in any historical ethnicity.</p>
   <p>Modern, liberal nation-states are more resilient than gated ethnostates like Israel, but they are far from infinitely resilient. That word “liberal” often connotes a claim that not only will the state provide equal rights and dignity to individuals who assimilate, but that they will also provide equal rights and dignity to different <em>communities</em>, including communities who choose not to assimilate, who do not join the shared self-understanding that defines the nation tethered to state.</p>
   <p>That claim is a pretense, a dangerous conceit. The nation part of nation-state is not optional. Ethically, we might wish for a world in which states could be neutral between radically diverse communities. But states rely upon citizens having understandings of themselves and of social affairs that, again, need not be identical, but must be mutually compatible. It is the nation in nation-state that enables the citizenry as a whole to mostly govern themselves, resorting only infrequently to deployment of the state’s hard power as an unwelcome but sometimes necessary backstop.</p>
   <p>The function and purpose of nation-states — effective social coordination at very large and impersonal scales — cannot be achieved relying solely or even primarily upon the blunt instrument of direct state power. Shared understandings and customs that become the basis for tacit, automatic, instinctual, decentralized coordination are not optional. A state is only effective if it superintends a nation. A nation is only effective if, beneath the amorphous evolving haze of custom and identity, sits the defining and stabilizing bone structure of a state.</p>
   <p>We are in an era of mass migration, which presents challenges to nation-states, and therefore to the capacity of humanity as a whole to coordinate at scale and prosper at scale, because that happens almost entirely under the auspices of strong nation-states. Our collective failure to achieve “convergence”, under which less developed states would find a path towards matching the prosperity and safety of developed states, means that, for much of the world, migration to a more developed state is your best and perhaps only strategy to give your kids a decent life. Climate change is likely to supercharge migration pressures, as some places grow too dangerous or barren to support their existing populations.</p>
   <p>Humanity is not a democracy, but a thing about the humans is everybody gets a vote anyway. You may wish we did not face the challenge of mass migration, but the migrants get a vote, and they say that we must in fact face it. You can adopt the MAGA “America First” response to this new era, but to do so is to elect to become Israel, and to pay the costs — military, economic, and moral — that Israel now is paying. If your main response to growing demand for mass migration is to become restrictionist, then you will have to militarize your borders in order to enforce your restrictions. You will have to become authoritarian internally to detect and deport those who have evaded your restrictions, and to manage security threats created by citizens of your own state who will not assimilate to the nation you propose, because they sympathize with migrants.</p>
   <p>Israel is a brittle ethnostate because it cannot or will not bring people who live on its territory or who insist disruptively that they will live on its territory into its national community. It bears large costs to preempt conflicts and to fight them, larger costs in terms of social and economic potential foregone, and worst of all, social deformation, shame, and moral injury from all the murders the path it has chosen does require it to commit.</p>
   <p>The states of North America and Europe will be no different if we place ourselves in the same situation.</p>
   <p>The alternative to Israel is as it has always been America, the America of <em>e pluribus unum</em>. The United States is not, and never has been, a state without a nation. The America I grew up in had a deep and profound national identity. This was not mere “creedal democracy”, the thin, very intellectual idea that our quasi-worship of the Constitution and a few civic ideas was the basis for our common nationhood.</p>
   <p>No, the United States had, and still has, a very thick, tacit and instinctual, national identity. We have customs and a language and weird idioms that we share. We have American food, like pizza, bagels, kung-pao chicken, hamburgers, sushi, and gyro sandwiches. It doesn't matter that these things derive from other nations, or whether they are "authentic" to their roots. They are ours now.</p>
   <p>There is nothing more British these days than having a curry. In Germany you find wonderful kebabs. This reflects the most virtuous form of assimilation, where the shared understanding that defines the nation not only accepts migrants as individuals, but adapts the shared natural culture to include and celebrate what they as communities bring. Host country citizens recognize that they gain from “appropriating” the most congenial bits of migrants’ cultures. America would not be America without pizza! Migrant communities feel more welcome when at least some of their old self-understandings are celebrated by their new communities. They become more willing to walk the challenging, painful, road of ceding much of who they have been and how they understood their world in order to adopt something quite different. When migrants’ “ethnic” commodities — foods or foot massages or whatever — are embraced by home country natives, that helps to lubricate their assimilation economically, as it means there are services they are particularly well-placed to sell. Xenophilia is an incredibly adaptive national characteristic, and it will only be more so going forward.</p>
   <p>When restrictionists in developed countries say they don’t mind, aren’t against, immigration, they just want it to be legal and ordered and organized, that is fine and they are right. We do not want, should not abide a situation where our laws, whose tacit sanctity renders our national success possible, are run roughshod by new migrants that must learn also to hold them sacred if we are to collectively succeed.</p>
   <p>But at the same time, we cannot succeed if the laws we enact are ill adapted to our actual circumstances. To save Miami from sea-level rise, we could ban high tide. We could place militarized cops on the beaches, fire machine guns at each transgressing wave. The tide will still come. Our laws cannot be shaped only by our preferences. Reality will have its say.</p>
   <p>As pressures for mass migration accelerate, we will all become some admixture of Israel, Lebanon, and melting-pot America. Some countries will double-down on restrictionism become small, brutal, deformed shadows of the political communities they might have been. Some will accept the tide of bodies into the territory of their states, but prove unable to merge the diversity of communal identities and worldviews that come with those bodies into a coherent nation, leading to reduced social trust, impairment of the nation-state’s ability to coordinate at scale, bitterness among natives and new immigrants both, conflict, and authoritarianism.</p>
   <p>But some countries will manage what the United States managed in the 19th and 20th Centuries, to accept the bodies but also join the minds of new citizens into a continually evolving understanding of the nation to which they now belong. Countries that manage this will achieve the economies of scale that nation-states can gain from larger populations without bearing the deadweight, deadly costs of interethnic conflict, militarized borders, deterrent brutality.</p>
   <p>No law can make the immigration problem go away. The world is as it is, and the drivers of mass migration are likely to get stronger not weaker. The question before us is not “whether” or “how many”, but “how?” What set of practices and institutions might bring natives and migrants together under a version of national identity sufficiently nimble and attractive and adaptive to join and guide us all?</p>
   <p>For nation-states capable of answering this question, the coming era will be a time of growth, opportunity, and national greatness. For nation-states whose identities and self-understandings are incapable of adapting to integrate large numbers of new migrants, it will be a time of crisis, authoritarianism, decline, bitterness, and shame.</p>
   <p>We’d best get working on how.</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/02/02/nimble-nationality-will-define-state-capacity/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b>
   <br>
    [2024-02-02 @ 12:30 PM EST]
  </div>
 </div>
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <atom:link type="application/rss+xml" rel="self" href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/feed/index.rss"/>
  </channel>
</rss>
