<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss 
version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>drafts — interfluidity</title>
    <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/index.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[Feed for blog 'drafts — interfluidity' generated by unstatic]]></description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2023 11:39:54 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>https://github.com/swaldman/unstatic</generator>
    <docs>https://cyber.harvard.edu/rss/rss.html</docs>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2023 11:40:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">
        https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/24/financial-regulation-is-just-debt-covenants/index.html
      </guid>
      <author>nospam@dev.null (Steve Randy Waldman)</author>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[Financial regulation is to public lending precisely what loan covenants are in the private sector. They are similar mechanisms intended to serve the same function: to prevent shareholders from exercising their customary control rights in ways that, in expectation, would transfer wealth from debt investors to equity holders rather than or in addition to increasing the aggregate value of the enterprise. A leveraged firm is, from the perspective of shareholders, a call option on the assets of the...]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/24/financial-regulation-is-just-debt-covenants/index.html</link>
      <title>Financial regulation is just debt covenants</title>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header">
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <p>Financial regulation is to public lending precisely what loan covenants are in the private sector. They are similar mechanisms intended to serve the same function: to prevent shareholders from exercising their customary control rights in ways that, in expectation, would transfer wealth from debt investors to equity holders rather than or in addition to increasing the aggregate value of the enterprise.</p>
   <p>A leveraged firm is, from the perspective of shareholders, a call option on the assets of the firm. Equityholders maximize their wealth by taking large risks. If those risks work out, shareholders get to appropriate the increase in the value of the firm. If the firm crashes and burns, well, sure shareholders lose their stake, but their stake is only a fraction of the resources they had used to build their lottery ticket with. Lenders eat most of the loss.</p>
   <p>When shareholders swing for the fences, they enjoy all the fruits of victory, but creditors bear the cost of striking out. In expectation, creditors lose money on big risks. Creditors' upside is restricted to the interest payments they've contracted for, so their interests are maximized when the firm chooses the least risky path that would just cover those interest payments and repayment of the debt. Ambitions any risker than that increase the probability of nonpayment without doing creditors any good. However, riskier ambitions increase potential earnings beyond debt service, earnings that equityholders get to keep if the risks pay off. So risk-taking amounts to transfer from creditors to shareholders. As risk increases, the expected value of creditors' investment declines (because the probability of default rises), while the expected value of shareholders position rises (because the possibility of a big payoff increases).</p>
   <p>Creditors "sign up" to a certain degree of risk-taking by equity holders when they agree to lend to a firm. The firm presents its business plan. Firms must take <em>some</em> degree of risk to generate the operating profits from which interest will be paid.</p>
   <p>But once the contracts are signed and the money is lent, what is to prevent shareholders from changing their business plan and adopting a much riskier strategy that effectively loots their creditors?</p>
   <p>Well, when the lenders are private, they insist upon "debt covenants" in the lending contracts. These give creditors leverage to usurp shareholders' control rights as soon as it seems like shareholder risktaking may be putting repayment in jeopardy. What kind of "leverage"? Usually, they allow the creditors to demand full and immediate repayment, which the firm which has borrowed to spend and invest, is unlikely to be able to provide. So, when covenants are violated, shareholders and lenders enter into negotiation, and shareholders ultimately have to do whatever creditors say to avoid being sued into bankruptcy.</p>
   <p>In a better world, public lenders could do the same thing. They could protect their interests via debt covenants. Unfortunately, most public lending is opaque and covert: it takes the form of public <em>guarantees</em> of private debt, rather than public lending directly. In this case, the notional lenders (bank depositors, for example), have no reason to negotiate debt covenants and monitor adherence to them, because the notional lenders could care less. They are not on the hook for the loss. The actual bearer of risk, the public guarantor, is not directly a party to the contracts, and so cannot negotiate covenants either.</p>
   <p>Thus financial regulation.</p>
   <p>There are lots of different kinds of financial regulation, for lots of different purposes, sure. But the main thrust of financial regulation is simply to do for public guarantors exactly what covenants do for private debt contracts. Just as private covenants are negotiated so that creditors can usurp control from shareholders early on in the dangerous-risk-taking process, financial regulation aspires to <a href="https://www.federalreservehistory.org/essays/fdicia">prompt corrective action</a>, under which regulators exert control before shareholders can put too big a hole in balance sheets that the state guarantees. Private creditors take control by threatening to accelerate repayment of their loans. Public regulators use a variety of tools, from compelling management to perform specific actions in order to reduce risk, to taking the indebted firm into receivership and operating it themselves.</p>
   <p>Fundamentally, private debt covenants and public financial regulation are the same thing. They are means by which creditors of leveraged firms try to ensure shareholders can't loot them by building tripwires that allow creditors to usurp control from shareholders when shareholder risktaking threatens creditor interests. They look different, they take different forms, because private creditors can regulate within debt contracts that they sign, while the public sector offers finance primarily via guarantees, and so must impose its regulation outside of the contracts that borrowing firms and their notional creditors devise.</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/24/financial-regulation-is-just-debt-covenants/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b><br>[2023-03-24 @ 11:40 AM EDT]
  </div>
 </div>
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2023 16:15:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/21/banks-are-not-private/index.html</guid>
      <author>nospam@dev.null (Steve Randy Waldman)</author>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[Banks are not private businesses. Yes, of course, they do pretend to be. They are listed on stock markets. They take the organizational form of a private business. Their profits are definitely privatized. But their risk is borne almost entirely by the state. Beyond a small sliver of equity and bonds sits a vast ocean of "deposits" that the state guarantees, explicitly via "deposit insurance", tacitly far beyond that. "Deposit insurance" itself is a pretense. Recall that the first thing FDIC did...]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/21/banks-are-not-private/index.html</link>
      <title>Banks are not private</title>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header">
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <p>Banks are not private businesses.</p>
   <p>Yes, of course, they do pretend to be. They are listed on stock markets. They take the organizational form of a private business. Their profits are definitely privatized.</p>
   <p>But their risk is borne almost entirely by the state. Beyond a small sliver of equity and bonds sits a vast ocean of "deposits" that the state guarantees, explicitly via "deposit insurance", tacitly far beyond that.</p>
   <p>"Deposit insurance" itself is a pretense. Recall that the first thing FDIC did during the 2008 financial crisis was more than double its insurance limit from $100,000 to $250,000. What kind of insurance company <em>increases</em> the limit of the insurance it provides at just the moment claims become likely to be made? What kind of insurance company lets you multiply your insuredness for free if you perform bureaucratic busywork that does not in anyway mitigate the underlying risk, like split your deposits between an account in your name and a joint account, or form a <a href="https://www.fdic.gov/deposit/diguidebankers/documents/revocable.pdf">trust</a> that's still yours unless you die?</p>
   <p>FDIC is not "limited deposit insurance". When it was founded, perhaps it was intended to be that. But <a href="https://www.clevelandfed.org/publications/economic-commentary/2017/ec-201717-origins-of-too-big-to-fail">by the early 1970s</a>, as the strict prudential regulation that emerged during the Great Depression was slowly whittled away, anyone paying attention came to understand that the state's role in banking goes far beyond an insurance product, maybe on slightly subsidized terms. With an insurance company, it's usually a bit of a struggle to get claims paid. The companies are trying to minimize payouts. With FDIC, it is an extraordinary event when even notionally <em>uninsured</em> depositors are not made whole. It does occasionally happen! But it is the exception, not the rule. It results from the sin of keeping deposits beyond FDIC's notional limit in a bank so minor and insignificant that its customers can be sacrificed to the project of maintaining appearances. It must appear that FDIC is an insurance company with a statutory obligation to minimize costs. It must appear that banks are private companies that are required, as many businesses are, to purchase certain insurance products in order to protect customers or workers.</p>
   <p>Whether the resolution of a bank — or, more usually, a cluster of banks, since bank failures are not independent events — will ultimately be cheap or costly to "the taxpayer" depends almost entirely upon regulation and supervision prior to the resolution. FDIC (and the Treasury, and Fed) can <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/12/unlimited-deposit-insurance/index.html">play various games</a> to limit the impact of resolution on the Deposit Insurance Fund, like levying fees to other banks that will be passed along to taxpayers in their role of bank customers (or that would be, if bank profits were disciplined by competition). But the cost of a bank resolution will always be the size of the hole in the banks' balance sheet that supervisors have allowed to emerge before resolving the bank. All FDIC can do is allocate (or obfuscate) the cost.</p>
   <p>That said, bank resolutions needn't be costly! When supervisors do their job — when the state uses the tools at its disposal to aggressively <em>manage</em> this risk of banks that the state almost entirely bears — banks are prevented from taking risks that will make the bankers rich if things work out, but leave a crater in a balance sheet they walk away from if things don't work out. When supervisors actually do take <a href="https://www.federalreservehistory.org/essays/fdicia">"prompt corrective action"</a>, they can prevent balance sheet holes from growing very large, and so minimize the cost of resolving a bank.</p>
   <p>Bank resolutions needn't be costly, though of course often they are. The bank failures attending the 2008 financial crisis and the 1980s S&amp;L crisis were not cheap.</p>
   <p>But people spend far too much energy worrying about the cost of bank failures, and far too little worrying about the cost of bank survival.</p>
   <p>Banks are not private businesses. Their risk is borne almost entirely by the state, so the state tilts the playing field to ensure that overt, embarrassing, disruptive bank failures are suppressed. No one objects (except the bankers) when this takes the form of supervision and prudential regulation. But the most costly forms of state support take the form of subsidies that the state can pretend are not "taxpayer funded", but that impose quiet costs on the public anyway. Do you remember when the Fed <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/posts/1160447599.shtml">retroactively rewrote millions of lending contracts</a> so that banks could charge more interest and recapitalize? Do you remember when the nation debt <a href="https://fred.stlouisfed.org/graph/?g=11AvT">doubled in less than four years</a>, precisely so that large banks would <em>not</em> have to be resolved? <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/2587.html">Yes, Virginia.</a> Bank failures, actually, are much less expensive than the things we do to fill holes in bank balance sheets so we need never acknowledge their failures.</p>
   <p>Apropos nothing, check out this <a href="https://www.federalreserve.gov/newsevents/pressreleases/monetary20230312a.htm">Bank Term Funding Program</a>! Valued at par. <sup id="fnref-1"><a class="footnote-ref" href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/21/banks-are-not-private/#fn-1">1</a></sup></p>
   <p>Meanwhile, since we pretend banks are private businesses, we let shareholders and managers siphon off wealth while banks take risks on behalf of the state, and then again as they skim from the opaque subsidies the state pours into them when things go sour.</p>
   <p>It is a good thing, not a bad thing, that the risk of aggregate investment is ultimately borne by the state. I am sometimes asked whether I really believe that our choices are to tolerate something on the verge of fraud or <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/2669.html">revert to goat-herding</a>. The answer is no, I don't believe that. Even though historically private bank finance emerges — very productively! — at the edge of fraud, we now have states that can overtly undertake investment risks on our collective behalf that we as individuals would not consent to take with our own resources. The state already is the bank. What's left is to acknowledge that and, importantly, to devise an institutional structure for state-backed development finance that is not so obfuscated and corrupt and shell-gamish as contemporary banking, but that also avoids the pathologies of politicized lending.</p>
   <p>Once upon a time, I might have been persuaded that it's good that banking camouflages as private finance while it covertly mobilizes the resources of the state. The theory is that it's much better to have investment mobilized on commercial terms than on political terms, and the pretextual privateness of contemporary banking permits that. You don't want a world in which state resources are allocated based on political connectedness or populist fads rather than investment quality.</p>
   <p>The proof is in the pudding, though. The contemporary "private" financial system is shit. It can mobilize resources stupidly — secured against collateral like real-estate, or against least-common-denominator "hard information" like credit scores. But it no longer performs its most essential task: ferreting out and funding <a href="https://syntheticassets.wordpress.com/2012/02/22/what-banks-do-monetize-human-capital/">good <em>uncollateralized</em> loans</a>. It creates rivers of financial flows from the poor and disorganized to the rich and well-connected. It has profitably, but contrary to domestic public interest, underwritten the near total offshoring of critical industrial capabilities in ways that overtly public finance, whatever else its flaws, would never have allowed. It finances consolidation of industry, and helps <a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=3649879">organize shareholders into tacit cartels</a>. Despite its privateness and supposed commercial orientation, contemprary finance is hardly immune to cronyism.</p>
   <p>For all the obvious pathologies of our politics — in part <em>because</em> those pathologies are obvious and public — I think we would be better off reorganizing finance, disentangling deposits and payments entirely from risk investment, ensuring credit availability by having the state explicitly support investment funds dedicated to forms of economic development we decide are prosocial.</p>
   <p>Of course there will be scandals. It is an institutional reality that private sector business aggressively markets itself as virtuous, despite its unhidden thirst to maximize the rents it can extract, while the public sector is subject to eternal scrutiny, under which every failure to live up to an ideal of public spiritedness is treated as discrediting of the entire enterprise. But the public sector succeeds at least partially at virtues that the private sector does not even pretend to attempt. The private sector is precisely in the business of doing the self-interested things that in the public sector get called corruption. It's just not labeled corrupt, because treating aggressively in ones own self-interest is what's expected!</p>
   <p>A better financial system would include investment funds whose private managers, like contemporary banks, enjoy outsized gains in exchange for exposure to first loss on state-financed investment. But there would be no prevarification about where the money is coming from. It is coming from the state. It is a mobilization of our collective risk-bearing capacity, towards ends that the broad public supports. The composition of our aggregate investment portfolio — the most important edifice that we all collectively construct — would not be pawned off on anonymous market forces. It is the responsibility of the democratic state, however imperfect our democracy remains.</p>
   <hr>
   <p><em>See also <a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2820176">Robert Hockett and Saule Omarova</a></em></p>
   <div class="footnotes">
    <hr>
    <ol>
     <li id="fn-1"><p>BTFP should be understood as a bet by the Fed that inflation will subside and they can soon revert to the last decade's very low interest rates. This would create capital gains that will help offset losses of banks that reached for yield — but too little yield — buying longer-term, low risk, bonds. (Banks that reached for actual profits by making high-quality unsecured loans are fine, despite rising rates, because the credit spread in those loans can cover this moment's high cost of short-term finance. They'll be at risk, though, if an economic downturn creates a wave of failures to repay.)</p> <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/21/banks-are-not-private/#fnref-1" class="footnote-backref">↩</a></li>
    </ol>
   </div>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/21/banks-are-not-private/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b><br>[2023-03-21 @ 04:15 PM EDT]
  </div>
 </div>
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Mar 2023 20:40:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/19/disintermediation/index.html</guid>
      <author>nospam@dev.null (Steve Randy Waldman)</author>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[Whenever there is a conversation about narrow banks or central bank digital currencies, the bogeyman of "disintermediation" ghoulishly appears, shrieking and wailing about the death and destruction that awaits if any part of our deposits and payments system were to be wrested from the cuddly, gentle banks who grant us convenience and prosperity and take nothing from us but our ingratitude. I actively favor disintermediation of status quo banks. I consider the "risk" that, if the public were...]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/19/disintermediation/index.html</link>
      <title>Disintermediation</title>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header">
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <p>Whenever there is a conversation about <a href="https://www.econlib.org/lyn-alden-on-bank-safety/">narrow banks</a> or <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/8876.html">central bank digital currencies</a>, the bogeyman of "disintermediation" ghoulishly appears, shrieking and wailing about the death and destruction that awaits if any part of our deposits and payments system were to be wrested from the cuddly, gentle banks who grant us convenience and prosperity and take nothing from us but our ingratitude.</p>
   <p>I actively favor disintermediation of <em>status quo</em> banks. I consider the "risk" that, if the public were offered a simple, safe alternative, depositors would flee to it, to be like the risk that a better world might in fact be possible. That would mean something might change!</p>
   <p>Let's understand the issue. Currently, we hold our liquid wealth as "deposits" at commercial banks. Deposits are just loans that <em>we</em> make to banks, but they are callable on demand: we can withdraw them as cash, or use them any time to make payments. Most deposits are in fact created from loans by our banks. The name "deposit" is intentionally misleading, emphasizing the case where you "deposit" hard government cash into the bank, and that's why it owes you something back. In reality deposits are IOUs banks conjure at will, as easily as incrementing numbers in an internal database. Banks are constrained in theory in the amount of "money" they produce by the risk that account-holders may demand cash, or make payments to (net of receipts from) customers of other banks, beyond what the bank has on-hand or can borrow. Banks are constrained in practice by restrictions imposed by regulators, because it turns out the theory doesn't work. As long as customers value bank deposits at par — you accept $1 in the bank as worth the same as a green bill in your pocket — bankers would do best making up as much money as they can to invest, selling or borrowing against their investments to raise cash if customers make unexpected demands, walking away from the wreckage with profits they've already taken when they can no longer sell or borrow to meet withdrawals. If you want banks to be truly regulated by a free-market, then you'll have a shitty payments system, because a dollar "on deposit" at each bank will have to be worth less than a dollar, to account for the risk the bank's bets won't actually cover the deposits they owe. Each bank's deposits will have its own constantly changing price, whose fairness most customers will be unable to independently evaluate. If you want banks to run a smooth payments system where a dollar is a dollar at any bank, then you'll need a state, both to offer guarantees that keep the promised value credible, and then to regulate, in order to counter the "heads I win, tails I walk away" incentive that the ability to issue par-valued money begets.</p>
   <p>Seems like a lot! Why not just have some institution — a "narrow bank" if private, the central bank if public — actually just keep green money that we deposit, and we can make payments with that? A dollar would always be worth a dollar, because without any need for regulation or concern about tricky incentives. A narrow bank would basically just keep every dollar deposited to it, the Fed can issue dollars at will, when it issues back dollars previously deposited it's not increasing the quantity or liquidity of money, so there's no new inflation risk. This would be "disintermediation". We'd disintermediate the banks, finally tell them to fuck off. Hooray!</p>
   <p>But there is a real problem with disintermediation. All of the money banks conjure from thin air to make risky loans, the money regulators are endlessly struggling to prevent turning into a heads-I-win-tails-I-walk scam? That is the same money that is loaned to you when you get a mortgage to buy your home. It's the same money that finances the loan a business takes to buy its machinery or inventory or create that amazing ambiance for your dining pleasure. Those are the banks' risky bets! (Well, they are some of the banks' risky bets. Banks make a lot of less sympathetic, not-so-obviously-productive bets too.)</p>
   <p>If we <em>only</em> disintermediate, without replacing banks' phrenetic incentive to exploit their money-making franchise and invest in stuff, we'll get a lot less aggregate investment. Our civilization will collapse into <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/2669.html">goat-herding</a>. The scare-mongers will have been proven correct.</p>
   <p>If we disintermediate (and goat-herding does not appeal), what could replace <em>status quo</em> banks? Do we need to invent something untried and revolutionary?</p>
   <p>Well, no. It turns out, much of our banking system is undergoing disintermediation as we speak! A week ago, the Federal Reserve announced the <a href="https://www.federalreserve.gov/newsevents/pressreleases/monetary20230312a.htm">Bank Term Funding Program</a>, which will allow</p>
   <blockquote>
    <p>banks, savings associations, credit unions, and other eligible depository institutions [to borrow] pledging U.S. Treasuries, agency debt and mortgage-backed securities, and other qualifying assets as collateral...valued at par.</p>
   </blockquote>
   <p>I know, dear reader. Finance-speak! The eyes glaze! What does all this mean, in English?</p>
   <p>It means that the general public, which usually makes the bankers' money machine work by treating bank deposits like money-good-as-cash and letting them sit unwithdrawn, is now withdrawing much of its money. If Jane Public is not deserting the banking system entirely for actual cash, then she is piling into one of <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@interfluidity/110002159996385364">Citi, JP Morgan Chase, Bank of America, or Wells Fargo</a>, "systematically important financual institutions" that we all know are too vast and entrenched for the government to allow depositors to be screwed. These are as risk-free good-for-the-money as the government is risk-free-good-for-the-money, because in a pinch the government would rather cover their deposits than deal with the hell that would break loose if they didn't.</p>
   <p>The big banks are <a href="https://markets.businessinsider.com/news/stocks/bank-of-america-deposits-svb-too-big-to-fail-jpmorgan-2023-3">raking it in</a>! But what about the rest of the banks? They will not, you will notice, collapsing like mayflies at the end of a long summer's day. Banks' money-making machinery, and so their investment-making machinery, depends on customers' willingness to leave "their money" in the form of the deposits banks invent, rather than immediaately withdrawing it. The money small and midsized banks invented would be suddenly uninvented, and all those banks' loans and investments would have to be called or sold in a fire sale, if depositors fled and no one else could be persuaded to accept IOUs from these banks as good money. So, the Federal Reserve has stepped in and is replacing fleeing depositors, importantly without even asking whether the investments the banks have made are good enough to eventually cover the loan the government, instead of the general public, is now making to these banks. That's what "valued at par" means in finance-speak.</p>
   <p>The Federal government may lend banks a great deal under its new program, or it may ultimately lend very little. Knowing that the Fed will replace fleeing deposits with loans of goverment-issued cash, dollar-for-dollar even against bank investments that have lost value, means there is little reason for depositors to actually flee. Anytime they want to withdraw, the government will be there with a dollar for the bank to give them.</p>
   <p>There is nothing new in any of this. It is the essence of modern banking. If you want a dollar in a bank to be worth as much as a dollar in your pocket, the government must, and only the governnment can (because only it can issue dollars in any quantity, at will), be willing to replace a bank deposit with a dollar. If deposit insurance were truly limited, all but the smallest businesses would not have a reliable payments system. Since the mid-20th-Century, we've maintained the conceit that bank deposits represent private "investments" and deposit insurance is "limited" (though you can multiply it through the economically counterproductive busywork of splitting accounts). But that has been bullshit all along, because we have wanted an economy in which businesses could use the payments system as a payments system without worrying about their "investment" in the bank. The term "too big to fail" is not some new invention from the 2008 financial crisis. In the United States, it <a href="https://www.clevelandfed.org/publications/economic-commentary/2017/ec-201717-origins-of-too-big-to-fail">begins in the 1970s</a>, as the strict prudential regulation enacted during the Great Depression begins to get whittled away by bankers pushing to make their money-printing machine whirr just a little bit faster. Limited deposit insurance has only ever been a thing for small banks, where it could be symbolically upheld to promote a useful myth. It has been untenable since the scale of payments by a large fraction of businesses came to exceed the level that insured accounts could conveniently provide. Big business simply banks with Citi and JP Morgan to be sure their deposit insurance is unlimited. They don't fuck around with hundreds of $250K accounts.</p>
   <p>Disintermediation is not a novelty. <em>Intermediation</em> is a fiction. The clear-eyed way to describe our banking system is that</p>
   <p>But for our purposes here, we can stick to the intentionally misleading simple case. You deposit money in the bank, the bank increments its database of how much it owes you,</p>
   <p>Another way to put that is to say that deposits are IOUs from our banks to us, but they promise to redeem them for government cash whenever they want.</p>
   <p>The IOU frame is helpful, because it reminds us that banks can <em>create</em> deposits at will. The name "deposit" is intentionally misleading. It suggests you "deposit" something into the bank, then it owes you that thing back on demand. But most deposits are never "deposited" at all: they are conjured into existence by loans. If you go to your bank and ask for a $1000 loan (and you being you, so fucking awesome, are obviously good for it), what happens is you sign a piece of paper that promises to repay the bank on certain terms, including an interest rate, and the bank just increases the number in its database that represents your account balance. The paper you sign means you owe the bank some money. The extra balance in the account means the bank owed you some money. It's a like-for-like exchange, and no government money was involved. You and the bank both just conjured up some IOUs.</p>
   <p>Suppose you use your new "cash" to buy something cool from the store. If the store and you have the same bank, guess what happens? You "spend" $500. The bank deducts $500 from your account (a record of how much the bank owes you) and add $500 to the store's account (how much the bank owes the store). No government money ever changes hands. Your bank created the "money", you and the store transact in it.</p>
   <p>Banks can't just create money however they feel like it, though. They are constrained in theory by the fact that you might want to withdraw the cash, or you might try to pay someone who banks at a different bank. In either of those cases, your bank might have to come up with government-issued money. They face two constraints, liquidity and solvency. Liquidity means they should have enough cash on hand to meet the demands of withdrawers, and of payments out to other banks, net of payments the bank receives. In any given day — well, on almost any given day — the vast majority of bank deposits will be neither withdrawn or paid out. So the bank needs to hold as <em>assets</em> (remember deposits are the bank's liabilities, its <em>debt</em>) only a little bit of government cash, whether the green paper you might withdraw from a teller or the electronic reserves used for interbank payments. The rest of the bank's deposits represent <em>loans the bank has made that it is earning interest on</em>. The bank may pay some interest on our deposits, sure, but because we value the convenience, liquidity-on-demand, and safety-from-armed-robbery that keeping our money in the bank provides, in fact we accept a much lower rate of interest than we would on some loan we made as an "investment". And that is the heart of the trick. Bank intermediation creates a pool of money bankers can invest paying much less than the interest that other investors would require for a loan to a risky investment fund. Which is precisely what a bank is.</p>
   <p>Keeping money in a bank might be convenient and keep you safe from armed robbery, but it doesn't keep you safe from a bank failure! Since the bank keeps on-hand as cash only a small fraction of hypothetically withdrawable deposits, even a bank that has invested well may sometimes face a situation where it has made promises that it cannot immediately keep. In theory, if the bank has invested well, that should be no big deal. The bank can just sell its investments (its loans to you and me!) to some other bank or investor, and those investments will be worth substantially more than all the deposits the bank owes customers, so just give them a minute or two and they'll raise the cash to pay you back (or borrow it using their sterling investments as security).</p>
   <p>However, in real life, sometimes banks will have not invested well. (Silicon Valley Bank made some <em>oopsie!</em> bets on interest rates.)</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/19/disintermediation/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b><br>[2023-03-19 @ 08:40 PM EDT]
  </div>
 </div>
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2023 23:40:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/12/unlimited-deposit-insurance/index.html</guid>
      <author>nospam@dev.null (Steve Randy Waldman)</author>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[Tonight the US Treasury, Federal Reserve, and FDIC delivered a joint statement in order to staunch the panic provoked by last week's resolution of Silicon Valley Bank. (ht Steve Herman). Regulators shocked the market last week, not because SVB was shut down and put under FDIC receivership, but because initially it seemed like regulators were going to only insure up to the formal $250,000 limit of FDIC insurance, which would leave SVB's many business customers unsure of when and how much of what...]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/12/unlimited-deposit-insurance/index.html</link>
      <title>Unlimited deposit insurance</title>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header">
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <p>Tonight the US Treasury, Federal Reserve, and FDIC delivered a <a href="https://home.treasury.gov/news/press-releases/jy1337">joint statement</a> in order to staunch the panic provoked by last week's resolution of Silicon Valley Bank. (ht <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@w7voa@journa.host">Steve Herman</a>).</p>
   <p>Regulators shocked the market last week, not because SVB was shut down and put under FDIC receivership, but because initially it seemed like regulators were going to only insure up to the formal $250,000 limit of FDIC insurance, which would leave SVB's many business customers unsure of when and how much of what they had thought were safe bank deposits would ever be recovered.</p>
   <p>Today's joint statement returns us to the post-Great-Financial-Crisis tacit <em>status quo</em>. During the Great Financial Crisis, regulators <a href="https://www.americanbanker.com/opinion/will-fdic-keep-protecting-failed-banks-uninsured-deposits">created an expectation</a> that customers — at least customers of not-tiny banks — would not lose a penny even of their uninsured deposits in a bank failure. By law, of course, uninsured deposits are, well, uninsured. FDIC is supposed to resolve banks at least-cost to the taxpayer and if that means stiffing uninsured depositors, well, so be it. But in practice, regulators post-GFC have understood that stiffing uninsured depositors makes no sense in our brave new world of banking, and have <a href="https://www.fdic.gov/news/speeches/2019/spoct1619.html">publicly fretted</a> whether inadequate precautionary regulation might place them in the position in which they found themselves last week, where they might feel they have no choice.</p>
   <p>To be clear, I think that Treasury, the Fed, and FDIC have done the right thing here. Once upon a time, the rationale for limited deposit insurance was that large depositors, whether rich individuals or big businesses, should monitor the operations of the banks they entrust with their money. Bankers who took unsound risks would face market discipline, losing the major depositors without whom they have little capital to risk.</p>
   <p>But in practice, this just doesn't work. Even regulators, who are highly trained specialists with privileged access to internal bank data, struggle to evaluate the soundness of modern banks. A midsized business that keeps $1M in the account from which it has to make payroll each month has zero real ability to keep honest a profession deeply schooled in the financial dark arts. If we insist that uninsured depositors take losses when their bank fails, the outcome won't be better disciplined banks, but a run to the banks that are hardest of all to discipline, the ones widely understood to be "too-big-to-fail". Despite tonight's walkback by regulators, the chaotic resolution of SVB may have already made that very bad result inevitable.</p>
   <p>What I do take issue with is Treasury/Fed/FDIC's claim that "no losses will be borne by the taxpayer" as they make uninsured depositors whole. Not to put too fine a point on it, that's bullshit. It's a particular strain of bullshit that has grown both common and destructive in the policymaking community.</p>
   <p>Treasury/Fed/FDIC say no losses will be borne by the taxpayer because they will levy a "a special assessment on banks, as required by law" to recover FDIC's losses. But who, pray, will pay for that "special assessment on banks"? It is not an assessment on the personal wealth of bank managers or shareholders. Some bank managers are billionaires, but they will pay no more of this "special assessment" than you or I. What will happen is <em>all deposits</em> will become effectively mutually insured by the industry as a whole. Every bank's costs — whether paid up-front as explicit FDIC deposit insurance premiums or paid on the backside as "special assessments" — will increase. Banks will have to recover this new cost from customers, in higher fees, higher lending rates, or lower deposit rates.</p>
   <p>Sure, there will not formally be a new tax to cover these costs. But in substance, the tax-paying public will experience higher expenses or foregone income. This habit of declaring "no new taxes" in form, while tacitly imposing taxes in substance, deprives the public of any capacity to design the tax, to shape its incidence, and to hold accountable those who provoke the costs the tax must recover.</p>
   <p>This is not the only case where policymakers launder taxes through what are ostensibly "private insurance premiums". Health care is riddled with this tactic. Whenever policymakers cap the "out-of-pocket cost" for a drug or medical procedure without also capping the cost billed to insurance companies, they are simply socializing whatever cost the billers impose via a "tax" that gets embedded all of our monthly premium payments. Whether any particular medical cost should be "socialized" or concentrated on the recipient of the service can be a subject of heated debate. (I'm on the side that says most medical costs should be socialized.) But regardless, we need to manage the cost we pay <em>in aggregate</em> for medical services, however we divide the hit. Capping out-of-pocket costs but not capping costs billed to insurers may perversely lead to <em>increases</em> in aggregate cost, as larger costs spread over the whole insurance base escape the outrage and scrutiny that concentrated costs provoke.</p>
   <p>It's better when we impose costs the public will have to bear as overt, explicit taxes than to let policymakers impose costs through private intermediaries then pretend "no losses will be borne by the taxpayer".</p>
   <p>One way or another, the public, or some part of it, will have to bear the cost of unlimited deposit insurance. The clearer it is that you and I and all of us are on the hook whenever any bank's hunger for yield leaves any deposit unbacked, the more likely we are to adopt actually sensible policy, like disentangling the deposits and payments system entirely from private risk investment.</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/12/unlimited-deposit-insurance/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b><br>[2023-03-12 @ 11:40 PM EDT]
  </div>
 </div>
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Wed, 8 Mar 2023 18:15:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/08/libertarians-and-hierarchy/index.html</guid>
      <author>nospam@dev.null (Steve Randy Waldman)</author>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[In my post on how why higher education is shockingly right-wing, some libertarian commentators didn't like this: If "left" and "right" have any meaning at all, "right" describes a worldview under which civilized society depends upon legitimate hierarchy, and a key object of politics is properly defining and protecting that hierarchy. "Left", on the other hand, is animated by antipathy to hierarchy, by an egalitarianism of dignity. While left-wing movements recognize that effective institutions...]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/08/libertarians-and-hierarchy/index.html</link>
      <title>Libertarians and hierarchy</title>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header">
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <p>In my post on how why <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/08/libertarians-and-hierarchy/(##right-wing-higher-ed)">higher education is shockingly right-wing</a>, some libertarian commentators didn't like this:</p>
   <blockquote>
    <p>If "left" and "right" have any meaning at all, "right" describes a worldview under which civilized society depends upon legitimate hierarchy, and a key object of politics is properly defining and protecting that hierarchy.</p>
    <p>"Left", on the other hand, is animated by antipathy to hierarchy, by an egalitarianism of dignity. While left-wing movements recognize that effective institutions must place people in different roles — sometimes hierarchical, sometimes associated with unequal rewards — these are contingent, often problematic, overlays upon a foundational assertion that every human being has equal dignity and equal claim to the fundamental goods of human life.</p>
   </blockquote>
   <p>That, dear reader, is about the best and most concise explanation of left and right as you are ever going to get.</p>
   <p>But my libertarian friends hate it! Here's <a href="https://www.timworstall.com/2023/03/so-let-us-take-interfluidity-seriously-for-a-moment/">Tim Worstall</a>:</p>
   <blockquote>
    <p>Therefore markets – and free markets more especially – are not a right wing idea. For the entire point about the free in free markets is that absolutely anyone gets to try overturning that hierarchy. And, often enough, succeeds. Apple fucked over AT&amp;T rather nicely, Whitney’s cotton gin entirely shafted the linen and wool weavers, Aldi and Lidl cost Sainsbury’s shareholders billion upon billion.</p>
    <p>Which means that the left embraces markets as those hierarchy overturning engines that they are. Right?</p>
   </blockquote>
   <p>Ah, Tim. Markets are not just ideas. They are actual practices and institutions, which occur in the context of real societies and lived circumstances.</p>
   <p>Free markets were indeed a left-wing practice, several hundred years ago, when an ascendant bourgeoisie, bound only by the spontaneous organization of market logics, overturned the feudal hierarchies that had dominated Europe until then.</p>
   <p>Markets can be anti-hierarchy, and when they are, yes, they are on the left! "Classical liberals" used to be at war with the traditional right, remember?</p>
   <p>But what if, today, we talk about Marin County.</p>
   <p>Marin County, for those who don't know, is an exclave of San Francisco. It's the spit of land immediately across the Golden Gate Bridge from the city proper. It is breathtakingly beautiful. Its towns — places like <a href="https://www.sausalito.gov/">Sausalito</a>, <a href="https://www.cityofmillvalley.org/">Mill Valley</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Larkspur,_California">Larkspur</a>, <a href="https://www.townofsananselmo.org/">San Anselmo</a>, <a href="https://www.townoffairfax.org/">Fairfax</a>, and <a href="https://www.townoftiburon.org/">Tiburon</a> — are contemporary paradises: safe, culturally lively, brimming with small-town charm but only a short drive from the big city.</p>
   <p>And Marin County is impeccably progressive! Everywhere you go, you will see the signs:</p>
   <div style="text-align: center;">
    <p><img src="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/08/libertarians-and-hierarchy/in-this-house.jpg" alt="IN THIS HOUSE, WE BELIEVE: BLACK LIVES MATTER / WOMEN'S RIGHTS = HUMAN RIGHTS / NO HUMAN IS ILLEGAL SCIENCE IS REAL LOVE IS LOVE KINDNESS IS EVERYTHING / DIVERSITY MAKES US STRONGER"></p>
    <p><img src="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/08/libertarians-and-hierarchy/immigrants-and-refugees-welcome.jpeg" alt="REFUGEES AND IMMIGRANTS ARE WELCOME HERE"></p>
   </div>
   <div style="font-size: 80%; line-height:110%;">
    <hr>
    <p><em><strong>Note</strong>: I just found these pictures on the internet, one from <a href="https://i.pinimg.com/736x/43/4e/0c/434e0c6073ce77d81f9ba423532b06c6.jpg">pinterest</a>, one from the <a href="https://www.chicagotribune.com/resizer/uXzNN1abUmsJ6nQKjOCPYcg7FMI=/415x233/top/www.trbimg.com/img-5b55f1e1/turbine/ct-1532359133-ibv2lamjz4-snap-image">Chicago Tribune</a>. You'll have to take my word, dear reader, as someone who really enjoys Marin County and has spent a lot of time there, that signs of this sort are in fact common.</em></p>
    <hr>
   </div>
   <p>Perhaps Tim and I would agree that there's something a bit hypocritical in all this progressivism. Everyone really is welcome in Marin! (Well, not in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bolinas,_California">Bolinas</a>, that's a different story.)</p>
   <p>Everyone is welcome, but a modest home will cost you a couple of million dollars. Those charming towns are incredibly segregated, racially and economically.</p>
   <p>The residents of Marin, like university professors, are perfectly sincere in their progressivism, as far as it goes. Yet, the residents of Marin assiduously defend exclusive access to extraordinarily desirable places to live without erecting a single physical gate. All they need is the housing market, under land-use rules that serve both to preserve the very real charm of their communities and to keep housing scarce.</p>
   <p>Perhaps that's not the market Tim would prefer! But it is the market we actually have.</p>
   <p>Matt Yglesias sometimes <a href="https://tinyletter.com/mattyglesias/letters/what-s-driving-me-is-driving-you">describes</a> his YIMBY preferences with respect to land use as Latin-America-style land reform. And he has a point! If Marin housing markets were made "free" in the way that Matt, and I suspect Tim, would prefer, then they might have a left-wing, anti-hierarchical valence!</p>
   <p>But that is not our world. In our real world, social hierarchies are <em>primarily inscribed via market processes</em>.</p>
   <p><a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/7263.html">Quoting myself</a> yet again (fucking narcissist):</p>
   <blockquote>
    <p>[W]hat it means to live in a stratified society, precisely what it means to live in a stratified society, is that there are objective correlates to position along dimensions that individuals and communities cannot themselves choose. There are positional dimensions whose importance is a social fact, not arbitrary, but real as social facts are, by virtue of their consequences. In such a society, positional goods with desirable correlates, inherently scarce and inelastically supplied, become extremely valuable. In some societies, those goods may be rationed by custom, or by heredity, by caste or race. But to the degree that a society is “liberal” and capitalist, they will be price-rationed, as they largely (but incompletely) are in our American society.</p>
    <p>In a stratified, liberal capitalist society, the ability to command market power, to charge a margin sufficiently above the cost of inputs to cover the purchase of positional goods, becomes the definition of caste.</p>
   </blockquote>
   <p>If libertarians restricted their support for markets to arrangements and circumstances when they are anti-hierarchical, well, then they would be of the left!</p>
   <p>But very obviously, they do not in practice do that.</p>
   <p>Libertarians share exactly the same pathology as university professors and the smiling residents of Marin County: They flatter themselves that they stand in opposition to vicious social hierarchy, and find true-enough narratives by which to spin their allegiances into support for equal dignity. But their actual practices, the institutions they inhabit and animate and from which they earn their succor, belie all that.</p>
   <p>Contemporary libertarians are, um, quite disproportionately winners under current market arrangements. And they assiduously support those arrangements. They do not, for example, condition their support of markets on the rigor of actual competition, so that economic rents don't accumulate. Libertarians are not like a certain stripe of socialist, whining that socialism has never really been tried. Libertarians say that capitalism has been tried, and it works great.</p>
   <p>But under actually existing capitalism, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matthew_effect">Matthew effects</a> rule the day. Markets may be notionally "free", but past winners (humans, not just firms) have tremendous advantage. Certain classes of people understand that market arrangements are likely to continue to deliver <em>to them</em> security and abundance, but will sadly deliver those goods less adequately to other groups whose ongoing misfortune, despite occasional bootstrap stories, we can pretty well predict.</p>
   <p>Markets, under these circumstances, become a locus of hierarchy, rather than a challenge to it.</p>
   <p>Which is why, despite protestations about loving freedom and encouragements to individual pluck, contemporary libertarians quite correctly identify as of the right.</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/08/libertarians-and-hierarchy/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b><br>[2023-03-08 @ 06:15 PM EST]
  </div>
 </div>
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <atom:link type="application/rss+xml" rel="self" href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/feed/index.rss"/>
  </channel>
</rss>
