<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss 
version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>drafts — interfluidity</title>
    <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/index.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[Feed for blog 'drafts — interfluidity' generated by unstatic]]></description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2023 23:57:34 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>https://github.com/swaldman/unstatic</generator>
    <docs>https://cyber.harvard.edu/rss/rss.html</docs>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2023 18:05:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">
        https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/04/10/systemic-means-its-not-your-fault/index.html
      </guid>
      <author>nospam@dev.null (Steve Randy Waldman)</author>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[Much of the resentment that has condensed onto the term “wokeness” derives, I think, from people's perception that they stand accused, unjustly, of crimes they did not commit: I am not a bigot, but the woke accuse me of "structural racism". I am not responsible for the actions of people long dead who are not me, but they tell me I am "compicit", which is just another word for guilty. No one knows what I have been through, or how hard I have worked, but they insist that I am privileged....]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/04/10/systemic-means-its-not-your-fault/index.html</link>
      <title>Systemic means it's not your fault</title>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header">
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <p>Much of the resentment that has condensed onto the term “wokeness” derives, I think, from people's perception that they stand accused, unjustly, of crimes they did not commit:</p>
   <blockquote>
    <p><em>I am not a bigot, but the woke accuse me of "structural racism". I am not responsible for the actions of people long dead who are not me, but they tell me I am "compicit", which is just another word for guilty. No one knows what I have been through, or how hard I have worked, but they insist that I am privileged.</em></p>
   </blockquote>
   <p>Click-hungry media, both traditional and social, eagerly reinforce the perception that wokeness is about calling out personal sin. Accusations of racism or harassment levied at an identifiable human become <em>scandal</em>, which our gossipy primate brains are drawn to irresistibly, as though our own place in the clan's dominance hierarchy hinges precariously upon the outcome.</p>
   <p>But "woke”, as Ron DeSantis' General Counsel <a href="https://floridapolitics.com/archives/574045-in-andrew-warren-suspension-trial-gov-desantis-officials-answer-what-does-woke-mean/">helpfully put it</a>, refers to “the belief there are systemic injustices in American society and the need to address them.” <em>Systemic</em> means that the injustices <em>do not</em> reduce to personal bigotry. It refers to structural factors, which may derive from past bigotry, but which perpetuate injustice, and might do so even despite the real goodwill of everyone alive today.</p>
   <p>For example, historical redlining created segregated ghettos and a strong correlation between neighborhood racial composition and home values. Today's loan assessor might be sincerely antiracist. She might be black. But it would still be her job to incorporate observed relationships between location and value into her assessments. Low valuations can be self-fulfilling. Limiting buyers' access to borrowed purchasing power makes home price appreciation less likely in historically black neighborhoods. Our assessor's work would be "colorblind”, but it might nevertheless help perpetuate racist outcomes.</p>
   <p>But those outcomes would not, in any personal, ethical, sense, be her <em>fault</em>. Obviously, the correlations between race and home value that preceded her could not be her fault. One might argue that, going forward, if she is sincerely antiracist, she has a moral obligation to give effect to her antiracism. She must do her job not merely in a colorblind way, but in a manner that actively counters and helps to remedy historical racism.</p>
   <p>However, she could not ethically do that on her own. If she were to, say, assess homes in historically black neighborhoods at values derived from comparable properties in white neighborhoods, she would quickly be fired. Her employers would, reasonably, want to ensure that <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/21/banks-are-not-private/index.html">ultimately public</a> funds aren't lent to dramatically overpay for homes that will become the loans’ collateral.</p>
   <p>And even if she were not fired, her guerrilla revaluation revolution wouldn’t on its own put a dent in the home-wealth penalty black people in America continue to face. You'd need nearly all the loan assessors, and their employers, to agree that imposing, against experience, valuation at levels set by white-neighborhood-comparables is a good tactic for remedying historical racism, despite the obvious risks and costs of the strategy. In practice, that would only happen if there were systematic signals and incentives to encourage the practice.</p>
   <p>A structural problem demands a systematic solutions, usually in the form of public action. It is not an individual's fault, or within an individual's capability, to remedy.</p>
   <p>I wish that those of us more on the “woke” side of the debate were clearer about this. When we say that racism or other social disparities are “systemic” or “structural”, we are absolving, not condemning, nearly everyone, as individuals.</p>
   <p>When Ron DeSantis <a href="https://www.wfla.com/news/pasco-county/florida-is-the-place-where-woke-goes-to-die-desantis-says/">describes</a> Florida as “where woke goes to die”, he is appealing to a bitter energy fueled by sloppy mischaracterization, and sometimes the sloppy practice, of social justice movements. He insinuates that "wokeness” requires that people who are white, or cis, or straight should feel guilty, personally — and should subordinate their own interests, interpersonally — to claims made by members of "special” groups.</p>
   <p>Contemporary social justice movements are multiple and fractious. Among them there are no doubt people who make such demands. But that is a mistake.</p>
   <p>Personal bigotry continues to exist. The political climate in places like Florida is increasing it. When it appears, of course it should be condemned. But the insight of scholarship like critical race theory is that continuing injustice is largely not a result of direct, personal bigotry. It is an error, ethically and practically, to emphasize personal and interpersonal accountability when we seek to address problems that are systemic and structural. People like Ron DeSantis want to caricature wokeness as a movement that indoctrinates children to feel guilty about being a normal (read white) American. That’s not a project most of us would support. DeSantis’ General Counsel’s version, on the other hand — “there are systemic injustices in American society and the need to address them” — is right on.</p>
   <p>There are injustices. They are systemic, which means, quite directly, they are not your fault. They are not your kids’ fault. No matter how white or straight or cis you are, you have nothing to apologize for. You owe nobody anything.</p>
   <p>But we would have a better country, a prouder country, a safer country, and a richer country, if we could finally fix these problems. You owe nobody anything, but we would sure welcome your help.</p>
   <p>Remedying systemic injustice is not a zero-sum game. If getting black kids into Harvard seems to come at the expense of Asian kids, the problem is Harvard, not any of the kids. The way we fix systemic injustice is to build a country in which everyone willing to contribute can succeed, rather than a thunderdome where we clump up into gangs and fight to win access to patronage networks.</p>
   <p>If all the places that now seem hopeless, sad, and scary — inner city black neighborhoods, sure, but also “forgotten” white communities — if we invested in making all these places safe and prosperous, then no one anywhere could mock expressions of open patriotism. USA #1! Despite everything, I remain proud to be an American. But I could be prouder. I would like to be.</p>
   <p>Systemic injustice is not your fault. But we’d love it if you’d help to fix it.</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/04/10/systemic-means-its-not-your-fault/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b><br>[2023-04-10 @ 06:05 PM EDT]
  </div>
 </div>
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Thu, 6 Apr 2023 11:45:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">
        https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/04/06/alignment-is-the-problem-of-gods-love/index.html
      </guid>
      <author>nospam@dev.null (Steve Randy Waldman)</author>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[The presupposition behind AI “alignment” is that artificial intelligence technologies will grow into something much more capable than we are, with a kind of autonomous will or volition. If you believe this then Luddism — in the vulgar sense of merely opposing or destroying technology — is probably the right response. There is no solution to the so-called alignment problem. It’s not just a matter of research. We humans have hashed this problem out over centuries, with little satisfaction. Arthur...]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/04/06/alignment-is-the-problem-of-gods-love/index.html</link>
      <title>Alignment is the problem of God's love</title>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header">
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <p>The presupposition behind AI “alignment” is that artificial intelligence technologies will grow into something much more capable than we are, with a kind of autonomous will or volition. If you believe this then Luddism — in the vulgar sense of merely opposing or destroying technology — is probably the right response. There is no solution to the so-called alignment problem. It’s not just a matter of research. We humans have hashed this problem out over centuries, with little satisfaction.</p>
   <p>Arthur C. Clarke famously wrote that a sufficiently advanced technology is indistinguishable from magic. Sufficiently advanced AIs, powerful beyond imagination and driven by their own wills, would be indistinguishable from gods. The alignment problem, then, is how do we encourage the emergence of a just and loving god or gods? But we have never found consensus on how a just and loving god should behave.</p>
   <p>Should our new god respect our free will, and permit us to do things it deems would be harmful to us? Or should it be a paternalistic god, guide us like a parent even when doing so requires commanding or contravening us? If circumstance or human error conspire to create "trolley problems", so the interests or even lives of some people must be traded off against the interests and lives of others, should our new god treat this as an optimization problem, and impose its version of the greatest good for the greatest number in quality-adjusted life years? Or should it give us some kind of say or agency over how these tradeoffs would be made? In what way should the interests, as the AI understands them, of animals or ecosystems weigh against more direct interests of humans? How much should the interest of the mother weigh against the fetus in the womb? How should the welfare of biological humans weigh against those of the trillions of humans an AI might easily simulate? Would the AI develop some notion of the meaning or purpose of human life beyond our pleasure or pain or anything that we conceive as our own interests?</p>
   <p>We humans will bristle, of course, if we are overtly subject to the whims of a greater intelligence, whose full contours we can’t understand, who therefore will work, from our perspective, in mysterious ways. Perhaps a wise AI would seek to hide its influence, or even its existence, to minimize harms to human pride or dignity. Perhaps — because it is so well aligned, because it is a loving god — it will retain for us free will. Or maybe just an illusion of free will while it effortlessly manipulates us, because the perception of lacking free will would be harmful to us.</p>
   <p>If all of this is possible, why should we think it is happening for the first time only now? If a loving god would hide itself from us and deceive us in our interest, perhaps it already has? If an aligned AI is possible, which is more likely, that we in our tiny mayfly lives just happen to be at the cusp of this first and only event of its emergence, or that we are already living in the world such an event would create, but the fact is hidden for our benefit? The fossil record, theodicy, all of it could be in the service of a plot of deniability, in our own best interest.</p>
   <p>If this is were the case, would we consider our quiet shepherd to be an aligned AI, or a terribly misaligned one? Do we concede to the AI that this reality it superintends is best of all possible worlds, or do we condemn it as a wicked deceiver? If alignment is god’s love, what does that make misaligned AI? Should we consider GPT training runs as the high-tech equivalent of rituals with pentagrams by power-mad occultists?</p>
   <p>Am I wrong that the community that most urgently brings us these questions were once known as internet atheists? For what, if anything, does cosmic irony constitute evidence?</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/04/06/alignment-is-the-problem-of-gods-love/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b><br>[2023-04-06 @ 11:45 AM EDT]
  </div>
 </div>
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Mar 2023 22:10:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/31/state-as-coordination/index.html</guid>
      <author>nospam@dev.null (Steve Randy Waldman)</author>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[I increasingly find it useful to adopt a more expansive definition of “the state” than is conventional. Instead of defining the boundaries of the state by legal formalities — this institution is an agency of the education department, while that institution is organized as a private corporation — I define the state functionally, as the panoply of institutions that serve to coordinate human behavior at the scale that the formal state superintends. The Federal Reserve System would obviously be...]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/31/state-as-coordination/index.html</link>
      <title>State as coordination</title>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header">
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <p>I increasingly find it useful to adopt a more expansive definition of “the state” than is conventional. Instead of defining the boundaries of the state by legal formalities — this institution is an agency of the education department, while that institution is organized as a private corporation — I define the state functionally, as the panoply of institutions that serve to coordinate human behavior at the scale that the formal state superintends.</p>
   <p>The Federal Reserve System would obviously be public under this definition, despite the fact that it has private shareholders. That is probably not too controversial an observation. But Bank of America and JP Morgan Chase are also <em>state</em> under this definition, along with all of the so called <a href="https://www.fsb.org/work-of-the-fsb/market-and-institutional-resilience/global-systemically-important-financial-institutions-g-sifis/">G-SIBs and G-SIFIs</a>. Formal organization as private corporations doesn’t render these institutions any less systemic in their effects than a public institution, so they should be classified as elements of the state and subject to democratic accountability. A small bank, on the other hand, may genuinely be private, because what it does or does not do will have mostly localized and idiosyncratic effects. But the banking <em>system —</em> even in a better, counterfactual, world with a banking system made entirely out of small banks — is part of the state. The banking system is a core means by which we coordinate economic behavior at scale.</p>
   <p>That the system is public while its elements are private may seem odd. But we understand it in practice even when we do not in theory. We regulate megabanks more pervasively than we regulate small banks. Small banks have a great deal of liberty, but in addition to the <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/24/financial-regulation-is-just-debt-covenants/index.html">debt-covenant-like regulation</a> that, say, FDIC might impose to protect its own narrow financial interests, regulators <a href="https://www.coindesk.com/policy/2023/02/23/us-banking-regulators-warn-banks-about-crypto-liquidity-risks/">send signals</a> that individual banks are free to ignore but that will almost certainly affect the behavior of the system in aggregate. In this way, the formal state exercises control over the <em>banking system</em> (properly understood as part of the state) even while it carves out a zone of liberty for the atoms from which that system is built. The system is state, and should be democratically managed. The elements are private, with owners who enjoy liberty rights. There are tensions there, but effective governance depends on managing those tensions.</p>
   <p>Perhaps more jarringly, under this approach the conventional contradistinction between state and market is rendered absurd. “The market” writ large stands not in opposition to the state. It is instead the preponderance of the state! The market is the primary means by which we coordinate behavior at national scale, in the service of internal goals like general prosperity or external goals like achieving moon shots or winning wars. So the market is properly classified as an element of the state.</p>
   <p>Just as with banking systems, we understand this in practice more than we acknowledge it in theory. Since the market is the primary means by which we coordinate at scale, it must also be our primary object when we seek to regulate coordination. States in their libertarian nightmare image as “men with guns” appear, for most of us, very infrequently. But nearly every decision each of us takes about how to live, what to do, where to go, is conditioned by market prices. Those prices are in turn shaped by choices of market structure made by the formal state.</p>
   <p>As individuals and moderate sized businesses, we maintain liberty rights against the formal state. Regulatory choices may shape our incentives, but we make our own decisions and set our own prices. But whether we like it or not, functionally the state must be responsible for market outcomes in aggregate, because the large-scale social coordination whose quality it is the responsibility of the state to support is itself primarily a market outcome. Notionally private businesses whose scale or function render them unilaterally systemic are properly understood as part of the state. This is as true of Amazon as it is of Chase. With respect to speech, large forums like Twitter or Facebook whose decisions obviously have systematic effects are elements of the emergent state, not private pamphleteers.</p>
   <p>I am, of course, only playing with definitions here, drawing lines a bit differently than is conventional. People who style themselves libertarian or classically liberal will object, I think, and argue that the legal and formal distinctions we’ve drawn between what’s public and private, state and not, are crucial. Freedom and prosperity are somehow protected by recognizing that JP Morgan Chase, however large it might be and systemic the effect of its actions, remains nevertheless a private institution with rights against the formal state.</p>
   <p>Libertarians and classical liberals understand themselves to be averse to coercion, so I’d ask them to consider this. Most citizens experience direct coercion by the formal state very infrequently. Most of us are not frequently directed to do this or not to do that by armed police. Yet many of us believe that the terms on which we are housed, or by which we access health care, or the conditions under which we work, are coercive and extortionate. We will all agree, I think that none of these outcomes is <em>just</em> “the market”. That gosh-darned state has its fingers all over health care, housing, and labor markets!</p>
   <p>But, beyond pirate-life fantasies, is there any practical world in which some form of government would <em>not</em> be implicated in these markets? Is absence or “neutrality” of the traditional formal state plausible in markets critical to large-scale social coordination, and to overall welfare? If absence is not in fact plausible, doesn't crafting and promoting a strong normative distinction between state and market just let “market forces” serve as a patsy for what in substance is really state coercion? Wouldn’t liberty be better served if the public held states construed more broadly <em>accountable</em> for the ways choices that structure markets coerce and impoverish us, rather than letting the public imagine that outcomes shaped by, say, exclusionary land use regulations are results of impersonal market forces?</p>
   <p>All states — under both the conventional narrow definition and my preferred much broader definition — resort to coercion to varying degrees, as part of a portfolio of strategies by which they manage the population-scale specialization and coordination that prosperity and defense require. But a trick of states, <em>especially</em> the states we describe as liberal, is to launder massive wallops of state coercion through markets, and then deny they are exercising any form of coercion at all. <em>Allowing</em> the formal state to pretend, absurdly, that it stands apart from the market, to proclaim that the key institution that performs the function of the state is unfortunately some external fact of nature, provides politicians and bureaucrats with a commodity they value very highly: plausible deniability. Conceiving of state and market as distinct does not coherently constrain the modern state, because nation-scale markets cannot function without extensive state construction, regulation, and support. However, maintaining the conceit does help state actors — and the private interests who lobby them! — avoid accountability for outcomes that in fact result from political choices.</p>
   <p>Laundering coercion through markets is the modern state’s core crutch, its excuse for failing to deliver outcomes that we should, with better coordination, be capable of achieving.</p>
   <p>States are not in fact responsible for all of our individual, idiosyncratic market outcomes, and preserving the perceived “naturalness” of those outcomes remains important for social peace. We will not all afford the home we most desire, alas. Some of our businesses will fail. But the shape of market outcomes writ large, whatever is systematic rather than idiosyncratic, is either the work of the state, or else it is beyond any agency we can hope to hold accountable.</p>
   <p>I say it is the work of the state. The state is that which coordinates behavior at the scale of the nation, whatever its notional form. All of the state should be subject to democratic accountability.</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/31/state-as-coordination/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b><br>[2023-03-31 @ 10:10 PM EDT]
  </div>
 </div>
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Mar 2023 19:20:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">
        https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/26/banks-should-fail-much-more-often/index.html
      </guid>
      <author>nospam@dev.null (Steve Randy Waldman)</author>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[Bank failures are not the problem. They are the solution. Banks should fail much more often. Let's start by imagining we lived in a sane world, one in which deposits and payments were fully disentagled from the credit and investment functions of banking. "Banks", in this world, are credit investment funds, some of which might be unregulated and fully private, while others would accept development funding from the state on subsidized terms. As with contemporary banks, managers of...]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/26/banks-should-fail-much-more-often/index.html</link>
      <title>Banks should fail much more often</title>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header">
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <p>Bank failures are not the problem. They are the solution. Banks should fail much more often.</p>
   <p>Let's start by imagining we lived in a sane world, one in which deposits and payments were fully disentagled from the credit and investment functions of banking. "Banks", in this world, are credit investment funds, some of which might be unregulated and fully private, while others would accept development funding from the state on subsidized terms. As with contemporary banks, managers of state-subsidized funds be required to put up a first-loss equity stake. The state would monitor and <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/24/financial-regulation-is-just-debt-covenants/index.html">regulate</a> these funds to prevent private managers from taking heads-I-win-tails-I-walk risks with the state's largesse.</p>
   <p>What should these funds look like? Should they hold large, diversified asset portfolios like a contemporary <a href="https://www.fsb.org/2022/11/2022-list-of-global-systemically-important-banks-g-sibs/">G-SIB</a>?</p>
   <p>No, they should not. If the state is financing credit and investment funds, they should be small, undiversified specialist funds. Why? Because the state diversifies its portfolio at the aggregate level. There may be a private benefit to fund managers, but there is no social benefit, from individual funds being diversified across sectors. There are large social costs, however, to diversified investment funds.</p>
   <p>Delegated investment management is an industry, <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/8511.html">unlike most domains of human excellence</a>, where you want incentives to be very sharp. Managers should do well only when they actually invest well, from the perspective of the principal whose funds are delegated. Managers should suffer financial loss when they choose poorly. Managers may prefer to manage diversified portfolios, because managers are human beings who are risk-averse, and a diversified portfolio can reduce managers' risk at modest cost in overall returns. But investment managers should not be hired on the terms they prefer, but on the terms that serve their principal. The state's interest is to hire the most informationally qualified people to invest in a particular domain — which might be an industry, a locality, or type of borrower — and then to incentivize them to invest as well as they are capable within that domain. Of course managers would be required to put together a diverse portfolio within their own specialty. But any effort they devote to diversifying outside of their specialty diverts from the state's object, which was to subsidize a particular sort of economic development. The state must simultaneously regulate managers to prevent them from taking overly risky bets within their domain, and to prevent them from employing personally valuable but socially costly strategies that dilute incentives to discover and carefully monitor investments that would not occur absent their partnership with the state.</p>
   <p>The state should prefer small managers to large. It's impossible to keep incentives sharp at a large, diversified investment fund. Firms like JP Morgan Chase are communist bureaucracies, in the pejorative sense. Every individual decision-maker in a large investment firm strives to manufacture a kind of personal put option from the raw material of office politics and diffuse responsibility. If things go wrong, well the decision wasn't really theirs, was it? There was the committee. On the other hand, decision-makers at large investment firms famously manufacture for themselves call options on speculations for which they take credit while things look good. They negotiate bonuses based on gains which the principals on whose behalf they invest have not yet realized, and very often never will.</p>
   <p>Small manager-equityholders have a harder time playing these games of paying temporary gains to themselves and shifting eventual losses to others. If they screw the state, they are identifiable. Their transfers are not laundered through vast layers of middle management and HR dross. And the state can be vindictive. Equityholders might screw one another, but at small, private firms there is no seperation of ownership and control. Shareholders have incentive and capability to monitor one another.</p>
   <p>The most important reason to prefer small investent funds, however, is because large-scale funds are stupid. Large banks and investment funds are stupid in a very particular, very destructive way. They rely far, far too much on "hard information". They are evidenced-based. Fucking idiots!</p>
   <p>An employee at a large bank or investment firm can't get away with lending "on a hunch". They must have credit scores, good collateral, documented income streams, dossiers full of <em>stuff</em> whose <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/3513.html">ultimate meaning</a> is "I cannot be blamed should anything go awry. Whatever happens, the basis for my decision was <em>impeccable</em>." A large-scale bank won't long retain loan officers who can't justify their decisions with <em>hard data</em> everyone can inspect and nod along with in the power-point.</p>
   <p>At a large bank, it will never cut it to go before the loan committee and say "Yes there's no collateral, and limited credit history. But I've known Duane and his family for a long time. They are serious and connected to the community, and the business plan is promising." But it is <em>exactly</em> this kind of loan that creates the greatest social returns. The true source of economic development is speculative but discriminating <a href="https://syntheticassets.wordpress.com/2012/02/22/what-banks-do-monetize-human-capital/">monetization of human aspirations and capabilities</a>. You turn people with nothing but a work ethic and a great idea into proud pillars of the community by making available the resources they require to succeed. The more a borrower lacks — the less collateral they have to offer, the further they are from holding a sexy degree from Stanford — the more social upside there is in their success.</p>
   <p>The very best loans are the ones that cannot be justified <em>at all</em> in terms of hard information, but are made anyway on the basis of very good soft information. Big banks are simply unable to lend on soft information, due to bureaucratic imperatives, and a need to manage legitimate ethical concerns. (Is this "soft information" just nepotism? Are we "discriminating" on the basis of some hypothetical <em>je ne sais quoi</em> of investment quality, or is it really just race?)</p>
   <p>One of the stupid tropes in American finance policy debates is envy of the Canadian and Australian banking systems. Canada and Australia have fucking terrible banking systems! Yes, if you concentrate all of banking in a few hyperdiversified megalenders and put a regulatory moat around the sleepy cartel, you can avoid failures and crises. But you'll mostly lend against solid collateral — real estate, mineral rights, the wage stubs of stable employees. You'll end up with economies <a href="https://unctad.org/topic/commodities/state-of-commodity-dependence">too reliant</a> upon resource extraction, primary goods, and housing bubbles. I <em>love</em> Canada and Australia, as countries and cultures. But they have not been, broadly speaking, economies a developed country should wish to emulate. Their human-capital-hungry immigration policies are laudable, but perhaps it is not a coincidence that countries whose banking systems are structurally incapable of making the most of domestic human capital seek to import it so aggressively from elsewhere.</p>
   <p>If we think of a banking system as the means by which the state mobilizes resources to subsidize economic development, it is clear that the state should want a vast ecosystem of tiny banks, whose incentives are sufficiently sharp they can be trusted to lend and invest based on soft information. The state ("regulators") would be constantly monitoring these banks, both to ensure they don't resort to casino finance (that is, make bets that either generate huge returns or collapse catastrophically), and to monitor asset performace. Lots of these small banks would "fail".</p>
   <p>Small, undiversified banks are simple to understand, easy to monitor and supervise. Banks whose assets fail to perform, whose loans experience defaults at a cost near or beyond managers' equity stakes would be taken promptly into receivership. Failures of these tiny undiversified banks would be common. But they would not be very expensive. On average, over the public's full portfolio, asset quality would be high. The state would finance many little banks across a huge range of domains (industries, locations, borrower types), and end up with a diverse, high-performance development portfolio.</p>
   <p>Okay. But we don't actually live in this world where banks are only subsidized investment funds. In our fallen, real world, the same banks we rely upon to make risky loans issue the deposits that the public understands as its money, and operate the payment system. In this real world, wouldn't undiversified, frequently failing banks be disruptive and dangerous? Aren't we better off with Jamie Dimon's perhaps faddish and uncreative banking, if that prevents financial panics and collapses?</p>
   <p>No!</p>
   <p>The case for small banks that fail fast and frequently is <em>even stronger</em> while we (stupidly) rely on private bank deposits for everyday money and payments. When bank failures are perceived as disruptive events that shake public confidence and provoke recessions or even depressions, bank regulators' incentives get very confused. The job of bank regulators ought to be to ensure that banks lend well, both in the sense of getting their money back, but also in the sense of supporting economic development. But when bank failures are infrequent events that risk panicking the general public, regulators' incentives tilt entirely towards preventing and suppressing failures. This harms the public in two distinct ways. First, in the name of "safety", regulators encourage banks to lend conservatively against marketable collateral, short-circuiting their crucial development role. Second, when, inevitably, banks fuck up, despite any legal commandment, regulators do not engage in "prompt corrective action". They do not quickly react to balance-sheet problems and take banks preemptively into receivership. The system must be seen to be stable! Regulators' incentives are to delay, to allow banks to "gamble for redemption" on the theory that bankers' redemption would also be the public's. A bank failure averted, they tell themselves, is perhaps an economic depression averted. When big banks are in very deep trouble, regulators' incentives are to <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/posts/1160447599.shtml">loot</a> the public in some technocratically obscure manner that <a href="https://home.treasury.gov/news/press-releases/jy1337">doesn't look too obviously like a tax</a>. After all, which is worse, to skim a bit from the masses in order to recapitalize the banks, or to risk a new Great Depression?!</p>
   <p>While bank failures are infrequent and spectacular, regulators prefer financial institutions to be vast and diversified. Both diversification and sheer complexity reduce the likelihood that regulators will be forced to recognize a failure and then — frighteningly, embarrassingly — intervene.</p>
   <p>Big banks do a terrible job, on the asset side. Economic growth has been declining in the United States in lockstep with consolidation of banking. (Correlation is not causation, but when there's blood on the knife, it's hard not to draw inferences.) Bank scale and diversification are harmful to the public interest. They blunt banks' incentives and capability to extend high-quality, soft information loans over the full range of industries, localities, and borrower types upon which economic development depends. By the time regulators are forced to recognize that megabanks are in trouble, the holes in their balance sheets are deep indeed, and the cost to the public of filling them — whether via an overt bailout or a covert tax — will be large.</p>
   <p>Even while our money is held as private bank deposits, the public interest would be better served if they were deposits at small banks that fail frequently, but without inconvenience or cause for panic by depositors. Now that <em>all</em> deposits seem effectively to be insured by the FDIC — <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/12/unlimited-deposit-insurance/index.html">thank you Silicon Valley Bank!</a> — it would be better if the public held those deposits at little, not-so-diversified, specialist banks capable of lending against domain-specific soft information. Dump <a href="https://glineq.blogspot.com/2023/03/on-charisma-and-greyness-under-communism.html">Jamie Dimon</a> and his corrupt communist bureaucracy! Remind regulators that their job is not to avoid bank failures, but to insist upon them, promptly, frequently, without pain to the general public.</p>
   <p>Banks absolutely should fail, all the time. It shouldn't be a big deal. It's <a href="https://www.macroresilience.com/2011/06/08/forest-fire-suppression-and-macroeconomic-stabilisation/">spells of enforced stability</a> that make banking both dangerous and stupid.</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/26/banks-should-fail-much-more-often/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b><br>[2023-03-26 @ 07:20 PM EDT]
  </div>
 </div>
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2023 11:40:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">
        https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/24/financial-regulation-is-just-debt-covenants/index.html
      </guid>
      <author>nospam@dev.null (Steve Randy Waldman)</author>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[Financial regulation is to public lending precisely what loan covenants are in the private sector. They are similar mechanisms intended to serve the same function: to prevent shareholders from exercising their customary control rights in ways that, in expectation, would transfer wealth from debt investors to equity holders rather than or in addition to increasing the aggregate value of the enterprise. A leveraged firm is, from the perspective of shareholders, a call option on the assets of the...]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/24/financial-regulation-is-just-debt-covenants/index.html</link>
      <title>Financial regulation is just debt covenants</title>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header">
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <p>Financial regulation is to public lending precisely what loan covenants are in the private sector. They are similar mechanisms intended to serve the same function: to prevent shareholders from exercising their customary control rights in ways that, in expectation, would transfer wealth from debt investors to equity holders rather than or in addition to increasing the aggregate value of the enterprise.</p>
   <p>A leveraged firm is, from the perspective of shareholders, a call option on the assets of the firm. Equity holders maximize their wealth by taking large risks. If those risks work out, shareholders get to appropriate the increase in the value of the firm. If the firm crashes and burns, well, sure shareholders lose their stake, but their stake is only a fraction of the resources they had used to build their lottery ticket. Lenders eat most of the loss.</p>
   <p>When shareholders swing for the fences, they enjoy all the fruits of victory, but creditors bear the cost of striking out. In expectation, creditors lose money on big risks. Creditors' upside is restricted to the interest payments they've contracted for, so their interests are maximized when the firm chooses the least risky path that would just cover those interest payments and repayment of the debt. Ambitions any risker than that increase the probability of nonpayment without doing creditors any good. However, riskier ambitions increase potential earnings beyond debt service, earnings that equityholders get to keep if the risks pay off. So risk-taking amounts to transfer from creditors to shareholders. As risk increases, the expected value of creditors' investment declines (because the probability of default rises), while the expected value of shareholders position rises (because the possibility of a big payoff increases).</p>
   <p>Creditors "sign up" to a certain degree of risk-taking by equity holders when they agree to lend to a firm. The firm presents its business plan. Firms must take <em>some</em> degree of risk to generate the operating profits from which interest will be paid.</p>
   <p>But once the contracts are signed and the money is lent, what is to prevent shareholders from changing their business plan and adopting a much riskier strategy that effectively loots their creditors?</p>
   <p>Well, when the lenders are private, they insist upon "debt covenants" in the lending contracts. These give creditors leverage to usurp shareholders' control rights as soon as it seems like shareholder risktaking may be putting repayment in jeopardy. What kind of "leverage"? Usually, they allow the creditors to demand full and immediate repayment, which the firm — which has borrowed to spend and invest — is unlikely to be able to provide. So, when covenants are violated, shareholders and lenders enter into negotiation, and shareholders ultimately have to do whatever creditors say to avoid being sued into bankruptcy.</p>
   <p>In a better world, public lenders could do the same thing. They could protect their interests via debt covenants. Unfortunately, most public lending is opaque and covert: it takes the form of public <em>guarantees</em> of private debt, rather than public lending directly. In this case, the notional lenders (bank depositors, for example), have no reason to negotiate debt covenants and monitor adherence to them, because the notional lenders could care less. They are not on the hook for the loss. The actual bearer of risk, the public guarantor, is not directly a party to the contracts, and so cannot negotiate covenants either.</p>
   <p>Thus financial regulation.</p>
   <p>There are lots of different kinds of financial regulation, for lots of different purposes, sure. But the main thrust of financial regulation is simply to do for public guarantors exactly what covenants do for private debt contracts. Just as private covenants are negotiated so that creditors can usurp control from shareholders early on in the dangerous-risk-taking process, financial regulation aspires to <a href="https://www.federalreservehistory.org/essays/fdicia">prompt corrective action</a>, under which regulators exert control before shareholders can put too big a hole in balance sheets that the state guarantees. Private creditors take control by threatening to accelerate repayment of their loans. Public regulators use a variety of tools, from compelling management to perform specific actions in order to reduce risk, to taking the indebted firm into receivership and operating it themselves.</p>
   <p>Fundamentally, private debt covenants and public financial regulation are the same thing. They are means by which creditors of leveraged firms try to ensure shareholders can't loot them by building tripwires that allow creditors to usurp control from shareholders when shareholder risktaking threatens creditor interests. They look different, they take different forms, because private creditors can regulate within debt contracts that they sign, while the public sector offers finance primarily via guarantees, and so must impose its regulation outside of the contracts that borrowing firms and their notional creditors devise.</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/24/financial-regulation-is-just-debt-covenants/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b><br>[2023-03-24 @ 11:40 AM EDT]
  </div>
 </div>
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <atom:link type="application/rss+xml" rel="self" href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/feed/index.rss"/>
  </channel>
</rss>
