<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss 
version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>drafts — interfluidity</title>
    <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/index.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[Feed for blog 'drafts — interfluidity' generated by unstatic]]></description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2024 23:35:15 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>https://github.com/swaldman/unstatic</generator>
    <docs>https://cyber.harvard.edu/rss/rss.html</docs>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2024 14:10:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">
        https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/02/11/situated-versus-unsituated-virtues/index.html
      </guid>
      <author>nospam@dev.null (Steve Randy Waldman)</author>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[Why is the world like it is right now? Why does it seem that we are putting more of ourselves than ever before into efforts to help, to make the world a better place, but we seem collectively to be growing only more incompetent? We are, as individuals, the largest, best educated cohort of human beings that have ever lived on Plant Earth. Sure, maybe Harvard teaches more woke stuff, or maybe we are manipulated by TikTok and Fox News or whatever. There have, nonetheless, never been more humans...]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/02/11/situated-versus-unsituated-virtues/index.html</link>
      <title>Situated versus unsituated virtues</title>
      <dc:creator><![CDATA[Steve Randy Waldman]]></dc:creator>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header">
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <p>Why is the world like it is right now?</p>
   <p>Why does it seem that we are putting more of ourselves than ever before into efforts to help, to make the world a better place, but we seem collectively to be growing only more incompetent?</p>
   <p>We are, as individuals, the largest, best educated cohort of human beings that have ever lived on Plant Earth. Sure, maybe Harvard teaches more woke stuff, or maybe we are manipulated by TikTok and Fox News or whatever. There have, nonetheless, never been more humans more capable and skilled at any other moment in human history. Todays' graduates of Harvard — and today's graduates of every State U — can read and write, perform mathematics, and make use of unprecedented technical tools more capably than any generation in history. If you are into IQ, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flynn_effect">Flynn Effect</a> means we are about as smart as we have ever been.</p>
   <p>Yet collectively, we are fucking idiots. If I may <a href="https://www.azquotes.com/quote/1407287">quote</a> Larry Summers, look around.</p>
   <p>I want to posit a very simple explanation for much of our aggregate incapacity. We now devote ourselves much more to <em>unsituated</em> rather than to <em>situated</em> virtues. But constructive action depends primarily on accomplishing situated activities, which the extremity of our dedication to unsituated virtues now undermines.</p>
   <p>What do I mean by "situated" and "unsituated" virtues? Unsituated virtues are virtues we can all recognize based on widely shared information and values. Situated virtues, on the other hand, are legible only within the context of specific institutions or circumstances. Only insiders, suffused in real-time institutional knowledge that would be difficult to formalize or communicate broadly, even perceive the choice set under which some actions would be virtuous and others destructive. Situated virtues encourage action that would further the mission of an institution in ways too indirect or internal or intuitive to easily communicate, let alone justify, to outsiders.</p>
   <p>Racial justice is an unsituated virtue. We all understand why racial justice would be a good thing and is a goal worth striving towards, or conversely how it is a shibboleth that woke elites abuse in order to subjugate working people and then legitimate that usurpation with tokenistic "diversity". You don't need to actually work in admissions at some specific university to understand or participate in this debate. The director of admissions at an elite college, the (now deposed) board of the San Francisco Unified School District that devoted pandemic year to an ill-starred renaming project, the HR director of any major corporation, all understand the project of racial justice on similar terms.</p>
   <p>Chris Rufo <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2023/03/new-college-florida-ron-desantis-takeover/673556/">famously understood nothing</a> about my <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/02/27/new-college/index.html">alma matter</a> before making it a battleground over "DEI". He didn't need to. His project is a "long march through" the institutions to counter what he perceives as the same long march through from the other side. His worldview leaves no room for the day-to-day, invisible-problems-solved, particular-goals-accomplished lifeblood of each institution. They are all just pieces on a vast chessboard, enacting a contest legible to all of us who let "politics" become our vocation and entertainment.</p>
   <p>"Woke" and "anti-woke" both are pursuits motivated by unsituated virtues. Obviously, to activists within each of these projects, the other is not motivated by any virtue at all, but by vice. Whoever is right, whoever is wrong, they share the same fundamental characteristic: They are driven by an "idealism" — or a "grift", whatever — that is not tightly tethered to the particularities of the institutions they seek to alter. Their project is overarching. It supercedes little details. They may eventually have to attend to idiosynchracies in order to bend those institutions to their will, but the direction of the bending is determined long prior to that attention.</p>
   <p>Another unsituated virtue is making money. Like woke and antiwoke, whether in some broad sense you consider making money virtuous or vicious is besides the point. It is a virtue in the sense that it is a thing many of us individually and collaboratively pursue. We behave as though making money, and making more money, would be a good thing. We certainly try to achieve it.</p>
   <p>The "shareholder value revolution" that took root in the 1970s was explicitly and proudly a project intended to subordinate situated virtues (which economists disparaged as "agency costs") to the unsituated virtue of profit maximization. The theory was that profit maximization promotes economic efficiency and social good, so whatever firms do that is not conspicuously profit maximization — any way they attend unnecessarily to internal, invisible projects and concerns — can only constitute waste. By incentivizing managers to focus solely on externally legible shareholder value — and ripping away cash flows that might otherwise "burn a hole in managers' pockets" — the revolutionaries sought to make the real world fit a simple economic model under which perfectly competitive profit maximization yields at least Pareto optimal outcomes, if not a true maximization of <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/5149.html">welfare</a>.</p>
   <p>This project was rich with an irony its protagonists mostly failed to notice. Politically they allied themselves with the Friedrich Hayeks of the world. But Hayek's enthusiasm for market mechanisms was <a href="https://www.econlib.org/library/Essays/hykKnw.html">based precisely on humility</a> about what disembodied wise outsiders could possibly know about a world in which welfare-relevant information is radically and illegibly dispersed.</p>
   <p>The shareholder value revolutionaries were not driven by humility. They were sure that an absurdly stylized model connecting immaculate profit-maximizing firms, share prices, and social welfare was all they needed to understand. They had no compunction about imposing the crudest incentives as strongly as possible for precisely the purpose of overwhelming any invisible, illegible, particular concerns that might interfere with the project of maximizing near-term — and therefore long-term, because our protagonists believed markets "efficient" — share prices. And so we emerged with leaner, more efficient, firms. Like <a href="https://www.vox.com/money/24052245/boeing-corporate-culture-737-airplane-safety-door-plug">Boeing</a>.</p>
   <p>Our poisonous overdedication to unsituated virtues is now structural. It is inseparable from the very transactional kind of society we've let usurp the banner of liberalism. Which was the chicken and which was the egg I don't know. But employers no longer offer anything like a lifetime career ladder, while the most skilled professionals often defer, or indeed never take on, very long-term institutional commitments. At a personal level, I'm deeply attached to continual reinvention and nomadism. But into what kind of institutions, what kind of societies, do all we nomads compose? And how does that liberty <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/8392.html">affect those less well-placed</a> to pick-up stakes and reinvent themselves when things go awry?</p>
   <p>The incentives of the portable professional are quite different than those of a dedicated lifer. Our careers flit between many firms in the private sector, or many roles and positions in nonprofits or public service. Skills we develop pursuing situated virtues aren't necessarily portable. They don't translate easily into resumé items. Whatever deep institutional know-how we acquire is rendered obsolete with our next pivot. A school board member can use her racial justice activism as a springboard for all kinds of other roles. It constitutes achievement legible to sympathetic outsiders. If she devotes the same energy to quietly organizing conversations, resolving internal disputes, facilitating consensus, all of which contributes to excellences in education provision that may or may not show up in standardized testing? From the outside all she has been is a faceless bureaucrat. She might receive a glowing reference, from a crony.</p>
   <p>So individually, rationally, we look for overlaps between whatever our organizational roles might be and externally legible, unsituated virtues. But by seeking the kinds of achievements that help build our personal brands, we quietly deform institutions that we constitute, and starve them of the kind of work whose dividends are more subtle and collective. We end up with very brilliant people occupying all the roles of very dysfunctional organizations. Increasingly we find ourselves quite explicitly letting pursuit of unsituated virtues override the more specific purposes and goals of the institutions we participate in. (See <a href="https://www.tampabay.com/opinion/2023/03/04/florida-new-college-what-we-lose-when-we-ignore-stewardship-competence-column/">New College</a>, the <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2020/11/12/audubon-society-claims-intimidation-threats-436215">Audubon Society</a>, etc.)</p>
   <p>This story has a lot of parallels, and touches on a lot of themes I've written about before.</p>
   <ul>
    <li>
     <p>"Situated versus unsituated virtues" is an institutional analog to <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/8511.html">extrinsic vs intrinsic motivation</a> at an individual level.</p></li>
    <li>
     <p>I think increasing reliance on <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/26/banks-should-fail-much-more-often/index.html">hard information rather than soft information has destroyed the unique role</a> banks used to play in economic and social development. Abjuring soft information in pursuit of scale has rendered banks little more than crony-capitalist, too-big-to-fail gatekeepers between citizens and the use of state money. Soft information is information that cannot easily be made universally legible and verifiable. Acting on soft-information is necessarily a situated virtue.</p></li>
    <li>
     <p>The financial analog of a very transactional social liberalism is the cult of liquidity, which is the <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/posts/1209978923.shtml">antithesis of investor commitment</a>. Perhaps firms are better run and managed with investors who must devote some attention and voice to the management of firms they invest in, rather than investors all of whom imagine they can costlessly exit if the firm is mismanaged, or who simply diversify away any care.</p></li>
   </ul>
   <p>Sometime in the 1980s, I think, David Letterman had on some MENSA person who was allegedly the smartest person in the world. So, he asked, why haven't you cured cancer?</p>
   <p>We have all become that person. More or better education, always the liberal cure-all, is beside the point. It's our institutions that are illiterate, not the individuals who people them.</p>
   <p>Garett Jones wrote a tweet that, more than a decade ago, I <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/4218.html">characterized</a> as "the single most insightful economics tweet of all time". He wrote</p>
   <blockquote>
    <p>Workers mostly build organizational capital, not final output. This explains high productivity per ‘worker’ during recessions.</p>
   </blockquote>
   <p>Jones has since deleted this tweet. It was probably already out of date when he penned it. Times have changed, and not for the better.</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/02/11/situated-versus-unsituated-virtues/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b>
   <br>
    [2024-02-11 @ 02:10 PM EST]
  </div>
 </div>
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Tue, 6 Feb 2024 11:10:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">
        https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/02/06/demographic-transition-is-just-specialization-and-trade/index.html
      </guid>
      <author>nospam@dev.null (Steve Randy Waldman)</author>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[On The New York Times' "Matter of Opinion" podcast, Ross Douthat worries about collapsing birth rates: I am interested in the problem of birthrates worldwide and in the developed world, and concerned about the consequences of demographic decline. Modest demographic decline leads to slower economic growth, even potentially negative economic growth. It leads to incredible burdens on old-age pension systems because you don’t have enough younger workers paying into them. And it leads to a lot of...]]>
      </description>
      <link>
        https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/02/06/demographic-transition-is-just-specialization-and-trade/index.html
      </link>
      <title>Demographic transition is just specialization and trade</title>
      <dc:creator><![CDATA[Steve Randy Waldman]]></dc:creator>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header">
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <p>On <em>The New York Times'</em> "Matter of Opinion" podcast, Ross Douthat <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/02/02/opinion/gen-z-gender-political-ideology.html?showTranscript=1">worries</a> about collapsing birth rates:</p>
   <blockquote>
    <p>I am interested in the problem of birthrates worldwide and in the developed world, and concerned about the consequences of demographic decline. Modest demographic decline leads to slower economic growth, even potentially negative economic growth. It leads to incredible burdens on old-age pension systems because you don’t have enough younger workers paying into them. And it leads to a lot of alienation and literal physical isolation.</p>
    <p>So if you look, though, at cases, like South Korea — and there are other countries headed rapidly in that direction — we aren’t talking about something an interesting sociological and economic question of, Well, what does society look like as it ages and has fewer kids? We’re looking at the potential for actual crisis and actual collapse.</p>
    <p>South Korea’s fertility rate is in the 0.7s right now, which means roughly for every two people, there is 0.7-ish offspring. If you just project that trend forward, South Korea’s population doesn’t just diminish. It starts to actually collapse over a two-generation time scale.</p>
    <p>...</p>
    <p>[W]hen the problem is, your birth rate is 1.5, and it would be better if it was 2, then it’s a somewhat-normal policy problem. And you can argue about what kind of social safety net you should have. And in those arguments, I have sympathies with liberals.</p>
    <p>I’m one of the conservatives who favors the new child-tax-credit provisions that Congress is considering this week. Those things have the potential to make it economically easier to have and rear kids. And they can affect the birth rate on the margins.</p>
    <p>But there are clearly just deeper, profound cultural forces at work here, which is why this trend shows up everywhere.</p>
   </blockquote>
   <p>Does neoliberalism count as a deeper cultural force?</p>
   <p>A simple definition of neoliberalism is expanding the scope of market logics in regulating human affairs, even into spheres that were traditionally the province of other institutions, like state, church, or family.</p>
   <p>The first result of market logics, the one <a href="https://www.gutenberg.org/files/3300/3300-h/3300-h.htm">extolled by Adam Smith</a>, is division of labor. Each worker should focus and become expert in one very specific aspect of production and then exchange the thing they produce most abundantly and excellently for other things. In aggregate we will then produce much more than if each of us made amateur attempts to produce for ourselves all that we require. "Cottage production", whereby an individual craftsmen artisanally produces all of the stages of a thing — let alone all of the stages of all of the things they might require! — is an epithet in economics. Even the production of pins, Smith famously described, is best meted out to specialists in a variety of tiny steps.</p>
   <p>From an economic perspctive, childrearing is a form of cottage production whose opportunity cost is gargantuan in the form of time misspent by specialists who could be producing valuable things.</p>
   <p>Child-rearing may not be quite as divisible as pin-making. We farm out aspects of education and health care to specialists, but it may be the case that shepherding infants into productive adulthood requires intense, indivisible, relationships with just a few consistent caregivers. Nevertheless, the most basic economic reasoning suggests that these caregivers should be specialists who devote themselves solely to caregiving, who trade the results of their caregiving excellence for the other goods and services they require.</p>
   <p>Market logics are not learned by catechism. They impose themselves invisibly, "naturally", via rewards and punishments embedded in the apparently disjoint choices of people who do or don't transact with us. The inefficient are left alone, and to be left alone is to be left to die. As Karl Marx famously <a href="https://www.marxists.org/archive/marx/works/1845/german-ideology/ch01a.htm">put it</a>:</p>
   <blockquote>
    <p>For as soon as the distribution of labour comes into being, each man has a particular, exclusive sphere of activity, which is forced upon him and from which he cannot escape. He is a hunter, a fisherman, a herdsman, or a critical critic, and must remain so if he does not want to lose his means of livelihood; while in communist society, where nobody has one exclusive sphere of activity but each can become accomplished in any branch he wishes, society regulates the general production and thus makes it possible for me to do one thing today and another tomorrow, to hunt in the morning, fish in the afternoon, rear cattle in the evening, criticise after dinner, just as I have a mind, without ever becoming hunter, fisherman, herdsman or critic.</p>
   </blockquote>
   <p>How then, "if he does not want to lose his means of livelihood", in our capitalist and far-from communist societies, should we expect him to be a hunter in the morning and a parent in the evening?</p>
   <p>Demographic transition — collapsing birth rates — is not the puzzle. The puzzle is the continued pervasiveness of cottage parenting despite its inefficiency and cost. Why don't we leave parenting to lower-cost specialists in the developing world and then purchase the workers they produce with nice wages?</p>
   <p>Contra Douthat, precisely becuase the trend shows up everywhere, "deep, profound cultural forces" seem unlikely. Douthat and his colleagues lament that birth rates have collapsed even in European countries with generous "safety nets", and especially in culturally quite distinct South Korea. But neoliberalism broadly construed and the "high-tech late modernity" that constitutes Douthat's antinatal everywhere are the same place.</p>
   <p>Elsewhere I have written that <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/5031.html">"'incentives to produce' are incentives to rig the game"</a>. They are equally incentives not to have children. The level of outcome dispersion we've invited in the name of "incentives to produce" means that a child tax credit of one or two or five thousand dollars per child doesn't begin to put a dent in the opportunity cost of raising the child.</p>
   <p>Even the Nordics — the best arranged countries on Earth — can't overcome this. The Nordics do an excellent job of clipping the downside of social outcomes. The state covers many of the basics of childrearing. Nordic countries <a href="https://www.euronews.com/health/2023/03/17/fertility-in-europe-which-countries-have-the-highest-and-lowest-numbers-of-live-births-per">do pretty well on birth rates</a> relative to peers of similar wealth. But not well enough to replace their own populations. Neoliberalism suffers also from its upside, from the outsize lives it delivers to those who devote themselves to its games and win.</p>
   <p>The relationship between wealth and natality is nuanced. When wealth is certain, its increase is likely pronatal, as people can bank on greater resources to cover the burdens of childrearing. But when wealth is uncertain, when it is delivered via tournaments that deliver outsize rewards to winners, then increases in "expected" (meaning average) wealth likely translate to <em>decreases</em> in natality. The bigger the prize, the greater the cost of anything that will reduce your chance of winning.</p>
   <p>American conservatives (I'm not accusing Douthat here!) love to sexualize everything. If only we could shove women back into the kitchen, they'd become bored enough to find meaning again in raising a bunch of kids. Maybe so! But that's just a specific case of a general proposition. To the degree that we can clip the opportunities available to households outside of raising kids, then households will choose to raise more kids.</p>
   <p>Instead of insisting women stay home, we might just impose steep levels of taxation at incomes just above what a single devoted earner might achieve. That would end the <a href="https://isbn.nu/0465090907">"two income trap"</a> for upper-middle class families. Affluent households would face little penalty for letting one parent specialize in market income and the other parent focus on childrearing, homemaking, and community-building. Choosing the location of the tax threshold would involve tradeoffs between how broadly in the population we wish to encourage natality versus neoliberal concerns about incentives to produce.</p>
   <p>Alternatively — preferably I think — rather than reducing the opportunity cost of childrearing by putting a tight ceiling on other opportunities, we could increase the payout associated with childrearing. The cost of raising a child well, in direct expenses and the opportunity cost of time, is tens of thousands of dollars per year. Policy encouragements that have been tried and mostly failed are simply nowhere near the relevant magnitudes.</p>
   <p>Adam Smith's ghost still haunts us. If we did compensate child rearing at levels roughly commensurate with its costs, there'd be more kids all around, but a disproportionate share of the new children would likely come from households that efficiently specialize in child rearing rather than seek other forms of market income. I suspect that, for contestable social reasons, we'd dislike that market logic and limit the number of compensated kids per household, or phase-in compensation only with other forms of income.</p>
   <p>But there really is no mystery. In our thoroughly marketized societies, we don't find it odd that other goods and services whose remuneration is lower than the opportunity cost of the inputs they require are meagerly supplied. We don't like to talk that way about children, but it is precisely the same situation. Various social institutions once encouraged childrearing anyway. Neoliberalism is just the project of demoting and eclipsing those.</p>
   <p>To their credit, many social conservatives have now reckoned with the inconsistency between their values and the neoliberal project. However, many of the most prominent contemporary pronatalists come from the tech/crypto/VC space, and have not grappled with or even recognized the contradictions among their allegiances. They have invented a new dialectic — <em>synthesis, antithesis, optimism</em> — and it is enough for them.</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/02/06/demographic-transition-is-just-specialization-and-trade/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b>
   <br>
    [2024-02-06 @ 11:10 AM EST]
  </div>
 </div>
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Fri, 2 Feb 2024 12:30:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">
        https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/02/02/nimble-nationality-will-define-state-capacity/index.html
      </guid>
      <author>nospam@dev.null (Steve Randy Waldman)</author>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[One thing perhaps we can agree is that Israel/Palestine serves as a cautionary tale. Israel/Palestine is the story of a failed state. Two populations, which define and distinguish themselves in terms of identities deemed immutable by virtue of history and religion and ethnicity, have failed now for decades to come to some accommodation under which they might peacefully coexist and jointly govern the small sliver of land they occupy between the Jordan River and Mediterranean Sea. If it weren’t...]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/02/02/nimble-nationality-will-define-state-capacity/index.html</link>
      <title>Nimble nationality will define state capacity</title>
      <dc:creator><![CDATA[Steve Randy Waldman]]></dc:creator>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header">
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <p>One thing perhaps we can agree is that Israel/Palestine serves as a cautionary tale.</p>
   <p>Israel/Palestine is the story of a failed state. Two populations, which define and distinguish themselves in terms of identities deemed immutable by virtue of history and religion and ethnicity, have failed now for decades to come to some accommodation under which they might peacefully coexist and jointly govern the small sliver of land they occupy between the Jordan River and Mediterranean Sea.</p>
   <p>If it weren’t for the all the dead bodies, it would almost be farcical. All of these big words — “rights” of national self-determination, of return, claims to history and indogeneity — just obscure and perpetuate and justify failures to address the most basic prerequisites of human flourishing on a territory the size of a postage stamp. It’s like academic politics are so bitter because the stakes are so small. Only now with murder.</p>
   <p>People live in places. People’s welfare is determined much more by the quality of the communities that occupy those places than by anything they can do as individuals. You may be very good at your work. You wouldn’t have done well in Somalia.</p>
   <p>The first prerequisite of flourishing for any geographically situated human community is peace. But peace, Thomas Hobbes <a href="https://www.gutenberg.org/files/3207/3207-h/3207-h.htm">reminds us</a>, is not the human default. We are quarrelsome creatures. Peace only obtains when some form of <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/6970.html">authority</a> emerges that serves as a basis for coordinating punishment of freelance banditry within a territory, and for coordinating defense against marauders from without.</p>
   <p>Both “nation" and "state” are names we give to this kind of coordinating authority. But the two words suggest quite distinct approaches. A “nation” is a community of people inculcated with some shared sense of who they are and how communal life should be arranged, who generally act in accordance with that sense. Members of a nation discourage violations of that shared understanding almost instinctually. Those who act in accordance with the shared understanding are welcomed in the collaborations that render a community prosperous and lively, while those who defy them face exclusion and stigma, and, for severe violations, improvisationally organized vigilanteism. A "state" is quite different. States are made of formal institutions and laws, written codification of how people are to behave, superintended by a hierarchical body which enforces its authority via a near monopoly in practice over coercive violence.</p>
   <p>The "nation-state" is the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rTTixlelryY">Reese’s Peanut Butter Cup</a> of human coordination at scale. It takes from nation a commonality of understanding that renders authority largely self-enforcing. It takes from state the stabilizing backstop of coercive enforcement, and also the dynamism that centralized codification — and therefore a centralized capacity for recodification — can engender.</p>
   <p>There are tensions between the two approaches. Laws can change faster than shared understandings. The shared understandings of a nation constitute the sacred. Nation-states must sacralize the everchanging law itself, must inculcate not just an understanding of how we live, but a meta-understanding that how we live is mutably governed. Today’s laws are owed the same reverence today that yesterday’s were owed yesterday, even when they are mutually contradictory. Conversely, the formal bureaucracy of the state must be attentive to and not outstrip the nation’s capacity to make sense of itself. The nation must be able to recognize in the changing law adaptations and improvements of how the community understands itself, rather than its undoing.</p>
   <p>Beyond peace, the quality of a geographically situated community is a function of how effectively and adaptively it can coordinate, and at what scale. A geographically situated community different elements of which are at war (however literally or figuratively) with one another, or are simply not mutually intercoordinating among one another, will be weaker and less prosperous than a community capable of recruiting its full population into coordination with little internal contestation. Holding constant the quality of internal coordination, larger nation-states will enjoy greater prosperity and military power than smaller nation-states. (Small nation-state that seem to defy this logic usually have some much larger patron with which they are deeply integrated in trade and which attends to their defense.) In practice, there are often tradeoffs between scale and quality of coordination. But when those can be overcome, bigger is better.</p>
   <p>So a nation-state is a natural monopoly subject to economies of scale. The essence of a state is a near monopoly in practice over coercive violence. The essence of a nation is a shared understanding that promotes effective coordination across the community. For economies of scale to be realized, mutually compatible, if not identical, understandings of how to act must be widely held. If a nation-state means to prosper and defend itself, it must cultivate some form of national identity that its population will almost universally adopt.</p>
   <p>Historically, the main solution to this problem is assimilation. France becomes a nation-state when it erases its historic provinces, to which grand stories and identities once attached, and replaces them with bureaucratic departments. This was <a href="https://www.gouvernement.fr/partage/9898-83-departements">openly a project</a> to supplant provincial identities with a new understanding of self and community that would be shared across the full territory of the French state. To this day, the French nation is evangelical and assimilative, willing to make equal citizens of all who enthusiastically adopt its shared self-understanding, discouraging to the point of persecution communities on its territory that insist upon understandings which the larger polity does not deem compatible.</p>
   <p>Ethnostates, on the other hand, are disfavored by the logic I have described. When there exists some prior ethnic group whose traditional self-understanding will serve as the national complement to a formal state, the scale of the nation-state is limited by the scale of that <em>ethnos</em> in the borders of some territory that it dominates.</p>
   <p>Ethnicity is not usually conceived as very permeable. You are of our tribe, or you are not. In a world (our real world) where self-perceived ethnic communities are not well sorted geographically, ethnostates cannot achieve the universality of shared identity that an effective nation-state requires. It will necessarily govern subpopulations not of the nation, for whom coordinating authority will derive primarily from the ungloved fist of the state.</p>
   <p>Hard power without soft power is always fragile power. Repression and especially conflict are costly — in a fiscal sense, but more importantly in potential coordination foregone. Repression and conflict are constant, when people inhabit territory a state claims but are excluded from the nation, from the shared understanding and identity under which citizens conform to state authority even without any proximate threat of coercive violence.</p>
   <p>It is one of history’s typical ironies that “the Jews” and “the Palestinians” have a great deal in common while they murder one another. Both are “nations” whose self-conceptions are incompatible with an inclusive, and therefore effective, state. As long as the narrative that binds each group is membership based on shared history and grievance, each of the nations is necessarily exclusive of the other. The “self-determination” of one in the form of an ethostate requires the continual oppression of the other, poisoning the lives of victor and vanquished alike, unless and until near complete separation or elimination can be achieved. Both Israel and Palestine, as they conceive themselves, are bad projects, practically and ethically. They rot from their seeds.</p>
   <p>But the rest of us ought not rest on our laurels. As the Israelis point out when they complain about “double standards”, there is a little bit of ethnostate in most contemporary nation-states. On the one hand, modern liberal states promise to be states for all their citizens, to provide equal rights and equal dignity to all. On the other hand, the same states privilege language and cultural practices historically associated with one demographically dominant ethnicity.</p>
   <p>Unlike Israel, however, most liberal states tolerate and encourage assimilation by outsiders. Only Jews can be Jews in Israel. Anyone who moves to France or Germany, who adopts and embraces the language or culture, can become German. The United States is so new, and the provenance of its population is so mixed, that its national identity is openly synthetic and syncretic. But the United States has nevertheless constructed a strong national identity, despite little anchoring in any historical ethnicity.</p>
   <p>Modern, liberal nation-states are more resilient than gated ethnostates like Israel, but they are far from infinitely resilient. That word “liberal” often connotes a claim that not only will the state provide equal rights and dignity to individuals who assimilate, but that they will also provide equal rights and dignity to different <em>communities</em>, including communities who choose not to assimilate, who do not join the shared self-understanding that defines the nation tethered to state.</p>
   <p>That claim is a pretense, a dangerous conceit. The nation part of nation-state is not optional. Ethically, we might wish for a world in which states could be neutral between radically diverse communities. But states rely upon citizens having understandings of themselves and of social affairs that, again, need not be identical, but must be mutually compatible. It is the nation in nation-state that enables the citizenry as a whole to mostly govern themselves, resorting only infrequently to deployment of the state’s hard power as an unwelcome but sometimes necessary backstop.</p>
   <p>The function and purpose of nation-states — effective social coordination at very large and impersonal scales — cannot be achieved relying solely or even primarily upon the blunt instrument of direct state power. Shared understandings and customs that become the basis for tacit, automatic, instinctual, decentralized coordination are not optional. A state is only effective if it superintends a nation. A nation is only effective if, beneath the amorphous evolving haze of custom and identity, sits the defining and stabilizing bone structure of a state.</p>
   <p>We are in an era of mass migration, which presents challenges to nation-states, and therefore to the capacity of humanity as a whole to coordinate at scale and prosper at scale, because that happens almost entirely under the auspices of strong nation-states. Our collective failure to achieve “convergence”, under which less developed states would find a path towards matching the prosperity and safety of developed states, means that, for much of the world, migration to a more developed state is your best and perhaps only strategy to give your kids a decent life. Climate change is likely to supercharge migration pressures, as some places grow too dangerous or barren to support their existing populations.</p>
   <p>Humanity is not a democracy, but a thing about the humans is everybody gets a vote anyway. You may wish we did not face the challenge of mass migration, but the migrants get a vote, and they say that we must in fact face it. You can adopt the MAGA “America First” response to this new era, but to do so is to elect to become Israel, and to pay the costs — military, economic, and moral — that Israel now is paying. If your main response to growing demand for mass migration is to become restrictionist, then you will have to militarize your borders in order to enforce your restrictions. You will have to become authoritarian internally to detect and deport those who have evaded your restrictions, and to manage security threats created by citizens of your own state who will not assimilate to the nation you propose, because they sympathize with migrants.</p>
   <p>Israel is a brittle ethnostate because it cannot or will not bring people who live on its territory or who insist disruptively that they will live on its territory into its national community. It bears large costs to preempt conflicts and to fight them, larger costs in terms of social and economic potential foregone, and worst of all, social deformation, shame, and moral injury from all the murders the path it has chosen does require it to commit.</p>
   <p>The states of North America and Europe will be no different if we place ourselves in the same situation.</p>
   <p>The alternative to Israel is as it has always been America, the America of <em>e pluribus unum</em>. The United States is not, and never has been, a state without a nation. The America I grew up in had a deep and profound national identity. This was not mere “creedal democracy”, the thin, very intellectual idea that our quasi-worship of the Constitution and a few civic ideas was the basis for our common nationhood.</p>
   <p>No, the United States had, and still has, a very thick, tacit and instinctual, national identity. We have customs and a language and weird idioms that we share. We have American food, like pizza, bagels, kung-pao chicken, hamburgers, sushi, and gyro sandwiches. It doesn't matter that these things derive from other nations, or whether they are "authentic" to their roots. They are ours now.</p>
   <p>There is nothing more British these days than having a curry. In Germany you find wonderful kebabs. This reflects the most virtuous form of assimilation, where the shared understanding that defines the nation not only accepts migrants as individuals, but adapts the shared natural culture to include and celebrate what they as communities bring. Host country citizens recognize that they gain from “appropriating” the most congenial bits of migrants’ cultures. America would not be America without pizza! Migrant communities feel more welcome when at least some of their old self-understandings are celebrated by their new communities. They become more willing to walk the challenging, painful, road of ceding much of who they have been and how they understood their world in order to adopt something quite different. When migrants’ “ethnic” commodities — foods or foot massages or whatever — are embraced by home country natives, that helps to lubricate their assimilation economically, as it means there are services they are particularly well-placed to sell. Xenophilia is an incredibly adaptive national characteristic, and it will only be more so going forward.</p>
   <p>When restrictionists in developed countries say they don’t mind, aren’t against, immigration, they just want it to be legal and ordered and organized, that is fine and they are right. We do not want, should not abide a situation where our laws, whose tacit sanctity renders our national success possible, are run roughshod by new migrants that must learn also to hold them sacred if we are to collectively succeed.</p>
   <p>But at the same time, we cannot succeed if the laws we enact are ill adapted to our actual circumstances. To save Miami from sea-level rise, we could ban high tide. We could place militarized cops on the beaches, fire machine guns at each transgressing wave. The tide will still come. Our laws cannot be shaped only by our preferences. Reality will have its say.</p>
   <p>As pressures for mass migration accelerate, we will all become some admixture of Israel, Lebanon, and melting-pot America. Some countries will double-down on restrictionism become small, brutal, deformed shadows of the political communities they might have been. Some will accept the tide of bodies into the territory of their states, but prove unable to merge the diversity of communal identities and worldviews that come with those bodies into a coherent nation, leading to reduced social trust, impairment of the nation-state’s ability to coordinate at scale, bitterness among natives and new immigrants both, conflict, and authoritarianism.</p>
   <p>But some countries will manage what the United States managed in the 19th and 20th Centuries, to accept the bodies but also join the minds of new citizens into a continually evolving understanding of the nation to which they now belong. Countries that manage this will achieve the economies of scale that nation-states can gain from larger populations without bearing the deadweight, deadly costs of interethnic conflict, militarized borders, deterrent brutality.</p>
   <p>No law can make the immigration problem go away. The world is as it is, and the drivers of mass migration are likely to get stronger not weaker. The question before us is not “whether” or “how many”, but “how?” What set of practices and institutions might bring natives and migrants together under a version of national identity sufficiently nimble and attractive and adaptive to join and guide us all?</p>
   <p>For nation-states capable of answering this question, the coming era will be a time of growth, opportunity, and national greatness. For nation-states whose identities and self-understandings are incapable of adapting to integrate large numbers of new migrants, it will be a time of crisis, authoritarianism, decline, bitterness, and shame.</p>
   <p>We’d best get working on how.</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/02/02/nimble-nationality-will-define-state-capacity/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b>
   <br>
    [2024-02-02 @ 12:30 PM EST]
  </div>
 </div>
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2023 14:35:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/12/28/how-to-regulate-ai/index.html</guid>
      <author>nospam@dev.null (Steve Randy Waldman)</author>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[Predictably, The New York Times is suing Open AI and Microsoft for copyright infringement. OpenAI has used The Times' text to train their large language models. I have no opinion on the legal merits of the case. Courts will try invent some line between fair use and infringement under existing law that balances various interests in this brave new world of LLMs. But I hope that Congress will act to address the question more holistically and creatively than courts can. Here is my two point plan...]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/12/28/how-to-regulate-ai/index.html</link>
      <title>How to regulate AI</title>
      <dc:creator><![CDATA[Steve Randy Waldman]]></dc:creator>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header">
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <img src="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/12/28/how-to-regulate-ai/never-held-accountable.jpeg" width="100%" alt="Printed slide, 'A computer can never be held accountable, therefore a computer must never make a management decision.'">
   <p>Predictably, <em>The New York Times</em> is <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/12/27/24016212/new-york-times-openai-microsoft-lawsuit-copyright-infringement">suing</a> Open AI and Microsoft for copyright infringement. OpenAI has used <em>The Times'</em> text to train their large language models. I have no opinion on the legal merits of the case. Courts will try invent some line between fair use and infringement under existing law that balances various interests in this brave new world of LLMs.</p>
   <p>But I hope that Congress will act to address the question more holistically and creatively than courts can. Here is my two point plan for what Congress should do:</p>
   <ol>
    <li>
     <p>Congress should declare that big-data AI models do not infringe copyright, but are inherently in the public domain.</p></li>
    <li>
     <p>Congress should declare that use of AI tools will be an aggravating rather than mitigating factor in determinations of civil and criminal liability.</p></li>
   </ol>
   <h4><a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/12/28/how-to-regulate-ai/#congress-should-declare-that-big-data-ai-models-do-not-infringe-copyright-but-are-inherently-in-the-public-domain" id="congress-should-declare-that-big-data-ai-models-do-not-infringe-copyright-but-are-inherently-in-the-public-domain" name="congress-should-declare-that-big-data-ai-models-do-not-infringe-copyright-but-are-inherently-in-the-public-domain" class="anchorlink"></a>Congress should declare that big-data AI models do not infringe copyright, but are inherently in the public domain.</h4>
   <p>The moral justification for this is clear. Big-data AI models are summarizations of the work of large publics. They are a whole much greater than the sum of the parts. Their value comes from a public much too broad and amorphous to constitute an identifiable party who might license inputs or be compensated.</p>
   <p>The law should explicitly reject claims like <a href="https://helpx.adobe.com/stock/contributor/help/firefly-faq-for-adobe-stock-contributors.html">Adobe’s</a> that, by training models on only work explicitly licensed to them or in the public domain, they address this concern. Even if every individual input dots the i's and crosses the t's of prior copyright law, modeling very large corpuses of work extracts information not only from the direct inputs summarized, which might in theory be compensated, but from all the inputs and influences to the creators of those direct influences.</p>
   <p>These models not simply new creative works derivative of particular other works. The modeling process is something new, a tool designed to extract regularities and patterns and ideas that characterize the domains they model as a whole. The training set is a telescope and a microscope. Their object of study is human creation very broadly, and these fruits of human creation can belong only to humanity writ large.</p>
   <p>In order to immunize themselves from claims of unlawful expropriation, including both old-school copyright claims and new claims on behalf of the public itself, anyone who trains AI models would have an affirmative obligation to publish and place into the public domain both the results of their training — the “weights” — and the structure of the model under which those weights take their meaning, including code, such that people or ordinary skill in the domain could quickly stand up and run new instances of the model.</p>
   <p>This would, you might object, take away some of the incentive to train large models. It would. But the commercial incentives to develop AI models are already very strong. The Microsofts of the world that want to integrate AI tools into their products can easily afford to fund them as loss leaders. Business communities more broadly, who perceive opportunities to increase productivity or reduce labor costs, would find that pooling resources to train open-source models easily pencils. Academics and the public sector would train public models as well.</p>
   <p>On the other side of the training set, you might object that putting these models in the public domain does nothing to put food on the table of the creators whose work is ingested to produce them. That is very true. But it is a common result of new technologies that old activities that once were remunerative cease to be so. <a href="https://a16z.com/the-techno-optimist-manifesto/">Marc Andreeson is wrong</a> to imagine that inherent characteristics of technology and capitalism ensure that as some means of subsisting are eliminated, better and more remunerative jobs are sure to replace them because of higher marginal productivity or whatever. At an individual level, many people whose work has been technologically obsoleted suffer harms from which they never fully recover. At a broader level, <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/1116.html">only the expansion of social democracy</a> has rendered technological development and something like full employment remotely compatible.</p>
   <p>Widespread use of large-language models will demand a more redistributive state, as much of the public will find these models undermine their (our) current source of market power and therefore ability to command a decent wage. Nevertheless, it remains true that, with decent governance, we are collectively better off when we can all do more with less human work. The right way forward is to continue to let technology make us, in this narrow sense, “richer in aggregate", but use the institution of the state aggressively to ensure that richer in aggregate means all of us live better lives and none of us bestride the narrow world like Elon Musk.</p>
   <p>AI models do nothing at all to hinder human creativity. For many people, generative AI will enable, has already enabled, new means of creative expression. But what is less scarce is less valuable in commerce. It is not creativity that is threatened, but the creative professions.</p>
   <p>I don't think we want market forces to turn 90% of today's creative professionals into nurse's assistants, plumbers, and staff for upscale resorts. Art lives not just in its artifacts, but in collaborative relationships between human artists and audiences, and in forms of collaborations where roles of producer and consumer are less distinct than those terms suggest. The value that we derive from creative work is not independent of who produced it and how. Creative work constitutes the symbols and sinews of human communities. It is the substrate, scaffolding, upon which we develop our notions of the sacred.</p>
   <p>Creativity and capitalism have always sat awkwardly together. They will now sit even more awkwardly. There will be no papering over the divergence between exchange value and value. I don't think we should romanticize the era that is ending. The imperatives of remuneration have recruited beautiful hearts to compellingly sanctify arrangements that are horribly profane. There have been so many beautiful ads.</p>
   <p>We will all still need to eat. We will be less able to pretend that "free markets" can somehow reconcile meeting that need with performing our highest purposes. The challenge we face has always been political. I think it's neither wise nor virtuous to try to suppress generative AI in order to retain a <em>status quo</em> under which some of us could pretend that it was not.</p>
   <h4><a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/12/28/how-to-regulate-ai/#congress-should-declare-that-use-of-ai-models-is-an-aggravating-rather-than-mitigating-factor-in-determinations-of-civil-and-criminal-liability" id="congress-should-declare-that-use-of-ai-models-is-an-aggravating-rather-than-mitigating-factor-in-determinations-of-civil-and-criminal-liability" name="congress-should-declare-that-use-of-ai-models-is-an-aggravating-rather-than-mitigating-factor-in-determinations-of-civil-and-criminal-liability" class="anchorlink"></a>Congress should declare that use of AI models is an aggravating rather than mitigating factor in determinations of civil and criminal liability.</h4>
   <p>AI models clearly have a lot of potential uses. But they just as clearly could cause a great deal of harm. AI models can <a href="https://isbn.nu/0553418815">launder</a> what we might otherwise recognize to be invidious discrimination by race or sex. They can render “objective" or “rational” the <a href="https://www.972mag.com/mass-assassination-factory-israel-calculated-bombing-gaza/">murder of children <em>en masse</em></a>. They can run down pedestrians and then, in their digital confusion, <a href="https://www.freep.com/story/money/cars/general-motors/2023/11/15/gm-general-motors-cruise/71586950007/">drag them for twenty feet</a>.</p>
   <p>There’s <a href="https://twitter.com/bumblebike/status/832394003492564993">that slide, usually attributed to an IBM presentation from the 1970s,</a> stating “A computer can never be held accountable, therefore a computer must never make a management decision.” No sentence ever has more completely misunderstood the imperatives of management. Managers, who are inevitably made responsible for much more than they can control, constantly, desperately, seek means of escaping accountabilty for the decisions that they calculate will be in their interest. An <a href="https://www.mckinsey.com/">entire, storied industry</a> is based upon serving this compulsion.</p>
   <p>If the public allows it, the first and most important use of LLMs will be to allow managers, firms, and governments to shirk accountability, either by deferring to the expertise of "objective” models, or by blaming inevitable, regrettable glitches that of course we must accept for the greater good while developing any brilliant new technology.</p>
   <p>So the public, via the state, must not allow it. Commercial users of AI models will argue that the law should treat occasional “mistakes” resulting from AI model outputs to be unintended and unforeseeable outcomes of ordinary business processes, for which their liability should be minimal. If the self-driving car hits a pedestrian, that is regrettable, but of course there can be no criminal charges, as there might have been for a human driver who dragged a person 20 feet after striking her. If lots of people are wrongfully denied insurance claims by some black-box model, eventually perhaps some class-action lawsuit will succeed and make some lawyers rich and fail to bring back the dead. The firm will pay a financial settlement, a cost of doing business. Of course, if a human had systematically made the same error, and it was in the firm's or their own financial interest, the human might have been convicted of fraud. But a computer is eternally innocent.</p>
   <p>We should not treat computational models — of any sort, but especially models as unpredictable as LLMs — as legitimate and ordinary decision-making agents in any high-stakes business process. A computer cannot be held accountable, so the law must insist that, by definition, it is never a computer that makes a management decision. If it seems to anyway, and then it errs, the humans who deployed it were presumptively negligent. If it errs systematically in the interest of the firm, its human deployers were presumptively engaged in a conspiracy to defraud.</p>
   <p>An analogy I like to use is alcohol and driving. One way we could think about a person who causes a fatal car crash while intoxicated is that they did not have their wits about them, they did not intend to do the harm. It was a tragic accident when they were not at their best, so their culpability should be limited.</p>
   <p>Another way we can think about the same event is that <em>precisely because</em> after drinking a person would foreseeably not have their wits about them, the very act of drinking without making alternative transportation arrangements increases their culpability for the accident. They should have known well in advance of the tragedy itself they were doing something risky. The risk that they took was essential to the crime, not just the fact of the horrific consequence.</p>
   <p>Each of these framings is legitimate. They just express different social values. If, as a society, we place a very high value on the joys of alcohol-lubricated conviviality and our liberty of automobile-mediated assembly for that purpose, then we might treat intoxication as a mitigating factor in car accidents, and accept their prevalence as a price we pay for a greater good. If we don’t place so high a value on a good time, or we place a much higher value on reducing car accidents, then we would adopt the framing that we have, under which alcohol is an aggravating factor.</p>
   <p>We face a similar social choice with LLMs. The business automation they might enable should be scored as a social good, to the degree they free humans to do either work only humans can do well or to enjoy greater liberty and leisure. But low-quality work and the risk of laundering fraudulent or unethical practices through an ablution of mysterious technology should be viewed as a grave social costs. There is no such thing as perfect balance. We have to decide whether to err on the side of license — on the theory rapid deployment of these technologies will make us richer and happier and better — or of caution, because we think quality of deployment outweighs any benefit of speed. Fifteen years ago, before our collective experience of social media and surveillance capitalism and platform peony, I would have opted for license. Now, however, I strongly favor caution.</p>
   <p>Use of these technologies should not be banned, for almost any purpose. But our social presumption should be they are unreliable, experimental, susceptible to difficult to detect forms of abuse and predation by their deployers. Whenever things go wrong, their deployers are innocent until proven guilty only of the fact of deployment. Once it has been established that they have deployed these technologies in consequential roles, they become presumptively responsible, civilly and criminally, for all the harms wrought by systems they deployed but negligently failed to adequately supervise, or worse.</p>
   <p>That presumption would be rebuttable. If deployers can show that the system they created performs at least as well, caused no more harm than, systems in common use that do not use the technology, then they have not been negligent. Waymo, for example, has <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/12/20/24006712/waymo-driverless-million-mile-safety-compare-human">approached autonomous driving</a> with a great deal more caution than competitors Cruise and Tesla, such that in practice its cars have been much safer than human drivers. So long as this is the case, those responsible for deployment of Waymo vehicles should not be held liable, civilly and criminally, for reckless driving following the very few accidents involving its vehicles that do occur. Cruise and Tesla, on the other hand, would not succeed at rebutting a presumption of negligence.</p>
   <p>The purpose of the proposed legal regime would not be to ban these technologies from business processes. It would be to insist upon their high quality, from a social perspective, and ensure that quality is placed before imperatives that might otherwise lead businesses to profit by externalizing risk and harms.</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/12/28/how-to-regulate-ai/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b>
   <br>
    [2023-12-28 @ 02:35 PM EST]
  </div>
 </div>
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Dec 2023 12:20:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/12/14/norms-mean-you-cant-pull-rank/index.html</guid>
      <author>nospam@dev.null (Steve Randy Waldman)</author>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[Why does it matter that, as I argued in the previous post, “international law” is not law at all, but international affairs are governed by norms? It’s important because it changes how we should conduct ourselves completely. In a courtroom, you can argue points of law and win, even if many people do not like the verdict. When defense and plaintiff meet in a courtroom, they are not trying to persuade one another, or to persuade a broad audience of spectators. They are appealing to the authority...]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/12/14/norms-mean-you-cant-pull-rank/index.html</link>
      <title>Norms mean you can't pull rank</title>
      <dc:creator><![CDATA[Steve Randy Waldman]]></dc:creator>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header">
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <p>Why does it matter that, as I argued in the <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/12/10/theres-no-such-thing-as-international-law/index.html">previous post</a>, “international law” is not law at all, but international affairs are governed by norms?</p>
   <p>It’s important because it changes how we should conduct ourselves completely.</p>
   <p>In a courtroom, you can argue points of law and win, even if many people do not like the verdict. When defense and plaintiff meet in a courtroom, they are not trying to persuade one another, or to persuade a broad audience of spectators. They are appealing to the authority of the state. In a legislature, you can "lobby" a small group to change the law. This will durably change how the authority of the state is wielded, even if much of the public finds it horrifying.</p>
   <p>With norms, there is nothing like this. There is no authority to appeal to. Norms bind only by a continuing consensus of multiple parties who model, enforce, and reinforce them.</p>
   <p>Norms can certainly be codified. I am a great fan of <a href="https://www.missmanners.com/">Miss Manners</a>. Whether those codifications matter at all depends on whether some community continually agrees to be bound by them. When disputes arise, it is never enough to be “right on the merits", whatever you might think that should mean.</p>
   <p>In any dispute, it is not just the belligerents that are on trial, but also the norms themselves. The space of putative norms is large and contains contradictions. I condemn you aloud for farting at the dinner party. You condemn me for calling attention to a phenomenon that, Miss Manners will remind us, socially does not exist. <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/AmItheAsshole/">AITA</a>? It doesn’t matter which transgression some book says is more serious. The matter is decided by to whom the eyerolls and subtle turning-aways are directed.</p>
   <p>The habits of command are counterproductive in a normative context. Humans value their own agency. Badgering people to accept a norm you favor can prompt defiance. Norms are enforced by mutual consent. You must invite and persuade rather than demand. In any dispute over a putative transgression of norms, you can bribe or threaten to force others to take your side. But then rather than reinforcing the norm you ostensibly were upholding, you have undermined it. The norm you have reinforced is that people behave only transactionally, which is the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gray_goo">gray goo</a> of norms, undoing all others.</p>
   <p>In international affairs, we really do want a “rules-based order”. But what those rules are can be no ones to command. Over the past two decades, the United States has collapsed from a soft power to a hard power, has traded persuasion in significant measure by a kind of moral prestige for the crude application of carrots and sticks. Do whatever we say is good or we’ll sanction you.</p>
   <p>But hard power is weak power, finite and exhaustible. Only soft power delivers resilience and longevity. As we go forward — those of us who manage to go forward without being murdered or bombed or recruited into some madman’s campaign to murder and bomb — I hope that we can return to soft power. Not unilaterally. Soft power is not zero sum. Our good reputation need not rely upon others having a poor reputation.</p>
   <p>“International law” cannot be a substitute for mutually-reinforced norms. International law only has any meaning downstream from such norms. It has no other method of enforcement. A strange mix of idealism and careerism has led us to devote tremendous energy to an edifice of high-minded codification while neglecting the invisible foundation upon which it must rest. The result has been weaponized sanctimony rather than international peace.</p>
   <p>We do want a rules-based order. Where are these rules written, asks Vladimir Putin, and who has written them? They are good questions, but there can be no document. Russia and the United States both can bomb and bribe, can make high-minded speeches, write manifestoes, whatever. The United Nations can declare whatever it wants.</p>
   <p>But the rules are written in how we collectively behave, not in anything Anthony Blinken or Sergey Lavrov or Wang Yi can proclaim, or that the United Nations might ratify. We can only write the rules together. Those who demand deference rather than earn respect ultimately have the least say in their composition. Unfortunately, anyone can contribute to their decomposition.</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/12/14/norms-mean-you-cant-pull-rank/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b>
   <br>
    [2023-12-14 @ 12:20 PM EST]
  </div>
 </div>
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <atom:link type="application/rss+xml" rel="self" href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/feed/index.rss"/>
  </channel>
</rss>
