<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss 
version="2.0" xmlns:iffy="http://tech.interfluidity.com/xml/iffy/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>drafts — interfluidity</title>
    <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/index.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[Feed for blog 'drafts — interfluidity', generated by unstatic]]></description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 11:16:28 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>https://github.com/swaldman/unstatic</generator>
    <docs>https://cyber.harvard.edu/rss/rss.html</docs>
    <atom:link type="application/rss+xml" rel="self" href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/feed/index.rss"/>
    <iffy:curation>
      <iffy:recent last="5"/>
    </iffy:curation>
    <iffy:completeness>Content</iffy:completeness>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 10:05:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">
        https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2025/01/24/hard-information-soft-information-groupthink-corruption/index.html
      </guid>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[I use the term "soft information" quite a lot, but I think it's unclear to readers what I mean, and what "hard information" would by contrast mean. "Hard information" (think "hard data") is often taken to imply true or accurate or reliable information. That is very much not what I intend when I use the term. Usually when I am writing about hard and soft information, I am advocating greater reliance upon soft information, or lamenting our institutions' inability to make use of it. That'd be...]]>
      </description>
      <link>
        https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2025/01/24/hard-information-soft-information-groupthink-corruption/index.html
      </link>
      <title>Hard information, soft information, groupthink, corruption</title>
      <dc:creator><![CDATA[Steve Randy Waldman]]></dc:creator>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss uid-hard-information-soft-information-groupthink-corruption">
 <div class="entry-header-body-footer">
  <div class="entry-header">
  </div>
  <div class="entry-body">
   <div class="flexmark markdown">
    <p>I use the term "soft information" <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/04/14/seeing-like-a-ceo/index.html">quite</a> <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/02/11/situated-versus-unsituated-virtues/index.html">a</a> <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/26/banks-should-fail-much-more-often/index.html">lot</a>, but I think it's unclear to readers what I mean, and what "hard information" would by contrast mean.</p>
    <p>"Hard information" (think "hard data") is often taken to imply true or accurate or reliable information. That is very much not what I intend when I use the term. Usually when I am writing about hard and soft information, I am advocating greater reliance upon soft information, or lamenting our institutions' inability to make use of it. That'd be pretty dastardly, if by hard information I meant good information and by soft information I meant bad.</p>
    <p>My definition of "soft information" comes out of the banking literature I once studied as an abortive finance grad student. It's kind of a puzzle, I was taught, that banks even exist. Finance types, or at least finance types of the still very neoliberal aughts, treated markets as the best information aggregators the humans ever invented. Loans are marketable. When you and I want a loan, why don't we just issue a kind of personal commercial paper, and let potential lenders bid on the debt, establishing our market interest rate?</p>
    <p>Okay, you and I are small potatoes, so maybe "frictions" in issuing marketable securities explain why personal loans don't work this way. But businesses take bank loans too, sometimes pretty big ones!</p>
    <p>The traditional resolution of this puzzle is "soft information". A bank has intimate information about the businesses who bank with it. It can observe a whole arc of history, how revenues flow and how stable or unstable they are, how reliably the business pays its bills and what kind of cushion it maintains. Bankers often know the principals of their business customers personally, and develop opinions about their character, which J.P. Morgan himself, um, <a href="https://libquotes.com/j-p-morgan/quote/lbt8g6m">characterized</a> as the most important information in a credit decision.</p>
    <p>Some of the information bankers superintend can get aggregated into a credit score — hard information! — but much of it is simply not accessible to the rest of the market. Evaluations of character in particular depend upon personal contact, and are ideally drawn from longstanding, continuing, human-to-human relationships.</p>
    <p>So, the theory went, banks exist, or at least exist as lenders to business, because bankers can outperform markets in pricing debt, because they have superior information. Bankers have access to all the same "hard information" other lenders would have, but also to this "soft information", available only to them.</p>
    <p>If soft information is information only available to a particular party by virtue of its relationship with the subject of the information, by virtue of its <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/02/11/situated-versus-unsituated-virtues/index.html">situatedness</a>, then hard information is information whose content and provenance is accessible to everyone, information that is unsituated.</p>
    <p>A score issued by a credit bureau is "hard information" because every potential lender can access it and observe the same value. Although the reporting that informs the score is private, the procedure by which the scores are computed is broadly public. Sure, details might be proprietary. Everybody understands that structuring the computation had to involve making choices that were discretionary, that might have been made differently. If you disagree with those choices, you might argue the scores are inaccurate. But the credit bureaus make those choices, and promise to perform their scoring <em>consistently</em>. Lenders accept the scores, and take them as a pretty good proxy for creditworthiness.</p>
    <p>More than that, because everybody sees the same information, "hard information" can serve as the basis for public conversations in a way that a banker's soft information cannot. Civil servants and the interested public can deliberate and conclude that 620 should be the minimum score for a borrower whose loan will be purchased by a government-sponsored agency. We perceive this criterion as "objective". Since we will all have the same "hard information" about a given borrower, we can all evaluate whether they are eligible. J.P. Morgan might object that crucial aspects of character are not captured by the credit score. But we'd have a hard time structuring a national bureaucracy around information accessible only to people with personal relationships to the borrower.</p>
    <p>But J.P. Morgan was undoubtedly right! If we could in some trustworthy and dispassionate way incorporate the experience of people who know the borrower best, we'd find plenty of cases where it would in fact be wise to lend to a person with a low credit score, and be unwise to lend to a person with a high score. But "we" constituted as a large bureaucracy — public or private! Bank of America as much as Fannie Mae! — have no such trustworthy means. "We" do not know the borrower. "We" do not know and have little reason to trust individuals from whom the borrower might solicit character references. Independently scouting such evaluators would be costly, and the problem of evaluating our putative evaluators' character is no less difficult than evaluating the character of the borrower.</p>
    <p>So, in public discussion and in large bureaucratic contexts, we necessarily rely on hard information <em>even though we understand it to be inaccurate</em>. We acknowledge the information condensed into a credit score is imperfect. Nevertheless we often treat it as though it is the thing itself, rather than at best a noisy proxy of a thing we wish to measure. If there are two otherwise similar borrowers, one has a credit score of 550, the other has a credit score of 650, we lend to the latter because she is "creditworthy", and deny the former because she is not.</p>
    <p>The fundamental character of hard information is not "accuracy" or "quality", but its susceptibility to serving as the basis of social convention. We need to talk about things, to reason together, to decide together. Almost everything of interest to us is not directly accessible to our senses. Your and my "gut" evaluations would not be consistent with one another, could not provide a basis for consensus in our decisions. Often we have no perfect or even good measures of the thing of interest. So we invent something, as least-bad as we can. We make the arbitrary choices we have to make to define and structure a public measure, because something is better than nothing.</p>
    <p>Fabricated hard information like this is everywhere. What's the "inflation rate"? The US Bureau of Labor Statistics does its very best — really! But it necessarily makes arbitrary choices, applies <a href="https://www.bls.gov/cpi/quality-adjustment/hedonic-price-adjustment-techniques.htm">hedonics</a> to commodities with quantifiable measures of quality but omits them for goods without, etc. The Consumer Price Index it publishes gives us "hard information" by which we publicly reason about inflation. But different choices might have been made than those BLS makes, and those might yield different numbers and very different conclusions, especially over long periods of time.</p>
    <p>Has the "real income" of the median household grown over the last two decades? Under one set of numbers yes. Under another measure which, say, took into account the effect of <a href="https://compass.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/soc4.12884">income segregation</a> on the <a href="https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/aer.20150572">affluence of neighbors</a> as a form of housing quality, it might not have. Neither measure would be incontrovertibly more or less "accurate" than the other. But it's likely that one would become conventional, would predominate in public debate, would come to be taken as "the fact of the matter".</p>
    <p>The susceptibility of hard information to convention, to standing in for fact, means that it often serves to engender a very authoritative kind of groupthink. The information, however well-intended its construction, will along some dimensions, for some purposes, prove inaccurate and inadequate.</p>
    <p>Are Americans happy with their health insurance? After UnitedHealthcare CEO Brian Thompson was murdered, I saw incredulous responses on social media pointing to <a href="https://files.kff.org/attachment/Topline-Survey-of-Consumer-Experiences-with-Health-Insurance.pdf">polling</a> that said 81% of respondents rated their insurance excellent or good.</p>
    <p>It's not a secret in everyday American life that a lot of people really hate health insurance companies. Insurers are perceived as making tragic situations even more miserable by virtue of the bureaucracy they impose on the sick and those who are forced to advocate for them. They are perceived as contributing to the death (murder?) of patients upon whose treatments they impose delays. Your cancer won't wait for prior approval. It's metastasizing while they mull.</p>
    <p>Yet prior to Thompson's murder, this thing that everybody knows was largely inaccessible in policy-oriented conversation. Are people unhappy with their health insurance? The polling says no. You can bring in your anecdotes, how mad your cousin was, how your friend died after the imaging was delayed. But you could come up with as many stories of people having great experiences! The hard information says 81% of patients are happy with their insurance.</p>
    <p>Thompson's murder has brought attention to some obvious-in-retrospect considerations. When we are judging the satisfactoriness of something, the intensity of dispreference of a dissatisfied minority can matter. Dissatisfaction on behalf of others' experience rather than ones own can be relevant. (There's a literal survivorship bias in polling customers' own health insurance satisfaction. A disproportionate fraction of people who personally suffered awful experiences are no longer around to be polled.)</p>
    <p>We can construct measures that try to address these things. But we didn't before. Our conventional hard information blinded us. Data-driven groupthink laughed off claims that the experience of the insured was a burning problem. The policy community focused on universality rather than quality of coverage, and praised itself for the success of ACA on that score.</p>
    <p>If hard information risks a kind of upscale groupthink, should we rely upon soft information instead?</p>
    <p>Unfortunately reliance on soft information yields its own pathologies. When we rely upon information accessible only to particular people by virtue of their situation or perceived expertise, we cannot evaluate the quality of decisions. We open the door to unfairness in decisionmaking, sometimes intentional, often even when decision makers are doing their very best. Relying on soft-information decisionmaking risks corruption.</p>
    <p>Most obviously, if someone is going to be trusted to make consequential decisions based on special information and judgment that others cannot evaluate or verify, who's to say the decisions aren't motivated by self-interest? On the basis of purported soft information, I lend the bank's money to my own friends and family more freely and at lower rates than to others. Perhaps by informal arrangement my own prosperity rises with that of my friends. Perhaps what I actually know, through my vaunted soft information, is my friend will make speculative investments with the money and cut me in on any gains, while she'll fail to repay the bank if things don't work out. If my cut will be big enough, the upside might be worth risking my job.</p>
    <p>One might try to police conflicts of interest, ensure that whenever decisiomakers might have, or might even be perceived to have, a personal stake in the outcome, of course they should not be trusted to judge. But then you might condemn yourself to the worst of both worlds. You are relying upon a decisionmaker's purported special information while insisting she only decide under circumstances where in fact she lacks any special information. A perfectly ethical loan officer will have the bank lend to a person she has known forever and considers a friend in preference to others with "objectively" similar creditworthiness, if part of what she knows is that the friend would be mortified ever to default on a loan and would move heaven and earth not to. That's not a violation of the trust the bank has placed in her. On the contrary.</p>
    <p>A worst-kept secret of finance is that the entire project of investment banking is <a href="http://epicureandealmaker.blogspot.com/2011/01/some-people-never-learn.html">built on managing, rather than eschewing, conflicts of interest</a>. Top M&amp;A firms do not compete on price, but on the thickness of their rolodexes and the trust they have engendered in the investment community. Firms looking to raise capital understand that bankers will offer access to good customers on sweetheart terms, at prices where there is still money to be made. They calculate the <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/1781.html">"money on the table" they lose from underpricing</a> will be more than compensated by the number and wealth and quality of investors the schmoozy bankers bring into the deal. Perhaps this works out best for everyone. Firms raise more money than they would have via any alternative channel, and investors expect and get good deals from bankers they trust. Perhaps not, and one or both sides of the transaction gets told all this as a kind of fairy tale while they get screwed. The trouble with soft information is it's hard from the outside to tell. Often it's hard from the inside to tell!</p>
    <p>In the United States, we reflexively equate "nepotism" with corruption. Opportunities should be distributed according to degrees, or exam scores, or some qualification that can be expressed on a resumé as verifiable, hard information.</p>
    <p>But that's too easy, and dangerous. Nepotism can be wise, and not only for corrupt reasons. I may know about competences and character traits among family and close friends that no test score can easily capture. I might actually know my nephew is well-suited the job, even if his resumé is inferior to other candidates I know less about. If the job is high stakes and I set aside my soft information to go with the best resumé, I risk a consequential mistake.</p>
    <p>The difficulty is that outsiders — and, in many cases, the decisionmaker herself — cannot easily distinguish between corruption and wise use of soft information. If I think, <em>I love my sister and my nephew so I'll give him a great job</em>, then hiring him is corrupt. If <em>I know my nephew is ethical and hardworking and unusually insightful about exactly the sort of problems he will face</em>, then hiring him may be wise. Of course, I may persuade myself of the latter when I am motivated by the former. And you, on the outside, have no way to tell which is which.</p>
    <p>The "good government" impulse to avoid this challenge by relying on hard information only is not sufficient. Hard information is also imperfect. If I hire the best resumé from Harvard, I can <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/3513.html">justify the choice and no one can blame me</a>, but it may well be entirely the wrong choice, if what we actually care about are outcomes. People who style themselves meritocrats like to imagine that talent is both abundant and objectively demonstrable. In many contexts, neither is true. Being precious about appearing above corruption can itself be a corrupt choice. I protect my own reputation at the expense of the cause I am pledged to serve.</p>
    <p>Even when a decisionmaker uses soft information impeccably, when she makes the best choice possible given her full information set, soft information decisionmaking is susceptible to <em>structural corruption</em>.</p>
    <p>I know, I know. That sounds like "critical race theory". Chris Rufo is going to come and <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/02/27/new-college/index.html">destroy something else I love</a>. But the mechanism is so straightforward even Chris could understand it.</p>
    <p>A banker strives to make credit decisions as best she possibly can, with no bias whatsoever in terms of race or religion or nationality or other irrelevances. But our banker has her life and her own social circle. It is quite likely that her family, friends, and near acquaintances are not distributed among races and religions and nationalities in proportion to their frequency in the population.</p>
    <p>When our banker receives a loan application from someone in or near her social circle, she has meaningful soft information that can help guide her choice. When she receives the same application from outside her social circle, she does not. Given two candidates who are in fact creditworthy, it's quite possible she will be able to recognize the quality of the candidate within her social circle, but be unsure of the candidate outside of it. Soft information decisionmaking introduces a structural bias towards choices that the decisionmaker has special information about, even though there may be equal or superior choices elsewhere. Our banker is making the best choices she possibly can, using all of the information at her disposal, but from the outside it will appear that she is biased towards the races, religions, and nationalities prevalent in her own social circle. It's the structure of her acquaintanceship, rather than any invidious discrimination, that introduces the bias.</p>
    <p>So, where do we go from here? Relying solely on hard information does not in fact capture all of the good information that ought to go into making a decision, and leaves decisionmakers susceptible groupthink, mistaking conclusions drawn from flawed but conventional information sources for the best decisions. Relying freely on soft information renders it almost impossible to police corruption, and leaves even honest decisionmakers susceptible to personal or structural bias.</p>
    <p>What to do? I hope to think more about this in future pieces, but a difficult truth is answers will themselves be context dependent. It takes soft information to design roles and incentives under which decisionmakers can fully exploit all the information at their disposal, neither falling back lazily to the most easily defended hard-information criteria, nor abusing (consciously or otherwise) the trust placed in their soft-information judgment.</p>
    <p>What I hope I can convey for now is "evidence-based" or "data-driven" is not in fact a recipe for high-quality decision-making. High quality decisions in practice require recourse to information that cannot meet a standard of public evidence, and skepticism of information that appears to meet such a standard. That this is hard to discipline doesn't render it any less true.</p>
   </div>
  </div>
  <div class="entry-footer">
   <div class="post-metainfo">
    <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2025/01/24/hard-information-soft-information-groupthink-corruption/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b>
    <br>
     2025-01-24 @ 10:05 AM EST
   </div>
  </div>
 </div><!-- entry-header-body-footer -->
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 15:15:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/12/31/segmentation-fault/index.html</guid>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[The politics of migration from poor countries to rich is structured by exploitation and segmentation. For a migrant flow to be politically sustainable in the destination country, the migrants should constitute a labor force which [exploitation] works under conditions that would be considered exploitative from the perspective of natives of the rich destination country (although not necessarily relative to the norms of the source country); [segmentation] works under those conditions only in...]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/12/31/segmentation-fault/index.html</link>
      <title>Segmentation fault</title>
      <dc:creator><![CDATA[Steve Randy Waldman]]></dc:creator>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header-body-footer">
  <div class="entry-header">
  </div>
  <div class="entry-body">
   <div class="flexmark markdown">
    <p>The politics of migration from poor countries to rich is structured by <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/9548.html">exploitation</a> and segmentation.</p>
    <p>For a migrant flow to be politically sustainable in the destination country, the migrants should constitute a labor force which</p>
    <ul>
     <li>
      <p>[<em>exploitation</em>] works under conditions that would be considered exploitative from the perspective of natives of the rich destination country (although not necessarily relative to the norms of the source country);</p></li>
     <li>
      <p>[<em>segmentation</em>] works under those conditions only in segments of the labor market that citizens of the destination country have effectively withdrawn from and ceded to migrants, so that the migrant flow doesn't undermine natives' bargaining power in their own labor markets.</p></li>
    </ul>
    <p>When societies are unequal and divided, the <em>incidence of the surplus from exploitation</em> also becomes important. The case for immigration to natives is that "we all" benefit from exploitation of their labor. If the surplus value is thought to be captured by private bosses, rather than shared with the public in the form of low consumer prices or social democratic benefits, that will undermine the case for immigration.</p>
    <p>Immigration from poor countries is not so controversial in places like the UAE or Singapore. "Guest workers" have extraordinarily limited rights. They work in roles that native Emiritis and Singaporeans understand as proper to immigrants and do not seek, and are widely understood by natives to provide benefits that are broadly shared. We live like kings because they work like paupers.</p>
    <p>Immigration from poor countries becomes controversial in places where immigrants are, or are perceived to be, supported rather than exploited. <a href="https://www.chathamhouse.org/2021/06/denmarks-immigrants-forced-out-government-policies">Denmark</a> might be an example. Instead of natives exploiting immigrants (popular!), immigrants are seen as exploiting or harming natives (not popular!).</p>
    <p>Even when immigrants clearly do work under exploitative terms, immigration becomes controversial when migrants compete in the same labor markets as native workers. Then — even if "in aggregate" the destination country benefits from exploiting the migrant labor force — workers whose bargaining power is undermined become cross. Questions of the incidence of the surplus from exploitation come to the fore. Is immigration just a tool by which the rich get richer while immiserating and exploiting their own fellow citizens?</p>
    <p>In liberal states and social democracies, many of us have high-minded ideals, and pretend that migration from poor countries to rich should be embraced on moral grounds, rather than on the basis of exploitation. However admirable those ideals, this often yields unsustainable policy and dangerous backlash.</p>
    <p>Regardless of good intentions, migration yields its benefits and costs. Natives will in fact enjoy a surplus or bear a burden, the surplus from exploitation net costs of service provision and social disruption. Elements of society will experience an incidence of those benefits and costs, so even immigration that is net positive for natives may impose steep costs on certain groups.</p>
    <p>Framing migration in moral terms invites overlooking unsupportable costs, or celebrating benefits that are narrowly captured by some natives while imposing costs on others. It's great to believe that accepting migrants from difficult circumstances is a moral obligation. But that doesn't absolve us of carefully accounting for the burdens and benefits of taking on that moral obligation. It doesn't excuse us from building consent for our choices among the democratic public, or from ensuring that any burdens and benefits are shared fairly, another moral obligation.</p>
    <p>If you are "for immigration" in ways that don't seriously take these questions into account, you are for immigration only performatively. Those of us who do see immigration in moral terms should try to give immigrants as good a deal as is politically sustainable. That is, rather than try to maximize the surplus we extract from our immigration policy, as Singapore and UAE do, we should seek to vouchsafe from immigrants unmistakable benefits for natives, but for a limited tenure, while they "pay their dues". We must still exploit, enough that the migrant flow more than compensates its burden, providing natives with benefits that are widely recognized and broadly distributed. But once the cost has been covered, we can welcome them as coequal citizens rather than take them for all we can squeeze.</p>
    <p>In the United States, we do not in our public politics think clearly about these issues. We put things mostly in moral terms, pitting cosmopolitan human rights against against communal rights to protect ones kith and way of life. Framing things in terms of rights, as always, prevents us from thinking clearly about trade-offs and compromises.</p>
    <p>Nevertheless, over the years, the United States has found equilibria that quietly embrace the twin pillars of exploitation and segmentation. We criminalize a migrant labor force while winking at the businesses that employ them. The function of criminalization, of course, is not actually to <em>prevent</em> the flow of migrants, upon which many businesses quite depend. We criminalize in order to minimize the bargaining power of migrant workers, and maximize exploitation on behalf of natives. Spokespeople for industries like agriculture and meatpacking are quite candid that, absent this labor force, our food prices would be higher. (The cynical among us are left to wonder how much of this surplus from exploitation actually finds its way into lower prices for consumers, versus how much pads profits and managerial salaries.)</p>
    <p>We all quietly understand that these industries are segmented. Hand-harvesting of ground crops is "work Americans don't want to do", which means it's work Americans would not consent to do at the wages and under the conditions that criminalized, exploited laborers accept. In exchange for cheap food, Americans withdraw from these labor markets, cede them to maximally exploitable migrants.</p>
    <p>Exploitation. Segmentation.</p>
    <p>We all understand this bargain, even if we pretend we don't. Democrats get performatively mad at mistreatment of migrant workers, but don't actually upset the apple cart. Republicans sometimes make a show of pretending criminalizing immigration means "really, no illegals". They quietly, quickly, <a href="https://www.tampabay.com/opinion/2023/06/08/desantis-ships-migrants-texas-gop-legislators-beg-them-keep-working-florida-column/">walk it back</a>.</p>
    <p>For agricultural labor, we do have a more civilized alternative, the <a href="https://www.uscis.gov/working-in-the-united-states/temporary-workers/h-2a-temporary-agricultural-workers">H-2A visa</a> for temporary farm workers. It's conceivable we could expand this program to regularize the status of the people doing "work Americans don't want to do", exploit them just a bit less, but keep the basic contours of the deal in place. The H-2A program respects a labor market segmentation we as a political community have now tacitly accepted.</p>
    <p>The <a href="https://www.uscis.gov/working-in-the-united-states/h-1b-specialty-occupations">H-1B program</a> does not. The H-1B is for high-value white collar work that Americans broadly would love to do. It brings migrants from poorer countries under exploitative terms, because workers are placed at risk of losing immigration status if they lose their jobs. So H-1B workers tolerate wages and works condition less generous than native workers accept, or would accept absent competition or threat of replacement by H-1B workers.</p>
    <p>Exploitation and segmentation are twins. If a class of migrants is not exploitable, then its labor needn't be segmented.</p>
    <p>The United States offers a range of <a href="https://travel.state.gov/content/travel/en/us-visas/immigrate/employment-based-immigrant-visas.html">employment-based immigration visas</a>, under which workers labor with roughly the same security and on close to the same terms as US citizens. More migrants come to the United States under these visas than via the H-1B program, with almost no controversy. These visas are extended to people who are expected to do high-value work. The work, and the taxes that result from it, are presumed to be contribution enough to the welfare of other Americans.</p>
    <p>Employers <a href="https://x.com/elonmusk/status/1872374103983759835">like to pretend</a> the H-1B program is used like the "<a href="https://www.uscis.gov/working-in-the-united-states/permanent-workers/employment-based-immigration-first-preference-eb-1">Einstein Visa</a>", as a way to recruit the most extraordinary foreign talent to play for Team America. But if that's the case, the appropriate visa is an employment-based immigration visa, not the intentionally precarious, notionally temporary, H-1B.</p>
    <p>The H-1B program exploits the workers it recruits, but fails to segment the exploited workforce from native labor markets. We can argue about magnitudes, but this has the plain economic effect of reducing native worker bargaining power, and the predictable political effect of enraging native workers. One might conspiratorially attribute the allocation of H1-B visas by lottery rather than by salary not to poor design, but to the possibility employers value the program not so much for the employees it permits them to hire, but for its ability discipline labor across the salary spectrum.</p>
    <p>On both moral and practical grounds, I favor more rather than less migration. I have a soft spot for the H-1B program, because I have friends who'd not be here without it. Nevertheless, it is a bad program. Accepting a class of immigrants on terms that render them exploitable relative to native workers without ensuring that the labor markets they participate in are segmented from the work natives pursue is class warfare.</p>
    <p>The right way forward is to fold the H-1B program into employment-based immigrant visas. Existing H-1B holders should be able to trade their status for EB visas. Currently, roughly 140,000 employment-based immigrant visa are allocated each year. Including slots for professionals with advanced degrees, up to 85,000 H-1B visas are made available. We should just expand the employment-based immigrant visa program to 225,000 per year and call it a day.</p>
    <p>American firms should indeed recruit the very best talent from India and everywhere. When they do, the American government should hand these remarkable people green cards, rather than hand their employers a weapon, a cudgel, a threat they deploy against both migrant workers and their native colleagues.</p>
   </div>
  </div>
  <div class="entry-footer">
   <div class="post-metainfo">
    <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/12/31/segmentation-fault/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b>
    <br>
     2024-12-31 @ 03:15 PM EST
   </div>
  </div>
 </div><!-- entry-header-body-footer -->
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 14:30:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">
        https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/12/24/wreckresentative-democracy-secret-congress-and-bee-sting-theory/index.html
      </guid>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[“Wreckresentative democracy” is the name I’ve given to what stands in for representative democracy in the American system. Rather than meaningful, collaborative, representation — which we do not and cannot have, when our “representatives” are charged with “representing” almost 800,000 randos — we content ourselves with constraining the assholes who pretend to represent us, by wielding a credible threat to “throw the bums out” if they do something we dislike. We don’t have representation, but we...]]>
      </description>
      <link>
        https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/12/24/wreckresentative-democracy-secret-congress-and-bee-sting-theory/index.html
      </link>
      <title>Wreckresentative democracy, &quot;Secret Congress&quot;, and bee-sting theory</title>
      <dc:creator><![CDATA[Steve Randy Waldman]]></dc:creator>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header-body-footer">
  <div class="entry-header">
  </div>
  <div class="entry-body">
   <div class="flexmark markdown">
    <p>“<a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/12/20/wreckresentative-democracy/index.html">Wreckresentative democracy</a>” is the name I’ve given to what stands in for representative democracy in the American system.</p>
    <p>Rather than meaningful, collaborative, representation — which we do not and cannot have, when our “representatives” are charged with “representing” almost 800,000 randos — we content ourselves with constraining the assholes who pretend to represent us, by wielding a credible threat to “throw the bums out” if they do something we dislike. We don’t have representation, but we retain some influence by virtue of our capacity to wreck politicians' careers.</p>
    <p>Most of us are of course happily, rationally ignorant of whatever our “representatives” are or are not doing. So how can we sustain any credible threat?</p>
    <p>Human beings are wired for outrage and <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/5911.html">altruistic punishment</a> as means of enforcing pro-social behavior. So while we remain rationally ignorant of most things our legislators do, including the “good things”, we are primed to sense scandal, betrayal, and to punish it.</p>
    <p>The fact that the role of public participation in our democracy is almost entirely negative — we punish rather than guide — explains a lot about how our politics actually function. A few years ago Simon Bazelon and Matt Yglesias <a href="https://www.slowboring.com/p/the-rise-and-importance-of-secret">pointed out</a> that while Congress often seems hopelessly gridlocked, a lot of constructive activity occurs in what they termed “Secret Congress” — when legislators quietly get together to hash out deals about issues with little public salience, outside of the spotlight of media and partisan controversy.</p>
    <p>This makes sense in the context of “wreckresentative democracy”. Whatever action is taken on any salient, polarizing public controversy, it will create losers for whom the action will be a betrayal. It will create winners too. But most of the public will not perceive itself directly as winners. Losers will make a case to a mostly disengaged public that the legislation was an act of treachery. They will try to power up the wrecking ball of public revulsion, encourage coalescence behind an impulse to punish.</p>
    <p>Legislators enjoy little electoral advantage from the engaged sliver of the public that perceives an action as virtuous, but faces a serious risk that the engaged sliver that perceives itself as losing will gin up an electorally dangerous reaction. Inaction is close to costless. Action on matters of open controversy is dangerous.</p>
    <p>Note that this is a pathological result of “wreckresentative democracy”. It simply would not occur under genuine representation. In an actually representative system, constituents would not be 800,000 random citizens with widely divergent values and interests, but some much smaller number of people who actually share similar views that a representative could understand and advocate. The particulars of a legislative proposal might be obscure to constituents. Representation exists to absolve ordinary citizens of those details. But when a public controversy erupts, the position taken by a representative will be straightforwardly related to interests widely shared by her constituents. She might win or lose, but constituents would feel represented rather than betrayed regardless.</p>
    <p>The gridlock we take for granted on matters of sharp controversy, the paradoxical result that “democracy” can only progress when it addresses matters the electorate is too ignorant much to care about, all result from the asymmetry of incentives built into wreckresentation, where constituents have little means to reward a “representative” but they can sure as hell punish.</p>
    <p>Bee-sting theory is a name <a href="https://x.com/interfluidity/status/1435076577587433475">I gave</a> to a view expressed by David Shor, that political parties are basically always punished for bold action. You might call it the opposite of "<a href="https://prospect.org/politics/case-for-deliverism/">deliverism</a>".</p>
    <p>In Shor’s view, when a political party wins power, it can and sometimes should do big, important things, because that’s what political power is for. But like a bee choosing to sting, it is undertaking an action that will grievously harm it on behalf of some greater good. It should not expect to be rewarded, electorally. It should expect to lose, and should act only when the political cost will be worth it.</p>
    <p>A common interpretation of the phenomenon Shor describes is <em>status quo</em> bias. "The electorate," intone sad politics-knowers, "often <em>claims</em> to want change but in fact hates to see its habits disturbed."</p>
    <p>I think Shor is onto something descriptively, but the <em>status quo</em> bias story is wrong. There are times — not at all rare times! — when much of the public actually does want bold change from their government.</p>
    <p>However, proponents of any particular bold change are mixed together in the same constituency with people who would absolutely oppose the change, and with a much larger group that has never given the matter much thought. In a genuinely representative system, people would have been presorted into constituencies that would favor the change and constituencies who wouldn’t, and enacting the change would not be electoral poison for representatives of the former. In our wreckresentative system, where people pretend to represent huge populations that are not meaningfully sorted, the bigger the change the more easily it can be spun to the politically less engaged majority, by those who oppose the change, as a terrible betrayal.</p>
    <p>What looks like <em>status quo</em> bias in the electorate as a whole is not that at all. It is an artifact of asymmetrical incentives that "representatives" face due to how we have structured electoral and legislative institutions. An infantilized electorate without meaningful representation, with no real influence except its capacity to lash out, lashes out.</p>
    <p>Although I have <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/9069.html">my fancier ideas</a>, conventional multiparty proportional representation would go a long way towards fixing this.</p>
   </div>
  </div>
  <div class="entry-footer">
   <div class="post-metainfo">
    <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/12/24/wreckresentative-democracy-secret-congress-and-bee-sting-theory/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b>
    <br>
     2024-12-24 @ 02:30 PM EST
   </div>
  </div>
 </div><!-- entry-header-body-footer -->
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 13:25:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/12/20/wreckresentative-democracy/index.html</guid>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[There’s little meaningful "representative democracy" in a polity like the United States. There never really has been. Your “representative” in Congress allegedly represents almost 800,000 people, people with whom you have nothing in common other than geographic proximity, if even that after all the oddities of gerrymandering. We teach our children we live in a representative democracy when the claim is very obviously absurd. Europeans and political scientists may object that meaningful...]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/12/20/wreckresentative-democracy/index.html</link>
      <title>Wreckresentative democracy</title>
      <dc:creator><![CDATA[Steve Randy Waldman]]></dc:creator>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss uid-wreckresentative-democracy">
 <div class="entry-header-body-footer">
  <div class="entry-header">
  </div>
  <div class="entry-body">
   <div class="flexmark markdown">
    <p>There’s little meaningful "representative democracy" in a polity like the United States. There never really has been.</p>
    <p>Your “representative” in Congress allegedly represents almost 800,000 people, people with whom you have nothing in common other than geographic proximity, if even that after all the oddities of gerrymandering. We teach our children we live in a representative democracy when the claim is very obviously absurd.</p>
    <p>Europeans and political scientists may object that meaningful representation comes via the intermediation of political parties. Political parties are smaller, and by virtue of self-selection, more homogeneous than the polity as a whole. In theory, a person might be enfranchised <em>within</em> their political party by actively participating in it, and then be enfranchised <em>via</em> their political party in a parliament or legislature. Proportional representation means that all parties then are represented, according to their support within the population.</p>
    <p>Regular readers know I <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/06/15/state-capacity-and-authoritarianism/index.html">strongly</a> <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/03/28/how-to-understand-approval-voting/index.html">favor</a> electoral reform to bring multiparty democracy to the United States. So far be it from me to piss too hard on this parade.</p>
    <p>Nevertheless, even if we had six rather than two national parties, they would still, from the perspective of most citizens, be distant institutions run by insiders to whom most of us would have little access. Representation is a matter of degree, and multiparty parliamentary democracies do a better job of it than America’s destructive duopoly, but even in well-arranged parliamentary systems the claim a parliament is “representative” is a stretch.</p>
    <p>What would it mean for a law-making body to be representative? What are we actually after?</p>
    <p>Much as I am fond of <a href="https://equalitybylot.com/">sortition enthusiasts</a>, I don’t think what we want is a representative sample in a statistical sense. Lawmaking is an activity most of us have little expertise or inclination toward. The whole point of “representative democracy” is to delegate the task to specialist-experts, who by definition are unlike most of the rest of us, who become even less like us by virtue of being formally employed as “representatives”.</p>
    <p>In social affairs, statistical independence is the exception, correlation is the norm. The ways that specialist-expert representatives are different from the rest of us will bring divergences between that group as a class and the rest of our interests and values. There is no getting around this. If you choose legislators by sortition, they will be “representative” only until the moment they take their unusual job, school themselves in unusual skills, become overwhelmed by the generosity of well-wishers and lobbyists with whom ordinary constituents rarely truck. Representatives cannot be representative. Precisely because they are representatives, they are different.</p>
    <p>I think that the version of representation we are after is the version generally provided by the legal profession. When we hire a lawyer, we don’t do so because we imagine that she is “like us”. We do so because we imagine that the skills our attorney could bring to bear would be effective at advancing our values and interests, if only she would wield those skills on our behalf. So we hire her, we pay her, to wield those skills on our behalf.</p>
    <p>But in order for the arrangement to work, "we" — the people doing the hiring — must have a coherent set of values and interests she can advance. We must actively, persistently communicate to our attorney what those values and interests are. Her role is to listen and understand our interests as we understand them, help hone them into something actionable and coherent, and then to develop effective means of advancing them. Although it is not her role to gainsay what we understand our own interests to be, it very much is her role to provide expert feedback about the relationship between various tactics we might consider and the likelihood of actually advancing those interests.</p>
    <p>Effective representation doesn’t come from who our attorney <em>is</em>. She <em>is</em> nothing like us. Effective representation results from an active collaboration between the represented and the representative, and active supervision by the represented.</p>
    <p>In <em>status quo</em> American democracy, this kind of representation certainly does take place. But the “client” cannot be the electorate that gave our representative her perch. The very idea is incoherent. Those 800,000 people disagree among themselves, often strongly. They do not share the same values and interests.</p>
    <p>No, election as a representative doesn’t in practice mean a person represents the incoherent mass that is “their constituents”. It simply places a person in a position where they can choose what values and interests actually to represent. Some people who are elected have strong allegiances to a preexisting set of values, and they work to advance those, collaborating with people they understand to be important proponents of those values. That sounds noble, but keep in mind the values to which they are so strongly committed may be diametrically opposed to those of a significant fraction of their constituents, who are left not unrepresented, but anti-represented.</p>
    <p>Most electeds are more pragmatic. They effectively sell their advocacy in the same way that a lawyer might. Election simply places them in a position where they have something valuable to offer in the marketplace that otherwise they would not have.</p>
    <p>In any case, there is no meaningful collaboration with and supervision by “their constituents” as a whole. There cannot be. Constituents do not share a coherent set of values and interests that anyone could collaborate to advance.</p>
    <p>If we want meaningful representation, we would have to move towards a very different system, something like <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/9069.html">mass representative democracy</a>. But we are very, very far from such a thing.</p>
    <p>This has been a pretty bleak presentation of <em>status quo</em> representative democracy. I think accurately so! One reason why people are not so exercised to save “Our Democracy” is because most of us do not perceive ourselves to be meaningfully represented in the democracy that we are supposed to save.</p>
    <p>And yet.</p>
    <p>The actual practice of American-style “representative” democracy is somehow a lot more open, a lot less indifferent, than the picture I’ve painted. Representatives do not and cannot meaningfully represent the mass of their constituents, no. But they are nevertheless desperate to be liked. They cannot represent, but they still have to win the next election if they are to keep their job and the opportunities it brings.</p>
    <p>So in lieu of representation, we get pandering. Our representatives publicize the least contentious things they do, tell us in our newsletters how hard they are working for us, bend over backwards to offer “constituent services” in order to communicate that they are on our side. In safe partisan districts, we get fairy tales of heroes and villains, in which Our Noble Representative stands up to the corruption and perfidy of the Bad Political Party.</p>
    <p>Elected officials’ desperation to be liked offers a back-door simulacrum of actual representation. We cannot collaborate with our representatives to affirmatively advance our values and interests. But we can threaten punish them when they work against us. We can badmouth them, run ads against them, primary them. We don’t have representation, but we have “wreckresentation”. We can’t make them work on our behalf, but often we can frighten them away from working against us. Not always. Where controversies are aligned with partisan allegiances, representatives in non-swing districts can safely choose their party’s side with little fear of punishment. But when a representative might wish to work against a faction in their own party, or take a position on a controversy not yet calcified along partisan lines, they risk being villainized, demonized, becoming unliked and electorally vulnerable.</p>
    <p>The system feels “open” because even though we cannot gain representation, our “representatives” assiduously crave our approval. It’s not enfranchisement, but flattery can be a consolation prize. We do have some genuine capacity to manipulate elected officials, by threatening to render them dislikable. That’s not representation, but maybe “wreckresentation” is the next best thing.</p>
    <p>It may be over, however. “Wreckresentation” is becoming professionalized. AIPAC, of course, has been a pioneer, systematically surveilling American politics for dissidents against their version of a pro-Israel position, in order to disparage and destroy electeds who fail to toe the line. This cycle, the <a href="https://www.opensecrets.org/news/2024/07/pro-crypto-super-pacs-pouring-tens-of-millions-into-2024-elections/">crypto industry</a> adopted the same playbook. And Elon Musk, whose brave new scale of expenditures dwarfs all who came before, now <a href="https://www.yahoo.com/news/elon-musk-threatening-fund-primary-212351051.html">threatens in general</a> to wreck the careers of anyone not with his program.</p>
    <p>The desperation of elected officials to be liked, their fear of scandal, is the heart of what’s left for ordinary Americans to perceive as “our democracy”. We don’t have representation. But we do have the people we elect constantly pandering to us and currying our favor. As the fear of organized interests comes to overwhelm concerns about pissing off random groups of constituents, as more and more it is Elon Musk rather than constituents whose favor must be curried, this last affective vestige of “democracy” may too, like so much else, wither and die.</p>
   </div>
  </div>
  <div class="entry-footer">
   <div class="post-metainfo">
    <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/12/20/wreckresentative-democracy/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b>
    <br>
     2024-12-20 @ 01:25 PM EST
   </div>
  </div>
 </div><!-- entry-header-body-footer -->
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 12:40:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/11/19/plutocracy-as-a-positive-ideal/index.html</guid>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[This post is dedicated to John Roberts. People I talk to whose worldview is close to mine often profess a sense of bafflement: I mean, they are just destroying this country. It's one thing to want to win, to want to run the place. But what's the point of ruling a country if you turn it into a cesspool of corruption? The "Iron Law of Institutions", propounded by Jon Schwarz, offers one potential answer. I want to offer a less cynical explanation. Perhaps where we see corruption, our opponents...]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/11/19/plutocracy-as-a-positive-ideal/index.html</link>
      <title>Plutocracy as a positive ideal</title>
      <dc:creator><![CDATA[Steve Randy Waldman]]></dc:creator>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header-body-footer">
  <div class="entry-header">
  </div>
  <div class="entry-body">
   <div class="flexmark markdown">
    <p><em>This post is dedicated to John Roberts.</em></p>
    <hr>
    <p>People I talk to whose worldview is close to mine often profess a sense of bafflement:</p>
    <p><em>I mean, they are just destroying this country. It's one thing to want to win, to want to run the place. But what's the point of ruling a country if you turn it into a cesspool of corruption?</em></p>
    <p>The "<a href="http://www.tinyrevolution.com/mt/archives/001705.html">Iron Law of Institutions</a>", propounded by <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/schwarz.bsky.social">Jon Schwarz</a>, offers one potential answer.</p>
    <p>I want to offer a less cynical explanation. Perhaps where we see corruption, our opponents see virtue. Is "influence peddling" such a problem if the pedlars are, well, a good influence?</p>
    <p>We tend to see collective action problems, tragedies of the commons, self-interested, transactional decisions that compose to catastrophes no one could want.</p>
    <p>What if to our opponents these outcomes are not catastrophes at all, but great successes, a righting of wrongs?</p>
    <h3><a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/11/19/plutocracy-as-a-positive-ideal/#a-republic-if-you-can-keep-it" id="a-republic-if-you-can-keep-it" name="a-republic-if-you-can-keep-it" class="anchorlink"></a>A republic if you can keep it</h3>
    <p>From the moment of the American founding, our "republican form of government" has been Janus-faced.</p>
    <p>To most of us, in most of our civics classes, a "republic" just means representative democracy. Unqualified "democracy", direct democracy, doesn't scale. It suffers from information problems, as high-quality lawmaking requires more attention and expertise than can be expected of ordinary citizens, if we are to have lives and a prosperous economy as well.</p>
    <p>In a "republican" system, rather than participate directly in lawmaking, our information problem is simplified to periodically electing full-time professionals to represent our values and interests in the lawmaking process. Fundamentally, the system remains democratic. We've just settled upon a more practical, effective structure for government of the people, by the people, for the people than pretending we can run legislatures millions of citizens strong.</p>
    <p>But the republican form of government makes an appeal to a quite distinct tradition, also strong at the American founding.</p>
    <p>Under this second tradition, all men are not equal in real life, regardless what they were when our Creator endowed them. Some men are fit to rule. Other men and women are fit to serve.</p>
    <p>In a well-ordered nation, the best men must rule. This is an edict not of any parochial interest or self-dealing faction, but of nature itself. It serves the interest of all.</p>
    <p>A slave may have no control over his circumstance, yet be much better off than if he did, when his betters order a world in which his labor contributes to a prosperity that, in due measure, he also enjoys.</p>
    <p>Whatever it is called — "Congress", "Parliament" — the republican form of government vouchsafes a kind of aristocracy. The great virtue of a republic, in this tradition, is that it attaches to this aristocracy institutions of notional consent, easing the burden leaders always face of persuading the ruled to submit to those who rightfully rule them.</p>
    <p>The US Constitution was the Barack Obama of its time, fresh-faced and inspirational and sufficiently vague that different factions could project their own hopes onto its form. Idealists inclined to democracy could scry within it an improvement on the Athenian tradition. Entitled men who fancied themselves practical saw clever machinery for manufacturing consent in rule of the country by its natural rulers.</p>
    <p>We frequently discuss particular deformities framers of the Constitution adopted to ensure its ratification — "equal suffrage" of the states (and therefore radically unequal suffrage of citizens) in the Senate, counting slaves as three-fifths persons, the odd formula behind the electoral college. But the republican form of government itself — is it a <a href="https://www.independent.co.uk/news/science/duck-and-rabbit-illusion-b1821663.html">duck or a rabbit</a>? is the dress <a href="https://slate.com/technology/2017/04/heres-why-people-saw-the-dress-differently.html">gold or blue</a> — was the Constitution's main trick, allowing political opponents to rally together behind one document they interpreted quite differently.</p>
    <p>Ever since, of course, we have been fighting over just what kind of document it is. On paper a duck and a rabbit may be contrived to take a single form, but in life the two animals behave distinctly.</p>
    <h3><a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/11/19/plutocracy-as-a-positive-ideal/#money-as-a-martial-virtue" id="money-as-a-martial-virtue" name="money-as-a-martial-virtue" class="anchorlink"></a>Money as a martial virtue</h3>
    <p>Traditionally aristocratic lineages distinguished themselves in war. Men who were natural rulers held land, taxed peasants, raised armies for their own glory or to serve the even greater glory of the king. Men who held and taxed land, or who won the debt and favor of the king, became noblemen and ruled, as God and nature intended.</p>
    <p>By the American founding, commerce was already vying with conquest as a source of wealth and power. Nevertheless, suffrage under the early Constitution was <a href="https://www.colonialwilliamsburg.org/learn/deep-dives/who-voted-in-early-america/">usually restricted</a> to men who owned land, a reflex of deference to the natural ruling class.</p>
    <p>Following the Industrial Revolution, however, the notion that land ownership uniquely demarcated the best and most capable became both normatively and practically unsustainable. Surely the claim to greatness of some ranch owner paled in comparison to the conquests of an industrialist like John Rockefeller. Just as surely, men like Rockefeller had the means to ensure that their interests would not be subordinated to those of a gentry that fancied itself Jeffersonian.</p>
    <p>Proponents of aristocratic republicanism are not, have never been, mere throwback feudalists. Like all living traditions, aristocratic republicanism has adapted with the times. Rather than land, the marker of right-to-rule has been increasingly recast as wealth, money. In centuries past, men proved their mettle on horseback with lance or rifle. Now men contest for greatness on the terrain of business. In either case, the best men, those worthy of rule, are the winners.</p>
    <p>This has nothing whatsoever to do with your dorky economics textbook. The basis for deference to winners isn't because they must have provided goods and services at higher quality or lower prices than their rivals. It's because they fucking won. The more unfair the contest, the more impressive the victory.</p>
    <p>Business is the successor to the pillage and conquest that created duchies, kingdoms, empires. What of the theories of Friedrich Hayek? Milton Friedman? Bandits who style themselves kings have always hired balladeers to recast their pillage as glory unto God, service to the greater good. Even now, now more than ever, they extravagantly groom jesters and fools.</p>
    <p>Antitrust is abhorrent to this tradition. Antitrust is for slaves. When the Huns poured from the steppes and overtook Europe, could defenders lay one hand horizontally across their other hand held vertically, call "time out" and demand that referees inspect the rulebook?</p>
    <p>No. They fucking fought and fucking died. Or else they killed, held their patch of land and therefore continued to rule.</p>
    <p>In a fallen world chock full of slaves, people contending to be masters recognize no higher authority. The idea is abhorrent. They themselves are the highest authority, or else they are a corpse.</p>
    <h3><a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/11/19/plutocracy-as-a-positive-ideal/#lineage" id="lineage" name="lineage" class="anchorlink"></a>Lineage</h3>
    <p>Emperors do not concede that their domains must crumble when frailty overtakes their skin and bones. The quality that martial or business conquest reveals, in which inheres the right to rule, must subsist, then, not in individuals but in families, lineages.</p>
    <p>You can put this in terms as dweeby as you want. Just like they hire their Milton Friedmans, they hire their Charles Murrays and Arthur Jensens, balladeers who sing a different key. Men who rule are not "following the science" about genes and DNA and heritability. It simply is an axiom they require, that the unit of analysis for human quality should be lineage rather than person. Clever slaves can write up the textbooks.</p>
    <p>You have your axioms. They have theirs. Don't imagine that you fool yourself any less when you choose the foundations for your version of "reason".</p>
    <p>In any case, to understand the behavior of aristocratic republicans, you must understand that among them, excellence and awfulness, capability and cravenness, are characteristics of families rather than individuals. A just political order weighs and sorts whole lineages, rather than particular individuals. Inheritance is just, because it is the lineage, not the person, that conquers, accumulates, and so <em>earns</em> the spoils of conquest.</p>
    <p>Every family will have its black sheep, its morons, its fail-sons and squanderers. All of that is noise, the private business of great families to address. Usurpers and strivers who trade in gossip about such characters in order to contest the status of the lineage should be crushed.</p>
    <h3><a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/11/19/plutocracy-as-a-positive-ideal/#the-constitutional-order" id="the-constitutional-order" name="the-constitutional-order" class="anchorlink"></a>The constitutional order</h3>
    <p>From the perspective of aristocratic republicans, the purpose of the Constitutional order is to durably and reliably elevate the best to rule, while cloaking that coronation as the result of "democratic contestation", reflecting "consent of the governed".</p>
    <p>But there is always a danger that forms of democratic contestation might give way to substance, to an order in which mobs of lesser men and women grasp the reins of power and do mischief — not least to their own interests, as unsuited men elevated to rule inevitably do.</p>
    <p>So there must be a kind of dance. On the one hand, the forms of institutions must be sufficiently "democratic" or at least "legitimate" to cultivate the voluntary submission upon which a peaceful, prosperous order depends. On the other hand, the institutions should not be so "democratic" as to permit among the unworthy more than token representation in the halls of power.</p>
    <p>Suppose there were some kind of council, a chamber in which <a href="https://www.supremecourt.gov/about/justices.aspx">robed wise men</a> could fine-tune and reconfigure the institutions that are only vaguely sketched on the several pages of the American Constitution.</p>
    <p>Congress must be elected. Inadequate vigor on the part of the council's predecessors has rendered universal formal suffrage a <em>fait accompli</em>. The Senate as well as the House is now directly elected.</p>
    <p>Perhaps in time these errors can be reversed. But holding actions are needed now. The best men — recognizable as the richest men — must rule, despite institutions that insist on formal equality for all.</p>
    <p>What would you do?</p>
    <p>If there must be elections, you might <a href="https://supreme.justia.com/cases/federal/us/558/310/">ensure that the best have influence over those elections</a> as <a href="https://supreme.justia.com/cases/federal/us/572/185/">mighty as they can muster</a>.</p>
    <p>Elections are managed at the state level, and some states are, unfortunately, run by governments beholden to the other republican tradition, villainous mob democracy.</p>
    <p>But some states are not. States that are run under virtuous, aristocratic republicanism — if they given <a href="https://supreme.justia.com/cases/federal/us/570/529/">freedom to manage how elections are run</a>, or to <a href="https://supreme.justia.com/cases/federal/us/588/18-422/">strategically define electoral districts</a> — will vigorously use those powers to elevate men suited to rule, or men and women who can be counted upon to do those men's bidding.</p>
    <p>States that rule in the democratic republican tradition will refrain from using these powers with full, cold-eyed vigor as a counterweight. To do so would be to violate and undermine the very democratic norms they are besotted to protect. Idealists rather than warriors, they are hobbled. (Idiots. Fools. How could one trust such men to rule?)</p>
    <p>With great effort, considering several decades of backsliding, elections have been reoriented towards what the founders (at least those in the aristocratic republican tradition) intended — plebiscites that imbue legitimacy to rule by natural rulers.</p>
    <p>But the republic is large, messy. Some states are still run by usurpers, idealists, communists, "democrats". Unworthy men and women will, unfortunately sometimes be elected, and placed in positions where they can do real harm to the interests of the republic, even to interests they would understand as their own, if they were not so unworthy.</p>
    <p>So it is important that the best men retain channels of informal influence, by which they can guide and tutor men and women who rise above their station. They must be permitted to <a href="https://supreme.justia.com/cases/federal/us/603/23-108/">reward</a> the <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/clarence-thomas-scotus-undisclosed-luxury-travel-gifts-crow">best</a> and <a href="https://supreme.justia.com/cases/federal/us/598/21-1158/">worst</a> alike for acting correctly.</p>
    <p>When the Constitution was debated, the danger of mob rule was well understood by men in the aristocratic republican tradition. They calculated that, between the institutional safeguards ("checks and balances") within the new Constitution and attention to the administration of elections, the mob could be simultaneously coöpted and kept at bay. There have been some difficult decades, but patriots are now well on their way to restoring that balance. Elections are less and less a threat.</p>
    <p>Men who seek election are usually ambitious and vain. That is providential, because such men can be bought by those who have proven suited actually to rule by achieving and sustaining great wealth.</p>
    <p>Over the past few decades, however, a new threat has emerged, one that was not foreseen by the founding generation. A "professional civil service" — peopled by men of modest ambition but tremendous pride, confident in false moral and social theories — has arrogated to itself much of the state's capacity to govern. By virtue of their limited ambition and dangerous theories, this class of people is somewhat resistant to remunerative tutelage by their betters.</p>
    <p>Fortunately, these "professionals" are very devoted to the notion of service in the context of paid employment. Establishment of a <a href="https://therevolvingdoorproject.org/">revolving door</a> between professional roles in government and "private sector" jobs arranged in their interest can usefully serve to educate them.</p>
    <p>Nevertheless, as a class, they remain vexatious and dangerous.</p>
    <p>Happily, this class can be cast as illegitimate under <em>both</em> the aristocratic and democratic republican traditions, by virtue of being insulated from the influence both of money and elections. As at the founding, adherents of these two grand traditions, marinated in the best "common sense" money can buy, join together in a common goal — routing the influence of "unelected bureaucrats".</p>
    <p>We are now well on our way to <a href="https://supreme.justia.com/cases/federal/us/603/22-451/">neutralizing</a> <a href="https://supreme.justia.com/cases/federal/us/603/22-1008/">this</a> <a href="https://protectdemocracy.org/work/trumps-schedule-f-plan-explained/">pox</a>.</p>
    <p>Yea and truly, we are finally restoring the American founding.</p>
    <p>One side of it, that is.</p>
    <p>Duck or rabbit, gold or blue. In the end, there can be only one.</p>
   </div>
  </div>
  <div class="entry-footer">
   <div class="post-metainfo">
    <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2024/11/19/plutocracy-as-a-positive-ideal/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b>
    <br>
     2024-11-19 @ 12:40 PM EST
   </div>
  </div>
 </div><!-- entry-header-body-footer -->
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
