<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss 
version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>drafts — interfluidity</title>
    <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/index.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[Feed for blog 'drafts — interfluidity' generated by unstatic]]></description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Jan 2024 21:32:05 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>https://github.com/swaldman/unstatic</generator>
    <docs>https://cyber.harvard.edu/rss/rss.html</docs>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2023 14:35:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/12/28/how-to-regulate-ai/index.html</guid>
      <author>nospam@dev.null (Steve Randy Waldman)</author>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[Predictably, The New York Times is suing Open AI and Microsoft for copyright infringement. OpenAI has used The Times' text to train their large language models. I have no opinion on the legal merits of the case. Courts will try invent some line between fair use and infringement under existing law that balances various interests in this brave new world of LLMs. But I hope that Congress will act to address the question more holistically and creatively than courts can. Here is my two point plan...]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/12/28/how-to-regulate-ai/index.html</link>
      <title>How to regulate AI</title>
      <dc:creator><![CDATA[Steve Randy Waldman]]></dc:creator>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header">
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <img src="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/12/28/how-to-regulate-ai/never-held-accountable.jpeg" width="100%" alt="Printed slide, 'A computer can never be held accountable, therefore a computer must never make a management decision.'">
   <p>Predictably, <em>The New York Times</em> is <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/12/27/24016212/new-york-times-openai-microsoft-lawsuit-copyright-infringement">suing</a> Open AI and Microsoft for copyright infringement. OpenAI has used <em>The Times'</em> text to train their large language models. I have no opinion on the legal merits of the case. Courts will try invent some line between fair use and infringement under existing law that balances various interests in this brave new world of LLMs.</p>
   <p>But I hope that Congress will act to address the question more holistically and creatively than courts can. Here is my two point plan for what Congress should do:</p>
   <ol>
    <li>
     <p>Congress should declare that big-data AI models do not infringe copyright, but are inherently in the public domain.</p></li>
    <li>
     <p>Congress should declare that use of AI tools will be an aggravating rather than mitigating factor in determinations of civil and criminal liability.</p></li>
   </ol>
   <h4><a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/12/28/how-to-regulate-ai/#congress-should-declare-that-big-data-ai-models-do-not-infringe-copyright-but-are-inherently-in-the-public-domain" id="congress-should-declare-that-big-data-ai-models-do-not-infringe-copyright-but-are-inherently-in-the-public-domain" name="congress-should-declare-that-big-data-ai-models-do-not-infringe-copyright-but-are-inherently-in-the-public-domain" class="anchorlink"></a>Congress should declare that big-data AI models do not infringe copyright, but are inherently in the public domain.</h4>
   <p>The moral justification for this is clear. Big-data AI models are summarizations of the work of large publics. They are a whole much greater than the sum of the parts. Their value comes from a public much too broad and amorphous to constitute an identifiable party who might license inputs or be compensated.</p>
   <p>The law should explicitly reject claims like <a href="https://helpx.adobe.com/stock/contributor/help/firefly-faq-for-adobe-stock-contributors.html">Adobe’s</a> that, by training models on only work explicitly licensed to them or in the public domain, they address this concern. Even if every individual input dots the i's and crosses the t's of prior copyright law, modeling very large corpuses of work extracts information not only from the direct inputs summarized, which might in theory be compensated, but from all the inputs and influences to the creators of those direct influences.</p>
   <p>These models not simply new creative works derivative of particular other works. The modeling process is something new, a tool designed to extract regularities and patterns and ideas that characterize the domains they model as a whole. The training set is a telescope and a microscope. Their object of study is human creation very broadly, and these fruits of human creation can belong only to humanity writ large.</p>
   <p>In order to immunize themselves from claims of unlawful expropriation, including both old-school copyright claims and new claims on behalf of the public itself, anyone who trains AI models would have an affirmative obligation to publish and place into the public domain both the results of their training — the “weights” — and the structure of the model under which those weights take their meaning, including code, such that people or ordinary skill in the domain could quickly stand up and run new instances of the model.</p>
   <p>This would, you might object, take away some of the incentive to train large models. It would. But the commercial incentives to develop AI models are already very strong. The Microsofts of the world that want to integrate AI tools into their products can easily afford to fund them as loss leaders. Business communities more broadly, who perceive opportunities to increase productivity or reduce labor costs, would find that pooling resources to train open-source models easily pencils. Academics and the public sector would train public models as well.</p>
   <p>On the other side of the training set, you might object that putting these models in the public domain does nothing to put food on the table of the creators whose work is ingested to produce them. That is very true. But it is a common result of new technologies that old activities that once were remunerative cease to be so. <a href="https://a16z.com/the-techno-optimist-manifesto/">Marc Andreeson is wrong</a> to imagine that inherent characteristics of technology and capitalism ensure that as some means of subsisting are eliminated, better and more remunerative jobs are sure to replace them because of higher marginal productivity or whatever. At an individual level, many people whose work has been technologically obsoleted suffer harms from which they never fully recover. At a broader level, <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/1116.html">only the expansion of social democracy</a> has rendered technological development and something like full employment remotely compatible.</p>
   <p>Widespread use of large-language models will demand a more redistributive state, as much of the public will find these models undermine their (our) current source of market power and therefore ability to command a decent wage. Nevertheless, it remains true that, with decent governance, we are collectively better off when we can all do more with less human work. The right way forward is to continue to let technology make us, in this narrow sense, “richer in aggregate", but use the institution of the state aggressively to ensure that richer in aggregate means all of us live better lives and none of us bestride the narrow world like Elon Musk.</p>
   <p>AI models do nothing at all to hinder human creativity. For many people, generative AI will enable, has already enabled, new means of creative expression. But what is less scarce is less valuable in commerce. It is not creativity that is threatened, but the creative professions.</p>
   <p>I don't think we want market forces to turn 90% of today's creative professionals into nurse's assistants, plumbers, and staff for upscale resorts. Art lives not just in its artifacts, but in collaborative relationships between human artists and audiences, and in forms of collaborations where roles of producer and consumer are less distinct than those terms suggest. The value that we derive from creative work is not independent of who produced it and how. Creative work constitutes the symbols and sinews of human communities. It is the substrate, scaffolding, upon which we develop our notions of the sacred.</p>
   <p>Creativity and capitalism have always sat awkwardly together. They will now sit even more awkwardly. There will be no papering over the divergence between exchange value and value. I don't think we should romanticize the era that is ending. The imperatives of remuneration have recruited beautiful hearts to compellingly sanctify arrangements that are horribly profane. There have been so many beautiful ads.</p>
   <p>We will all still need to eat. We will be less able to pretend that "free markets" can somehow reconcile meeting that need with performing our highest purposes. The challenge we face has always been political. I think it's neither wise nor virtuous to try to suppress generative AI in order to retain a <em>status quo</em> under which some of us could pretend that it was not.</p>
   <h4><a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/12/28/how-to-regulate-ai/#congress-should-declare-that-use-of-ai-models-is-an-aggravating-rather-than-mitigating-factor-in-determinations-of-civil-and-criminal-liability" id="congress-should-declare-that-use-of-ai-models-is-an-aggravating-rather-than-mitigating-factor-in-determinations-of-civil-and-criminal-liability" name="congress-should-declare-that-use-of-ai-models-is-an-aggravating-rather-than-mitigating-factor-in-determinations-of-civil-and-criminal-liability" class="anchorlink"></a>Congress should declare that use of AI models is an aggravating rather than mitigating factor in determinations of civil and criminal liability.</h4>
   <p>AI models clearly have a lot of potential uses. But they just as clearly could cause a great deal of harm. AI models can <a href="https://isbn.nu/0553418815">launder</a> what we might otherwise recognize to be invidious discrimination by race or sex. They can render “objective" or “rational” the <a href="https://www.972mag.com/mass-assassination-factory-israel-calculated-bombing-gaza/">murder of children <em>en masse</em></a>. They can run down pedestrians and then, in their digital confusion, <a href="https://www.freep.com/story/money/cars/general-motors/2023/11/15/gm-general-motors-cruise/71586950007/">drag them for twenty feet</a>.</p>
   <p>There’s <a href="https://twitter.com/bumblebike/status/832394003492564993">that slide, usually attributed to an IBM presentation from the 1970s,</a> stating “A computer can never be held accountable, therefore a computer must never make a management decision.” No sentence ever has more completely misunderstood the imperatives of management. Managers, who are inevitably made responsible for much more than they can control, constantly, desperately, seek means of escaping accountabilty for the decisions that they calculate will be in their interest. An <a href="https://www.mckinsey.com/">entire, storied industry</a> is based upon serving this compulsion.</p>
   <p>If the public allows it, the first and most important use of LLMs will be to allow managers, firms, and governments to shirk accountability, either by deferring to the expertise of "objective” models, or by blaming inevitable, regrettable glitches that of course we must accept for the greater good while developing any brilliant new technology.</p>
   <p>So the public, via the state, must not allow it. Commercial users of AI models will argue that the law should treat occasional “mistakes” resulting from AI model outputs to be unintended and unforeseeable outcomes of ordinary business processes, for which their liability should be minimal. If the self-driving car hits a pedestrian, that is regrettable, but of course there can be no criminal charges, as there might have been for a human driver who dragged a person 20 feet after striking her. If lots of people are wrongfully denied insurance claims by some black-box model, eventually perhaps some class-action lawsuit will succeed and make some lawyers rich and fail to bring back the dead. The firm will pay a financial settlement, a cost of doing business. Of course, if a human had systematically made the same error, and it was in the firm's or their own financial interest, the human might have been convicted of fraud. But a computer is eternally innocent.</p>
   <p>We should not treat computational models — of any sort, but especially models as unpredictable as LLMs — as legitimate and ordinary decision-making agents in any high-stakes business process. A computer cannot be held accountable, so the law must insist that, by definition, it is never a computer that makes a management decision. If it seems to anyway, and then it errs, the humans who deployed it were presumptively negligent. If it errs systematically in the interest of the firm, its human deployers were presumptively engaged in a conspiracy to defraud.</p>
   <p>An analogy I like to use is alcohol and driving. One way we could think about a person who causes a fatal car crash while intoxicated is that they did not have their wits about them, they did not intend to do the harm. It was a tragic accident when they were not at their best, so their culpability should be limited.</p>
   <p>Another way we can think about the same event is that <em>precisely because</em> after drinking a person would foreseeably not have their wits about them, the very act of drinking without making alternative transportation arrangements increases their culpability for the accident. They should have known well in advance of the tragedy itself they were doing something risky. The risk that they took was essential to the crime, not just the fact of the horrific consequence.</p>
   <p>Each of these framings is legitimate. They just express different social values. If, as a society, we place a very high value on the joys of alcohol-lubricated conviviality and our liberty of automobile-mediated assembly for that purpose, then we might treat intoxication as a mitigating factor in car accidents, and accept their prevalence as a price we pay for a greater good. If we don’t place so high a value on a good time, or we place a much higher value on reducing car accidents, then we would adopt the framing that we have, under which alcohol is an aggravating factor.</p>
   <p>We face a similar social choice with LLMs. The business automation they might enable should be scored as a social good, to the degree they free humans to do either work only humans can do well or to enjoy greater liberty and leisure. But low-quality work and the risk of laundering fraudulent or unethical practices through an ablution of mysterious technology should be viewed as a grave social costs. There is no such thing as perfect balance. We have to decide whether to err on the side of license — on the theory rapid deployment of these technologies will make us richer and happier and better — or of caution, because we think quality of deployment outweighs any benefit of speed. Fifteen years ago, before our collective experience of social media and surveillance capitalism and platform peony, I would have opted for license. Now, however, I strongly favor caution.</p>
   <p>Use of these technologies should not be banned, for almost any purpose. But our social presumption should be they are unreliable, experimental, susceptible to difficult to detect forms of abuse and predation by their deployers. Whenever things go wrong, their deployers are innocent until proven guilty only of the fact of deployment. Once it has been established that they have deployed these technologies in consequential roles, they become presumptively responsible, civilly and criminally, for all the harms wrought by systems they deployed but negligently failed to adequately supervise, or worse.</p>
   <p>That presumption would be rebuttable. If deployers can show that the system they created performs at least as well, caused no more harm than, systems in common use that do not use the technology, then they have not been negligent. Waymo, for example, has <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/12/20/24006712/waymo-driverless-million-mile-safety-compare-human">approached autonomous driving</a> with a great deal more caution than competitors Cruise and Tesla, such that in practice its cars have been much safer than human drivers. So long as this is the case, those responsible for deployment of Waymo vehicles should not be held liable, civilly and criminally, for reckless driving following the very few accidents involving its vehicles that do occur. Cruise and Tesla, on the other hand, would not succeed at rebutting a presumption of negligence.</p>
   <p>The purpose of the proposed legal regime would not be to ban these technologies from business processes. It would be to insist upon their high quality, from a social perspective, and ensure that quality is placed before imperatives that might otherwise lead businesses to profit by externalizing risk and harms.</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/12/28/how-to-regulate-ai/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b>
   <br>
    [2023-12-28 @ 02:35 PM EST]
  </div>
 </div>
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Dec 2023 12:20:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/12/14/norms-mean-you-cant-pull-rank/index.html</guid>
      <author>nospam@dev.null (Steve Randy Waldman)</author>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[Why does it matter that, as I argued in the previous post, “international law” is not law at all, but international affairs are governed by norms? It’s important because it changes how we should conduct ourselves completely. In a courtroom, you can argue points of law and win, even if many people do not like the verdict. When defense and plaintiff meet in a courtroom, they are not trying to persuade one another, or to persuade a broad audience of spectators. They are appealing to the authority...]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/12/14/norms-mean-you-cant-pull-rank/index.html</link>
      <title>Norms mean you can't pull rank</title>
      <dc:creator><![CDATA[Steve Randy Waldman]]></dc:creator>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header">
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <p>Why does it matter that, as I argued in the <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/12/10/theres-no-such-thing-as-international-law/index.html">previous post</a>, “international law” is not law at all, but international affairs are governed by norms?</p>
   <p>It’s important because it changes how we should conduct ourselves completely.</p>
   <p>In a courtroom, you can argue points of law and win, even if many people do not like the verdict. When defense and plaintiff meet in a courtroom, they are not trying to persuade one another, or to persuade a broad audience of spectators. They are appealing to the authority of the state. In a legislature, you can "lobby" a small group to change the law. This will durably change how the authority of the state is wielded, even if much of the public finds it horrifying.</p>
   <p>With norms, there is nothing like this. There is no authority to appeal to. Norms bind only by a continuing consensus of multiple parties who model, enforce, and reinforce them.</p>
   <p>Norms can certainly be codified. I am a great fan of <a href="https://www.missmanners.com/">Miss Manners</a>. Whether those codifications matter at all depends on whether some community continually agrees to be bound by them. When disputes arise, it is never enough to be “right on the merits", whatever you might think that should mean.</p>
   <p>In any dispute, it is not just the belligerents that are on trial, but also the norms themselves. The space of putative norms is large and contains contradictions. I condemn you aloud for farting at the dinner party. You condemn me for calling attention to a phenomenon that, Miss Manners will remind us, socially does not exist. <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/AmItheAsshole/">AITA</a>? It doesn’t matter which transgression some book says is more serious. The matter is decided by to whom the eyerolls and subtle turning-aways are directed.</p>
   <p>The habits of command are counterproductive in a normative context. Humans value their own agency. Badgering people to accept a norm you favor can prompt defiance. Norms are enforced by mutual consent. You must invite and persuade rather than demand. In any dispute over a putative transgression of norms, you can bribe or threaten to force others to take your side. But then rather than reinforcing the norm you ostensibly were upholding, you have undermined it. The norm you have reinforced is that people behave only transactionally, which is the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gray_goo">gray goo</a> of norms, undoing all others.</p>
   <p>In international affairs, we really do want a “rules-based order”. But what those rules are can be no ones to command. Over the past two decades, the United States has collapsed from a soft power to a hard power, has traded persuasion in significant measure by a kind of moral prestige for the crude application of carrots and sticks. Do whatever we say is good or we’ll sanction you.</p>
   <p>But hard power is weak power, finite and exhaustible. Only soft power delivers resilience and longevity. As we go forward — those of us who manage to go forward without being murdered or bombed or recruited into some madman’s campaign to murder and bomb — I hope that we can return to soft power. Not unilaterally. Soft power is not zero sum. Our good reputation need not rely upon others having a poor reputation.</p>
   <p>“International law” cannot be a substitute for mutually-reinforced norms. International law only has any meaning downstream from such norms. It has no other method of enforcement. A strange mix of idealism and careerism has led us to devote tremendous energy to an edifice of high-minded codification while neglecting the invisible foundation upon which it must rest. The result has been weaponized sanctimony rather than international peace.</p>
   <p>We do want a rules-based order. Where are these rules written, asks Vladimir Putin, and who has written them? They are good questions, but there can be no document. Russia and the United States both can bomb and bribe, can make high-minded speeches, write manifestoes, whatever. The United Nations can declare whatever it wants.</p>
   <p>But the rules are written in how we collectively behave, not in anything Anthony Blinken or Sergey Lavrov or Wang Yi can proclaim, or that the United Nations might ratify. We can only write the rules together. Those who demand deference rather than earn respect ultimately have the least say in their composition. Unfortunately, anyone can contribute to their decomposition.</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/12/14/norms-mean-you-cant-pull-rank/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b>
   <br>
    [2023-12-14 @ 12:20 PM EST]
  </div>
 </div>
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Dec 2023 18:15:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">
        https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/12/10/theres-no-such-thing-as-international-law/index.html
      </guid>
      <author>nospam@dev.null (Steve Randy Waldman)</author>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[The United States’ diplomatic establishment likes to talk about a thing called the “rules-based order”, and to cite others, like Russia invading Ukraine, for violations of it. Vladimir Putin, for his part, has asked where are these rules written, and who gets to write them? One has to concede that these are good questions. A more academic exposition of Putin’s position can be found in this essay by John Dugard, which contrasts the "rules-based order" with "international law”, on the presumption...]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/12/10/theres-no-such-thing-as-international-law/index.html</link>
      <title>There's no such thing as international law</title>
      <dc:creator><![CDATA[Steve Randy Waldman]]></dc:creator>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rssuid-no-such-thing-as-international-law">
 <div class="entry-header">
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <p>The United States’ diplomatic establishment likes to talk about a thing called the “rules-based order”, and to cite others, like Russia invading Ukraine, for violations of it. Vladimir Putin, for his part, <a href="https://www.rt.com/russia/584993-putin-rules-based-order/">has asked</a> where are these rules written, and who gets to write them? One has to concede that these are good questions.</p>
   <p>A more academic exposition of Putin’s position can be found in <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/leiden-journal-of-international-law/article/choice-before-us-international-law-or-a-rulesbased-international-order/7BEDE2312FDF9D6225E16988FD18BAF0">this essay by John Dugard</a>, which contrasts the "rules-based order" with "international law”, on the presumption that "international law" is legitimate. He describes, and ultimately endorses, a view of the rules-based order “as the United States’ alternative to international law, an order that encapsulates international law as interpreted by the United States to accord with its national interests, ‘a chimera, meaning whatever the US and its followers want it to mean at any given time’.”</p>
   <p>He’s right enough about the “rules-based order”. But he’s wrong, in my view, that there is some more legitimate project, “international law”, which the United States’ malleable alternative undermines.</p>
   <p>International law is a cargo cult. It has founding documents and esoteric codes and courts that interpret them, just like national legal systems do. All of that is masturbatory and ultimately quite destructive, in my view. It adds a liturgical patina of law to a set of practices that cannot operate as law. International law cannot come anywhere near keeping its end of the most basic bargain that the law makes to those whom it binds: If you conform, you will be protected.</p>
   <p>Obviously that six word formulation of the basis of law needs caveats and elaboration. Sometimes, for example, the law compels a person to fight and to die for their country, quite the opposite of protection. Sometimes the law requires that a person who has committed no crime must leave their home, even when they have no other destination but the streets. Just exactly what the law protects of those whom it binds is always a matter of contestation. But at a minimum it means that those who abide the law will be treated equitably when the coercive power of the state is brought to bear. Similarly situated citizens will be treated similarly, and the basis for state discrimination, when citizens are seen not to be similarly situated and can be treated differently, must be widely accepted and adhered to for a body of coercive practice to be understood as law.</p>
   <p>For example, Jim Crow law was, from the vantage of today, not law at all, just a law-like patina on a practice of oppression. From the vantage of its own time, whether it was law depends upon just how universally its discriminations were accepted and adhered to. To the degree those subject to its very invidious discriminations internalized and accepted its distinctions — even if they disliked them and could argue against them in theory — then it did function as law. Once sizable classes of people did not accept those dinstinctions, and began actively to resist the "law", well, then it ceased to function as law at all. Legal order was only restored in the United States by revising the putative law to a version that the law’s resisters would accede to, and using the coercive power of the state when necessary to overpower and demoralize the resistance that same revision of the order provoked.</p>
   <p>Legal order might have been restored the other way, by overpowering and demoralizing Jim Crow’s resisters, instead of those who resisted civil rights. That a thing is law does not mean it is good. It just means that it performs a function that is prerequisite to the form of social order provided by modern states. Food is necessary for life, and Cheetos perform the function of food, but that doesn’t mean there are no important distinctions to be made between a fine meal and Cheetos.</p>
   <p>International law is <em>not even</em> not-law in the way that Jim Crow became not-law when postwar social movements rendered it illegitimate and widely resisted. Fundamentally law is a bargain between citizens who generally abide it and a state that holds both a monopoly on legitimate violence and a near monopoly in practice over violent coercion. If adherence to the law purchases equitable treatment when the coercive power of the state is brought to bear, then it buys nothing at all if there is no state, if there is no entity with a near monopoly on violent coercion that distinguishes those who abide the law from those who do not. International law is not in crisis, the way American law came into crisis in the 1950s and 1960s. "Law" is simply a construct that cannot be meaningfully applied to the international order as currently constituted.</p>
   <p>Without any institution that credibly stands in for the “state", without a coherent agent that holds a monopoly on legitimate violence and a near monopoly in practice over violent coercion, to use the word "law” is to perform exactly the kind of rhetorical legerdemain that John Dugard accuses of the "rules based order”. It becomes a loose, flimsy tactic for importing an aura of legitimacy to whatever outcome one might be pursuing.</p>
   <p>Israel is committing crimes against international law, say its critics. For the record, I agree at a moral level with those critics. Israel’s prosecution of its current war is morally indefensible. I would shed few tears for a Netanyahu at Nuremberg. But a few days ago, the security counsel by its duly chartered procedure declined to demand a cease fire which — in the unlikely event that Israel complied — would have halted those “crimes”. Do those who say Israel’s practices are war crimes under international law now stand corrected, since the body closest to a supreme international legal institution has declined to intervene?</p>
   <p>When the US Supreme Court declines to proscribe partisan gerrymandering, those of us who are outraged understand that means the practice has essentially been legalized, at least until Congress or a future Court changes the situation. Partisan gerrymandering is abhorrent, a deep violation of democratic and ethical norms, but it is legal in the United States. Similarly, prior to the overturning of Roe vs Wade, there were plenty of state-level statutes “on the books” forbidding abortion, but as they were unenforceable, nobody mistook them for law.</p>
   <p>Are international law proponents willing to say, following the United States’ veto under duly authorized procedures of the United Nations Security Counsel, that Israel’s continuing war on Gaza is legal? (Yes, some of its tactics might still be judiciable at an International Court for Justice, whose edicts Israel has in the past ignored without consequence.) The Security Counsel could have intervened against Russia over its invasion of Ukraine, but it has not and would vote (veto) down any attempt to do so. Then isn’t that invasion also legal?</p>
   <p>Of course proponents of international law will not say that. Because proponents of international law don’t actually mean anything like what we mean by law in a nation-state context. No less than America’s “rules-based order”, international law contains an explosion of mutually contradicting verbiage and ideals, and there is no identifiable entity whose actual behavior supervenes into a coherent set of expectations to which some body of citizens (or states, in an international context) might mutually conform.</p>
   <p>There’s no such thing as international law. And yet global affairs are far from anarchic. How do we actually organize and sustain the (remarkably high!) degree of peace and interchange that prevails?</p>
   <p>World affairs, like the vast majority of human affairs, are governed not by laws but by norms. If we want to think clearly about “the world order”, and to prevent the various apocalypses its breakdown might occasion, we’ll have to think more clearly than we have about the distinction, about how norms work rather than laws.</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/12/10/theres-no-such-thing-as-international-law/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b>
   <br>
    [2023-12-10 @ 06:15 PM EST]
  </div>
 </div>
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2023 11:20:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">
        https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/11/30/obama-was-the-most-destructive-political-figure-of-my-lifetime/index.html
      </guid>
      <author>nospam@dev.null (Steve Randy Waldman)</author>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[Matt Yglesias has a piece today called “Obama mostly got things right”. I expected to disagree with it, because I think Barack Obama was the most destructive political figure of my lifetime. But I agree with much of it! Yglesias just skips everything important, so he can sound contrarian now that the Democratic Party has actually managed to learn something. Yglesias cops to errors of the Obama administration, such as the ARRA stimulus being too small, setting the economy up for a decade of...]]>
      </description>
      <link>
        https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/11/30/obama-was-the-most-destructive-political-figure-of-my-lifetime/index.html
      </link>
      <title>Obama was the most destructive political figure of my lifetime</title>
      <dc:creator><![CDATA[Steve Randy Waldman]]></dc:creator>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header">
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <p>Matt Yglesias has a piece today called “<a href="https://www.slowboring.com/p/obama-mostly-got-things-right">Obama mostly got things right</a>”. I expected to disagree with it, because I think Barack Obama was the most destructive political figure of my lifetime. But I agree with much of it! Yglesias just skips everything important, so he can sound contrarian now that the Democratic Party has actually managed to learn something.</p>
   <p>Yglesias cops to errors of the Obama administration, such as the ARRA stimulus being too small, setting the economy up for a decade of demand deficiency. But he points out, correctly enough, that too small a check in a tough political environment represents not some grand mistake, but navigating trade-offs imperfectly.</p>
   <p>Yglesias is less defensibly revisionist when he writes “insufficient stimulus would generate a midterm wipeout that would bring several years of needless austerity budgeting as a knock-on consequence.” Obama actively embraced austerity, and nobody made him. In 2010, before the great shellacking, he made “belt-tightening”, budgeting the Federal government like a household, a centerpiece of his <a href="https://obamawhitehouse.archives.gov/the-press-office/remarks-president-state-union-address">State of the Union address</a>. Yglesias, at least, is smart enough to understand that during an era of demand deficiency, government finances are nothing at all like household finances and "belt tightening” by the state is dumb. Call it MMT, or just Keynes' Paradox of Thrift. As far as anyone can tell, Obama sincerely believed of the economy in 2010 what Yglesias believes of the economy today, that expenditure by the Federal government was unaffordable, that it crowded out (rather than crowding in) important alternative activity. Obama preached the gospel of deficit reduction when the unemployment rate was nearly 10%.</p>
   <p>Okay. Whatever. Obama had inherited the Clinton/Greenspan “responsible fiscal policy” orthodoxy. Treated as a timeless truth rather than a circumstance-contingent tactic, that orthodoxy is mistaken and destructive. But it’s a small piece of why Barack Obama’s presidency was a catastrophe.</p>
   <p>Barack Obama ran as a transformational figure, and in 2008, the United States needed a transformational figure. “<a href="https://www.npr.org/2008/11/05/96624326/transcript-of-barack-obamas-victory-speech">I will ask you join in the work</a> of remaking this nation the only way it's been done in America for 221 years — block by block, brick by brick, callused hand by callused hand.” He blazed into the political scene, and won the nomination from Hillary Clinton on a promise to govern differently. But instead he governed assiduously the same, exactly in the Clintonite tradition. When in power, he shut out and mocked the very people he had seduced during his campaign. He was an outsider who reveled in having made it to the inside, to the very pinnacle of the halls of power. He partied with Larry Summers rather than throw open the doors to the ball.</p>
   <p>By 2008, America was “coming apart” (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coming_Apart_(book)">Charles Murray’s apt phrase</a>). But that was as invisible to the United States' political class as the opioid epidemic had been in 2016, until Donald Trump brought it to the fore. Railing against <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/68.html">Wall Street and Walmart</a> and <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/55.html">inequality</a> was thankless work, then. The center of American politics saw these things more as triumphs than problems. The public was experiencing decline and tragedy that their leaders perceived not at all. Barack Obama — in his rhetoric much more than his track record, but rhetoric is what built his "movement” — promised a change. Yes we can! Hope! The fierce urgency of now!</p>
   <p>Then he got elected, and became as blind as the rest of them.</p>
   <p>He still gave great speeches sometimes. Barack Obama can speak amazingly, his words radiating perception and empathy and wisdom. But juxtaposed against how he actually governed, the remarkable quality of those speeches came to seem more like narcissistic celebration of the speaker’s talents than any part of the work of healing the world.</p>
   <p>How did Obama govern? What did he do that was so bad? I agree with Yglesias that the too-small ARRA stimulus was an error, not some great betrayal. I also agree with Yglesias that Obama’s universalistic approach to the politics of race was far better than the strident, performative antiracism that now dominates progressive politics.</p>
   <p>But you discredit even the best of your ideals when you sell your coalition out. That’s the heart of it. Obama inherited a financial crisis that represented the market system itself working desperately to course-correct, to undo some of the concentration of wealth and power three decades of bad policy and exuberant malinvestment had engendered. “My administration,” he <a href="https://newrepublic.com/article/48854/obama-bankers-beware-the-pitchforks">told the bankers</a>, “is the only thing between you and the pitchforks.” The public, pitchforks in hand, observed just that.</p>
   <p>Barack Obama, Timothy Geithner, Larry Summers steered us through the Great Financial Crisis. When it was over, banking and financial power were more concentrated than they ever had been, while millions of Americans had lost their homes as programs ostensibly designed to help them were cynically administered instead to “<a href="https://www.salon.com/2014/05/14/this_man_made_millions_suffer_tim_geithners_sorry_legacy_on_housing/">foam the runway</a>” for banks, in Geithner’s memorable phrase. The Great-Gatsby-ish world that people like Geithner and Summers — and now Barack Obama too — inhabit had been saved. The few factories that remained were still fleeing to China. Great tracts of the remains of someone’s American dream were getting looted for copper in Maricopa County.</p>
   <p>People who had voted for Obama, who had placed their hopes and dreams in his soaring rhetoric, his promise of change, were left devastated. White midwesterners became so-called Obama-to-Trump voters. They understandably perceived the “progressivism” for which Obama was hope-poster-child to be a sham, a shell game, a self-congratulatory exercise by a class of people who disdain them, exclude them, pretend to help them even while they prey upon them, mock and of course deplore them for the slightest transgression of their pieties. The less white part of the Obama coalition, a Black middle class which seemed briefly, finally, to be joining an American Dream of building wealth through homeownership, was decimated by the Obama presidency. The very same disillusionment that drove the white working class to Trump brought a renaissance of the muscular racial politics of the 1970s, renarrated through the kind of ideas that thrive in academia because their cleverness and radicalness and intentionally obscured simplicity render them useful for persuading colleagues and students that you are cool and worthy of tenure. The “Progressive left” (Yglesias’ “Lizard People”) and downscale MAGA voters are polarized now into enemy camps, but they are sisters and brothers sprung from the same seed.</p>
   <p>Joe Biden, to his very great credit, understands this.</p>
   <p>Yglesias is clear that he dislikes contemporary progressive racial politics. Yglesias mocks the anti-austerity economic coalition he was once — but with unusual sophistication, of course — an active part of, for allegedly not getting that their recommendations need to change with macroeconomic times. (This is a bit ironic in a piece rehabilitating Obama.) Yglesias describes people (like me!) “not enthusiastic about Biden in the 2020 primary but…pleasantly surprised by his openness to Lizardism on a range of topics.”</p>
   <p>Is Yglesias not enthusiastic about Biden’s Lizardism? What does he think of the problem of <a href="https://www.thebignewsletter.com/">economic concentration</a>, and Biden’s clear support for reviving an antitrust tradition focused on ensuring dispersion of economic power broadly, rather than consumer welfare narrowly construed in prices? Was Biden's appointment of Lina Khan bad Lizardism? How about the Biden administration’s labor policy, his willingness to actually walk a UAW picket line, his NLRB's <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/how-to-unionize-illegal-union-busting-nlrb-rules-2023-8">making the price</a> of being found to union-bust instant recognition of the union? What does Ygesias think of the Biden administration’s <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/briefing-room/speeches-remarks/2023/04/27/remarks-by-national-security-advisor-jake-sullivan-on-renewing-american-economic-leadership-at-the-brookings-institution/">New Washington Consensus</a>?</p>
   <p>I know what I think. I think Joe Biden has learned something from the catastrophe that was his prior administration, and is finally, at long last, beginning the work that Barack Obama promised, “block by block, brick by brick, callused hand by callused hand.” I am shocked that this man — the Senator from MBNA who famously jousted with Elizabeth Warren in service of debt peonage — has in a quiet way begun the sort of economic transformation the United States desperately requires. If Joe Biden is on the ballot in 2024, I will vote <em>for</em> him, and it will only be the second time in my 54 years that I will be voting <em>for</em> anyone, rather than against the other guy, in a US general Presidential election.</p>
   <p>The first time was for Barack Obama.</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/11/30/obama-was-the-most-destructive-political-figure-of-my-lifetime/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b>
   <br>
    [2023-11-30 @ 11:20 AM EST]
  </div>
 </div>
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Nov 2023 22:10:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/11/15/how-rights-make-wrongs/index.html</guid>
      <author>nospam@dev.null (Steve Randy Waldman)</author>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[There is no way to reconcile a right of existence of two "peoples" who view themselves as distinct and mean to maintain their distinctions; each people's "right" to national self-determination; every individual's right to full enfranchisement within their state; each people's, and every family’s, right not to be dispossessed of or forced from their own homes or lands; a right of any person, or the descendant thereof, to return to the particular geographies from which they or their ancestors...]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/11/15/how-rights-make-wrongs/index.html</link>
      <title>How rights make wrongs</title>
      <dc:creator><![CDATA[Steve Randy Waldman]]></dc:creator>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header">
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <p>There is no way to reconcile</p>
   <ol>
    <li>
     <p>a right of existence of two "peoples" who view themselves as distinct and mean to maintain their distinctions;</p></li>
    <li>
     <p>each people's "right" to national self-determination;</p></li>
    <li>
     <p>every individual's right to full enfranchisement within their state;</p></li>
    <li>
     <p>each people's, and every family’s, right not to be dispossessed of or forced from their own homes or lands;</p></li>
    <li>
     <p>a right of any person, or the descendant thereof, to return to the particular geographies from which they or their ancestors were historically dispossessed</p></li>
   </ol>
   <p>If you want to keep [1], [2], and [3], you must abrogate [4] and [5]. That's the two-state solution.</p>
   <p>If you want to keep [3], [4], and [5], you must abrogate [1] and [2]. That's the binational liberal democracy solution.</p>
   <p>The worst people on both sides of the conflict emphasize all of these rights at once.</p>
   <p>Both Israeli settlers and from-the-river-to-the-sea Palestinians cede no ground on [4] and [5].</p>
   <p>Likud and Hamas are entirely agreed in their demand for [1]. They are entirely averse to any kind of melting pot assimilation between the two peoples.</p>
   <p>Neither side will accept as legitimate colonial rule by some third power. Neither will accept second-class status beneath the other "people”, whether <em>de jure</em> (as the stateless Palestinians have endured, but do not accept) or <em>de facto</em>, due to demographic outcomes under notionally equal suffrage.</p>
   <p>Right [2] is nonnegogtiable, and right [3] is not consistent with [2] unless demographics can be engineered, which would contradict rights [4] and [5] and invite charges of ethnic cleansing.</p>
   <p>There is, however, one right that maximalists on both sides of the conflict are mutually willing to compromise upon.</p>
   <ol start="0">
    <li>The right of human beings to live in peace and safety, and not see their children murdered or made into murderers.</li>
   </ol>
   <p>If none of Rights [1] through [5] will be ceded, then Right [0] must give way.</p>
   <p>The worst people on both sides of the conflict emphasize rights [1] through [5] all at once.</p>
   <p>And so has the “international community”, for decades.</p>
   <p>Sanctimonious application of a human rights regime laden with internal tensions and contradictions guarantees that eventually some rights will give way. Maximalists can credibly condemn any proposed compromise as an illegitimate abrogation of rights, and so forestall any action they dislike that might reduce the tensions.</p>
   <p>The predictable effect is that some of these rights will give way all at once, in a crisis, provoking what will correctly be perceived as a terrible injustice to one or both of the parties.</p>
   <p>On Right [0] there has been a great deal of compromise already. Unfortunately that leaves partisans of both communities even more determined to exercise the other rights.</p>
   <p>Right [0] is the only claim that ought ever have been codified into a universal human right. The rest are legitimate aspirations, but human beings and human communities have conflicting, mutually inconsistent aspirations that somehow have to be managed.</p>
   <p>Canonicalizing a broad range of such aspirations into "rights" — which we sanctimoniously promise to uphold (but in practice uphold selectively, because they would be impossible to uphold universally, and of course our selection may not be even-handed) — has been a bloody, catastrophic, mistake.</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/11/15/how-rights-make-wrongs/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b>
   <br>
    [2023-11-15 @ 10:10 PM EST]
  </div>
 </div>
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <atom:link type="application/rss+xml" rel="self" href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/feed/index.rss"/>
  </channel>
</rss>
