<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss 
version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>drafts — interfluidity</title>
    <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/index.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[Feed for blog 'drafts — interfluidity' generated by unstatic]]></description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 1 Mar 2023 15:27:30 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>https://github.com/swaldman/unstatic</generator>
    <docs>https://cyber.harvard.edu/rss/rss.html</docs>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Wed, 1 Mar 2023 15:15:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">
        https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/01/higher-education-is-shockingly-right-wing/index.html
      </guid>
      <author>nospam@dev.null (Steve Randy Waldman)</author>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[Higher education is shockingly right-wing Perhaps the stupidest idea that everyone takes for granted is that higher education in the United States is left-wing. If "left" and "right" have any meaning at all, "right" describes a worldview under which civilized society depends upon legitimate hierarchy, and a key object of politics is properly defining and protecting that hierarchy. "Left", on the other hand, is animated by antipathy to hierarchy, by an egalitarianism of dignity. While left-wing...]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/01/higher-education-is-shockingly-right-wing/index.html</link>
      <title>Higher education is shockingly right-wing</title>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header">
  <h1><a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/01/higher-education-is-shockingly-right-wing/index.html">Higher education is shockingly right-wing</a></h1>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <p>Perhaps the stupidest idea that everyone takes for granted is that higher education in the United States is left-wing.</p>
   <p>If "left" and "right" have any meaning at all, "right" describes a worldview under which civilized society depends upon legitimate hierarchy, and a key object of politics is properly defining and protecting that hierarchy.</p>
   <p>"Left", on the other hand, is animated by antipathy to hierarchy, by an egalitarianism of dignity. While left-wing movements recognize that effective institutions must place people in different roles — sometimes hierarchical, sometimes associated with unequal rewards — these are contingent, often problematic, overlays upon a foundational assertion that every human being has equal dignity and equal claim to the fundamental goods of human life.</p>
   <p>Whatever else colleges and universities do in the United States, they define and police our most consequential social hierarchy, the dividing line between a prosperous <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/7263.html">if precarious</a> professional class and a larger, often immiserated, working class. The credentials universities provide are no guarantee of escape from paycheck-to-paycheck living, but statistically they are a near prerequisite.</p>
   <p>The academy itself is incredibly hierarchical. Within a university, distinctions reign between a graduate student or postdoc, an adjunct, an assistant professor on tenure track, an associate versus full professor. These ranks are salient and consequential, treated as legitimate and earnestly policed.</p>
   <p>Nothing is spared hierarchy in academia. Institutions are organized into pecking orders. Harvard University and Towson University are not the same. Everyone understands their relative rank, the <a href="https://www.oxfordreference.com/display/10.1093/oi/authority.20110803104247382;jsessionid=A3607E3AA98E806AB399FC75DC2F9817">social consequences of which are very real</a>.</p>
   <p>If you are an academic at a level beyond community college or adjunct professorship, you have devoted your life to swimming upstream, besting competitors who will relegated to lower ranks or simply expectorated from academic life. It is a key part of your job to rank and sort other people, whether they be the undergrads that you grade or the faculty your department hires. You strive to have your work published in "top-tier" journals.</p>
   <p>To be an academic and be left-wing is like being a fish opposed to water. It is not persuasive. Or it ought not to be.</p>
   <p>Of course it is true that the vast majority of professors "identify" as progressive or liberal or left. That is understandable! At a mass-level, the left-wing view that we are fundamentally equal in dignity has won the day. Even political movements that claim to be right-wing, that act overtly to defend and entrench social hierarchies, must pay lip-service to egalitarian norms to have any success in our electral democracy.</p>
   <p>Professors are people too. They don't like to think of themselves as the bone structure of our society's most consequentially oppressive hierarchy. At an individual level, they are wonderful people. And they are smart. They understand at some level that their role is problematic. But, individually, there is nothing they can do about that. They could opt out, cede their slot to the next striver, but that wouldn't change anything about the structure of our society and the role of academia within it. But it would cost them personally, tremendously.</p>
   <p>So, successful academics hew a path quite analogous to that taken by so many graduates of the prestigious schools they run. "I'll work at McKinsey, or Goldman, or Google, because doing so will provide me with resources to do some good, later, somehow." Academics, like most of us, would prefer a less hierarchical society, but they tell themselves that the best they can do is gain some social power by... contending for an elite position inside the hierarchy and using whatever influence comes from that to further a less hierarchical ideal. This attempt to use the <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/291810-for-the-master-s-tools-will-never-dismantle-the-master-s-house">master's tools to dismantle the master's house</a> is not very convincing on its face, so academics have to work unusually hard to convince themselves that they are not bad people. This encourages an unusually expressive and radical politics.</p>
   <p>Universities become bastions of an ostentatious "leftism" even while these same leftists perform the workaday labor of sorting and excluding upon which our stratified society depends. I'm not a fan of psychological explanations for political difference, but it does seem a touch neurotic.</p>
   <p>It is also counterproductive, in two respects:</p>
   <ul>
    <li><p>While <em>individually</em> academics may be helpless to affect the unequal distributions of dignity and deserts which their vocations undergird, collectively they have tremendous capacity to reform and reshape academia. Instead of taking pride in how exclusive their institutions are, professors could work as a group to discredit the conflation of exclusivity and merit. If a Harvard degree is so valuable, professors could insist the university franchise as liberally as McDonalds and grow the freshman class to tens of thousands. That should be practical, if the value-add is actual education. If Harvard's value to undergraduates is based on scarcity and social connection, well maybe that's the kind of institution the very best academics, if their political commitments are real, should refuse — <em>as an organized class, rather than as ineffectually expressive individuals</em> — to participate in at all.</p></li>
    <li><p>The combination of flamboyant left-wing expression and bitterly exclusive, hierarchical norms that nearly everyone has experienced directly (perhaps at a high-school level when they were sorted as unlikely to be college material) discredits left-wing political activism broadly as a sham.</p> <p>Right-wing grievance entrepreneurs complain that they have been locked out of the institutions and must make a long march to retake them. They pretend that Gramsci and Marcuse have won the culture for "the left" and their only hope is some desperate hail mary. Don't be a fucking idiot and take them at their word.</p> <p>Right-wing grievance entrepreneurs go after higher education because its role in politics is incoherent and hypocritical, in a way that the public viscerally experiences. Universities are attacked not because "the left" is strong within them, but because the academy's paperthin but shouty commitment to equal dignity makes it easy to present the whole left project as a sham, a trojan horse by which some sanctimonious elite is going to jam down arrangements under which <em>their</em> dignity and prosperity will somehow always be first among equals.</p></li>
   </ul>
   <p>Academia is right-wing, structurally. Diversifying academia in the conventional sense, bringing more members of underrepresented groups into higher rungs of the hierarchy, would not alter that fact. Left academics who analyze structural injustice so assiduously might take this obvious reality more seriously into account.</p>
   <p>Because as things stand, while academics sanctimoniously (and correctly!) opine about fascism and structural racism, the institutions they serve have become ever more consequential gatekeepers in an ever more extractive relationship with the students they purport to serve. Perhaps there are causes more proximate than 1619 why the public has become predisposed not to take alarms rung by earnest professors at face value.</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/03/01/higher-education-is-shockingly-right-wing/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b><br>[2023-03-01 @ 03:15 PM EST]
  </div>
 </div>
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2023 23:55:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/02/27/new-college/index.html</guid>
      <author>nospam@dev.null (Steve Randy Waldman)</author>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[New College After you’re dead, do you care if it’s the end of the world? New College is my goto metaphor when I contemplate death. You wonder what it will be like, all of life is this vivid stream of experience, and then all of a sudden it's just... gone? The high-school drama cliché play "Our Town" always brings me to tears. In the play, a town's graveyard becomes a kind of a greek chorus or MST3K riff. The dead once set there become spectators, chatting about the antics of the living. Only,...]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/02/27/new-college/index.html</link>
      <title>New College</title>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header">
  <h1><a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/02/27/new-college/index.html">New College</a></h1>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <p>After you’re dead, do you care if it’s the end of the world?</p>
   <p><em>New College</em> is my goto metaphor when I contemplate death. You wonder what it will be like, all of life is this vivid stream of experience, and then all of a sudden it's just... gone?</p>
   <p>The high-school drama cliché play <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Our_Town">"Our Town"</a> always brings me to tears. In the play, a town's graveyard becomes a kind of a greek chorus or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Our_Town">MST3K</a> riff. The dead once set there become spectators, chatting about the antics of the living. Only, over time, they become ever more forgetful and indifferent. The living world begins, when you are among the living, as an object of such intensity and care. You cannot help but feel pain, excitement, love, annoyance, hatred, hope, disappointment, triumph, anxiety, joy. The living world draws from you such attention. But time comes. Eventually it washes away all of your attention, all of your care.</p>
   <p>When I think of death I think of <em>New College</em> because the difference between life there and life after was a difference in kind like that. It was not (like physical death only sometimes is) a sharp transition. You graduate, you move away. You still know some people, keep in touch. But eventually it occurs to you that your ever less frequent chatter is like the gossiping among denizens of Thornton Wilder's cemetary.</p>
   <p>When I wonder how it will be to be dead, this is what I think. Experience is irredicible, axiomatic, beyond explanation or science. Whatever I am that experiences will in some indeterminate sense continue to experience.</p>
   <p>But care, care is contingent and fragile, an equilibrium balanced on the tip of a single strand of hair, at the mercy of an indifferent physics. Care depends upon memory, also fragile. I think I won't remember, just like now I can hardly remember the stream of years of days — rapids rather than a babbling brook — that was my time at <em>New College</em>.</p>
   <p>When I was at <em>New College</em>, I was a <em>New College</em> nationalist. There were politics then and now, and I realized, standing one day in <a href="https://michaeljamesfreedman.com/products/palm-court">Palm Court</a>, that I would die for <em>New College</em>, for that place, that community, if that were somehow called for. I was probably twenty years old, and I understood quite self-consciously how ridiculous this would seem to, well, almost everybody. <em>New College</em>, after all, is just a college. It is a means to an end. It is preparing us, the story goes, for something greater, for our productive adult lives.</p>
   <p>I knew that's how the world would think. But the world is full of idiots. I remembered life before <em>New College</em> and I knew, quite correctly, that life afterwards was more likely to be banal than something greater just because now I would have a degree and <em>skillz</em>.</p>
   <p><em>New College</em> was a stab at utopia. A stab. Life at <em>New College</em> was sharp and often painful. But we together flew closer to the sun than I would ever fly before or since. The purpose of <em>New College</em> wasn't to prepare us for the next thing, but for us to live together more richly and more fully, intellectually and otherwise, than would ever be possible in the world surrounding us. If the institution had a role to play in the larger world, it was not to produce more Fulbright Scholars and doctoral students, better <em>US News</em> rankings. That might be a kind of cover story, the justification for our funding, whatever. Our role was to experience an intensity of <a href="https://theconvivialsociety.substack.com/">conviviality</a> that our society can no longer remember or sustain, and carry some spark of that memory, some fading ember, when the academic cycle cast us out like dandelion seeds, like balooning spiderlings. Perhaps something from the experience would be left in our venom. I hope, dear reader, somewhere in all these words I've written, now and over 16 years, just a little bit of that poison has found you.</p>
   <p>Ron DeSantis is <a href="https://washingtonmonthly.com/2023/02/15/why-does-ron-desantis-want-to-fix-a-high-ranking-college/">trying to transform</a> <em>New College</em> into <a href="https://www.hillsdale.edu/">Hillsdale College</a> or whatever. He's an asteroid hitting a planet, pulled by some political gravity, stupid and indifferent to what he is destroying. <em>New College</em> is not just some "liberal arts college" that is woke or left-wing. It's a liberal arts college like Dr. Who's mode of transport was a telephone booth. Yes, sure, but perhaps also a bit more than that.</p>
   <p>I cannot speak to how "woke" <em>New College</em> has or hasn't become. I've been dead — I'm sorry, graduated — almost thirty years. But I suspect there is some continuity, between whatever thrives now on that sunny little campus and the experiment in living I was once a part of.</p>
   <p>The dead forget so much and care so little. Time scatters and numbs us. Yet, whether the fact is hopeful or it is tragic, it turns out the dead do still care about the end of the world. We can feel just that much pain.</p>
   <hr>
   <p><strong>Postscript:</strong></p>
   <p>Here is me circa 1993, from some marketing thing produced then by the college. Thanks Alice Abarca for having unearthed it. The shirt, which Camilla Mortensen and I screened with Gary Jurman's help, fits surprisingly into contemporary court cases and culture wars. But to pay much attention to that misses every meaningful point.</p> <img alt="a quote and photo of the author, spewing the same views he spews here, but in 1993" src="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/02/27/new-college/from-1993-admissions-catalog-via-alice-abarca.jpg" width="100%">
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/02/27/new-college/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b><br>[2023-02-27 @ 11:55 PM EST]
  </div>
 </div>
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2023 02:45:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/02/27/instead/index.html</guid>
      <author>nospam@dev.null (Steve Randy Waldman)</author>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[Instead I find myself falling into old habits. In a shower, on a walk, I am composing a future post. Already there are three or four, already much of what has been composed has been forgotten. I like to imagine the things I forget in this way are not lost, but are fertilizer. What is best will rise from the loam when I rouse myself to think of it again, when I actually. Write. The. Post. But most of those posts never get written. Sometimes (the result of a previous round of enthusiasm and angst...]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/02/27/instead/index.html</link>
      <title>Instead</title>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header">
  <h1><a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/02/27/instead/index.html">Instead</a></h1>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <p>I find myself falling into old habits.</p>
   <p>In a shower, on a walk, I am composing a future post. Already there are three or four, already much of what has been composed has been forgotten.</p>
   <p>I like to imagine the things I forget in this way are not lost, but are fertilizer. What is best will rise from the loam when I rouse myself to think of it again, when I actually. Write. The. Post.</p>
   <p>But most of those posts never get written. Sometimes (the result of a previous round of enthusiasm and angst to do something about this) I'll scribble some kind of draft or outline in a notes app I pay for only to make myself feel guilty for not using. The "interfluidity" folder there now has tens of notes of representing intended posts. Often a note is just a title, which I imagine will be sufficient to revive the conversation with myself that inspired it. Some of those titles are completely inscrutable to me now.</p>
   <p>The <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/02/21/hello/index.html">point of this "drafts blog"</a> was to skip the whole thing-I-intend-to-write-about-in-future step, and just write the damned thing instead. Badly, imperfectly, a first draft. But publicly, because what I don't do publicly I feel like I have not done at all. For some posts, there are paragraphs or even pages of text in the notes app. They are nothing until (right around the heat death of the universe) I draft the post.</p>
   <p>I've been hoping, but failing, to write a post a day on this blog. But maybe it'd be better to strive for that style of blogging that all the young, ambitious journalists used to grind, several posts a day, just a few hundred words each.</p>
   <p>I doubt I will pull that off. But maybe if the expectation is I write multiple times a day, when I find myself walking and talking and composing I'll just run to the machine and write something.</p>
   <p>I've blogged for almost two decades, but I don't like how I've been doing it. It hasn't been working. I want to do something else. Just write the damned thing instead.</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/02/27/instead/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b><br>[2023-02-27 @ 02:45 AM EST]
  </div>
 </div>
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Feb 2023 12:25:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/02/24/thick-antitrust/index.html</guid>
      <author>nospam@dev.null (Steve Randy Waldman)</author>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[Thick antitrust In the graphic at the heart of the previous draft, I used the term "thick antitrust". I want to unpack that a bit. Often when we think of antitrust, we think of "a cop on the beat", blocking mergers, policing price collusion, breaking up consolidations of economic power. And we do want such cops on the beat! I am very grateful that we have Lina Khan as the chair of the FTC. However, a very old theme at interfluidity is that we should prefer structural over supervisory solutions....]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/02/24/thick-antitrust/index.html</link>
      <title>Thick antitrust</title>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rss">
 <div class="entry-header">
  <h1><a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/02/24/thick-antitrust/index.html">Thick antitrust</a></h1>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <p>In the graphic at the heart of <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/02/22/four-quadrants-of-section-230ishness/index.html">the previous draft</a>, I used the term "thick antitrust". I want to unpack that a bit.</p>
   <p>Often when we think of antitrust, we think of "a cop on the beat", blocking mergers, policing price collusion, breaking up consolidations of economic power. And we do want such cops on the beat! I am very grateful that we have <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lina_Khan">Lina Khan</a> as the chair of the FTC.</p>
   <p>However, a very <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/posts/1258156478.shtml">old</a> <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/197.html">theme</a> at <em>interfluidity</em> is that we should prefer structural over supervisory solutions. Regulators come and go, enforcement of a given regulatory scheme may be a priority of one administration and then actively undermined by the next. Industry interests are consistent and persistent in a way that political fashions are not. Over time, the probability that supervisory agencies will become largely captured by the industries they regulate approaches one, until, predicatably, a crisis emerges from the misregulation which provokes the politicians pick up their pitchforks for a minute and the cycle begins anew.</p>
   <p>If you've given any thought to the idea of structural racism, you understand that subtle structural facts can lead to outcomes that are quite durable and are perceived by the broad public as ordinary or even "natural". But if we can encode vice into structure, we can also encode virtue.</p>
   <p>The best regulation does not look like regulation at all, but is embedded in the structure of institutions we take for granted, yielding desirable outcomes without very much need for continual enforcement. For example, Jane Jacobs taught us that the broad, tranquil plazas mid-20th-century urban planners imagined and tried to design were structurally incoherent. You don't get tranquility in vast, mostly empty, urban spaces. You get crime. Yes, you can try to address this by hiring lots of cops to supervise the space. But a better approach is to encourage busy, bustling streetscapes. "Eyes on the street", along with the proprietary interest of shopkeepers and neighbors in the safety of their neighborhood, will do a far better job, more reliably, more cheaply, largely invisibly.</p>
   <p>"Thick antitrust" is the idea that we should craft a regulatory environment in which undesirable forms of scale are simply not adaptive. We can rely less on fragile policing of economic power when provision at scale is uneconomic.</p>
   <p>Usually, regulation seeks to <em>enable</em> scale on efficiency grounds, and it is not always wrong to do so. How often do you hear lobbyists and regulators alike aver that firms "should not have to contend with 50 different regulatory schemes in 50 different states"? Whether by harmonizing state laws or imposing a Federal framework that preempts them, we usually work to make the marketplace friendly to large-scale business.</p>
   <p>And often that's the right thing to do! When we want a national marketplace in a good or service, when we think there are <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/8882.html">socially valuable economies of scale</a> such that competition should be structured between firms that serve or aspire to serve the national market, then we should harmonize or preempt. We can gain scale efficiencies and prevent predation by local monopolies if we sustain a competitive national market.</p>
   <p>But that "if" is critical. A single national marketplace is very legible to businesspeople interested in consolidating to gain market power, and to financiers who understand that scarcity and control is the only path of sustainable "alpha". When we encourage scale, we may gain efficiencies, but we accept tacit liabilities, including the cost of vigilant supervision and the much greater cost of forseeable failures of that supervision. It's a balance.</p>
   <p>For many activities, it's better simply to render firm-level scale uneconomical. Of course we want the "network effects" on the internet. Network effects are why we built the internet in the first place, duh. But we want the value that comes from interconnection to accrue to participants of the network broadly, rather than being captured within a few very fortunate firms. Precisely because network effects are so strong on the internet, we should seek regulation that favors enterprise at smaller scales. The value of the network can then be captured only by interoperability, by adherence to open standards under which many participants compete on fairly equal terms to provide and profit from connectivity.</p>
   <p>Because intrafirm coordination costs are far lower than the burdens associated with developing open standards, it will always be possible for an "innovator" to provide more value faster by growing network applications under its sole control. But this is the first step towards Cory Doctorow's <a href="https://pluralistic.net/2023/01/21/potemkin-ai/">"enshittification" dynamic</a>. Yes, "blitzscaling" creates an initial spurt of value for customers that is real, and could not have been created so quickly without the proprietary startup. But the cost of that front-loaded fast growth is a tail of predation and extraction and stagnation extending far into the future. The "innovator" will have enclosed for itself all the value that we, the network, create, and will make it difficult for new innovators to emerge.</p>
   <p>It isn't worth it. On the internet, and in finance (another domain where network effects entrench pernicious concentrations of power in early winners), we want to craft regulatory regimes under which scale becomes burdensome. But effective regulation demands elegance. If you just prohibit scale, a million clever lawyers will synthesize a megafirm out of a thousand LLCs, and a perpetual cat-and-mouse game will begin.</p>
   <p>That's much, much better than doing nothing, just bend over and get Googled! But it's still not great.</p>
   <p>One elegant way to discourage market power in an industry is to privilege, for regulatory purposes, aspects of the business that (in the ultimate tech-firm insult) "do not scale". Perhaps, as Section 230 proponents argue, you don't want to just default to the tort system as a regulator of internet firms, safe harbors are necessary to ensure an ecosystem of open and vibrant internet forums. Okay.</p>
   <p>But then rather than offering a blanket shield to any entity that can quilt their speech out of third-party content, why not craft a safe harbor for firms that demonstrate that they moderate and curate with careful attention to context by people informationally local to the speakers and familiar with subcultural norms? <sup id="fnref-1"><a class="footnote-ref" href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/02/24/thick-antitrust/#fn-1">1</a></sup></p>
   <p>Alternatively, some industries can be constructed from whole cloth out of regulation. Notaries, for example, exist to fill a slot created by regulatory norms. So does the legal industry more broadly. And modern banking. Most banks hold not a nugget of gold in any vault, all of the goods and services they provide are made of regulatory fabrications, yet we perceive banks as perfectly natural and quite essential.</p>
   <p>There's been wide-ranging debate on the concept of "information fiduciaries", introduced most prominently by <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2016/10/information-fiduciary/502346/">Jack Balkin and Jonathan Zittrain</a>. Balkin and Zittrain argue that we can make our peace with the megaplatforms that have become both indispensible and intolerable by imposing upon them a framework of legal obligations under which they'd be required they put users' interests before their own in their handling of the data we entrust to them.</p>
   <p>Critics, <a href="https://harvardlawreview.org/2019/12/a-skeptical-view-of-information-fiduciaries/">including</a> the redoubtable Lina Khan, are correctly skeptical. Firms like Facebook, Google, Twitter exist at the scale they do only because of business models based on surveillance of users and an undesirable influence over our collective cognition. Imposing a "fiduciary" obligation upon them would either wrap these harms beneath a sanctimonious legal fig leaf, or else necessitate a transformation tantamount to complete destruction of these firms in their present form.</p>
   <p>But what if we defined an entirely new category of actor, an intermediary who would have legal roles like a notary (current pratices surrounding electronic signatures are absurd), who would function as caretakers of personal data, intermediating between ordinary humans and monsters like Google, with whom nonprofessional individuals cannot meaningfully contend? And what if we enshrined, as a foundational requirement of this new industry, a limit on the ratio between legally responsible humans and the clients to whom they owe their duty?</p>
   <p>It wouldn't scale. Thank goodness.</p>
   <div class="footnotes">
    <hr>
    <ol>
     <li id="fn-1"><p>Of course, forums should still address any external harms their services cause. If defamatory speech is public in a way that would do continuing injury, that might override a general deference to within-communities norms. But careful moderators might be extended more grace in these circumstances than shoddy moderators.</p> <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/02/24/thick-antitrust/#fnref-1" class="footnote-backref">↩</a></li>
    </ol>
   </div>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/02/24/thick-antitrust/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b><br>[2023-02-24 @ 12:25 PM EST]
  </div>
 </div>
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2023 17:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid isPermalink="true">
        https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/02/22/four-quadrants-of-section-230ishness/index.html
      </guid>
      <author>nospam@dev.null (Steve Randy Waldman)</author>
      <description>
        <![CDATA[Four quadrants of Section 230ishness Section 230 is in the news again, as the Supreme Court hears two cases challenging the liability shield. Both cases concern whether large platforms (YouTube and Twitter respectively) should be liable for a role in helping recruit or radicalize terrorists for what their algorithms recommended (YouTube) or what they insufficiently failed to suppress (Twitter). I think it unlikely that the Supreme Court will find liability in these cases. They might well nibble...]]>
      </description>
      <link>https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/02/22/four-quadrants-of-section-230ishness/index.html</link>
      <title>Four quadrants of Section 230ishness</title>
      <content:encoded>
        <![CDATA[<article class="presentation-rssuid-section-230-quadrants">
 <div class="entry-header">
  <h1><a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/02/22/four-quadrants-of-section-230ishness/index.html">Four quadrants of Section 230ishness</a></h1>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-body">
  <div class="flexmark markdown">
   <p>Section 230 is in the news again, as the Supreme Court hears <a href="https://www.supremecourt.gov/DocketPDF/21/21-1333/220254/20220404211548101_GonzalezPetPDF.pdf">two</a> <a href="https://www.supremecourt.gov/DocketPDF/21/21-1496/226415/20220526180216120_21-xxxx%20-%20Twitter%20Inc.%20v.%20Taamneh%20-%20cert.%20petition.pdf">cases</a> challenging the liability shield. Both cases concern whether large platforms (YouTube and Twitter respectively) should be liable for a role in helping recruit or radicalize terrorists for what their algorithms recommended (YouTube) or what they insufficiently failed to suppress (Twitter).</p>
   <p>I think it unlikely that the Supreme Court will find liability in these cases. They might well nibble at the edge of Section 230, distinguishing the present facts from facts under which they might find platform liability despite the Section 230 shield, and that might prove consequential going forward. In the Twitter case, they seem eager to consider some questions about the Anti-Terrorism Act (the act that creates the liability that Section 230 might shield). But the Court understands that serious modification of the judiciary's broad interpretation of Section 230 would dramatically upend a large swathe of the economy, with questionable democratic legitimacy.</p>
   <p>Of course, this Court has been willing to countenace disruption and accept a loss of legitimacy where they are sufficiently ideologically motivated, as they were with abortion. But with the possible exception of Justice Thomas, I don't think there is that kind of motivation here.</p>
   <p>It's not a balls and strikes thing. I think it's entirely reasonable, as a substantive and legal matter, to argue that contemporary algorithmic recommendation and suppression is so different in scale and kind and consequence from the kind of moderation lawmakers considered in 1996 that Section 230 protections might not apply.</p>
   <p>But whatever the merits or demerits of that argument in theory, in practice a whole economy has been built around an aggressive interpretation of Section 230. I think it's a rotten economy, but the Court won't want to unilaterally tear it down, they'll want (probably appropriately) to punt these questions to Congress.</p>
   <p>As readers may or may not know, I've become a <a href="https://www.interfluidity.com/v2/8093.html">Section 230</a> <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2021/01/trump-fighting-section-230-wrong-reason/617497/">skeptic</a>. At a theoretical level, I think Section 230 enshrines a balance of liabilities that is quite perverse. If I, in private anger, text something defamatory about a third party to a friend who then publicly tweets my text, neither of the parties meaningfully responsible for whatever injury the defamed party suffers (the forwarder or the broadcaster) can be held liable, because Section 230 shields them. Only I, who communicated under an expectation of privacy, can be. I think that's dumb.</p>
   <p>But okay, it's an edge case. My animus towards Section 230 is about its central tendency, which has been to eliminate from the profit-and-loss statement very real diseconomies of scale associated with interpreting and curating speech well. Given the reality of network effects, eliminating these countervailing diseconomies has bequeathed to us a consolidated information sphere, dominated by massive platforms whose incentives are to promote engagement rather than high quality deliberation.</p>
   <p>Platforms like Facebook, Twitter, YouTube, etc. are implicated in profound, undeniable harms precisely because they cannot, for example, understand whether or not a post in Myanmar is promoting extermination and genocide. But they can broadcast that post regardless, and profit from the attention it provokes.</p>
   <p>Curating public speech well is an activity that is inherently artisanal, community and context bound. This centrifugal fact should counterbalance the yawning pull of network effects, except we've eliminated as a matter of law any reason for firms to pay attention to it. As a consequence, our public square has become Wonder Bread but worse: mass-produced and low quality, but enriched with no vitamins and minerals other than arsenic. For their trouble, the providers of this disservice have grown into prosperous and predatory monopolies, with profoundly antidemocratic power over public speech.</p>
   <p>Section 230 seemed like a good idea at the time, but we've run the experiment. The results aren't good.</p>
   <p>That's my view. A lot of people I usually agree with (including my past self!) vehemently support Section 230. I think I was mistaken, and they are mistaken. Yes, we want public forums on the internet, and we should craft a liability regime that renders it practical to operate one. But we want deliberation and controversial speech to inhabit a diverse array of smaller, higher quality public forums, with radically divergent "community standards". Megaplatforms may be okay for baby pictures and how-to videos. They make a terrible public square. There's no meaningful democracy with a terrible public square.</p>
   <p>A great thing about lawsuits is they tend to go where the money is. Section 230 proponents often argue fatalistically that it's no good trying to undo the platform economy by eliminating the law they <a href="https://www.jeffkosseff.com/home">enthuse literally created it</a>, because big platforms can afford lawyers to parry lawsuits, but small forums can't. Sure, but lots of us have blogged for decades with no liability shield, and it's fine, because defamation and other speech torts are hard to prove, and we're not so rich as to make long-shot lawsuits worthwhile.</p>
   <p>Win a case against Facebook, thogh, and you can make millions. Yeah, they can afford lawyers. But unless they err on the side of tremendous caution, they'll need a whole lot of them.</p>
   <p>We should strengthen <a href="https://anti-slapp.org/">anti-SLAPP protections</a>, and define safe-harbors (perhaps a notice period before forum operators become potentially liable for third-party speech). But the blanket immunity provided by Section 230 is just, in my view, a failed experiment.</p>
   <p>Anyway, I didn't plan to write all this. I mostly meant to post this graphic:</p> <img alt="Positions on Section 230 mapped into four quadrants" src="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/02/22/four-quadrants-of-section-230ishness/section-230-quadrants-white.png" width="100%">
   <p>I think it interesting that on both sides of the Section 230 discourse, there are both free-expression-focused and more censorious tendencies.</p>
   <p>In the upper-left quadrant, we have the old-school internet utopians. They supported, and however disappointed and disillusioned now still mostly support, Section 230 as a straightforward boon to free speech. We want people to be able to express themselves easily and freely on the internet, internet forums are an important venue for that speech, but no one will operate a forum if they'll be liable for whatever crap their users say. So, it felt (and still feels to many) free-speech supportive just to eliminate liability for forum operators, regardless of how much or little those forums moderate or curate or shape content. Forums are good for speech, a liability shield enables and encourages forums, QED, it seemed at the time.</p>
   <p>But it's worth recalling, the core of the <a href="https://www.mtsu.edu/first-amendment/article/1070/communications-decency-act-of-1996">Communications Decency Act</a> in which Section 230 is embedded was straightfowardly to censor putatively harmful material from the internet. Section 230 was supported also by people (the upper-right quadrant) who were less concerned with promoting freewheeling expression on-line, and more interested in making it possible for forums to censor. Prior to Section 230, by moderating, a forum operator might be deemed a publisher rather than mere distributor of material, so there was a perverse (pun intended) disincentive to ban or suppress speech operators did not want on their forums.</p>
   <p>Section 230 <em>allowed</em> anything without liability (pleasing the upper-left quadrant), while <em>enabling</em> suppression and censorship (pleasing the upper-right). Whether you were the kind of person who loved passing along <a href="https://dbpedia.org/page/Goatse.cx">transgressional memes</a> or wanted censoriously wholesome spaces for families, as long as you were optimistic about a "marketplace of ideas" that would reward what was best, you could believe that Section 230 would serve your cause.</p>
   <p>The bottom-right quadrant is easy to understand. A lot of people are not in favor of an anything-goes public sphere, and are happy for the law to discourage speech they think ought not go. Traditional religious conservatives have no illusions that some marketplace will elevate virtuous speech over porn. They suggest we ban the porn.</p>
   <p>Across the political spectrum, people concerned that less regulated spaces should be safe and welcoming for people and groups often subject to harassment are under no illusion that a market will solve their problems. They argue that forums should be assiduously policed against what they deem to be harassment or hate speech, and would use the law to insist on this.</p>
   <p>Many of those I've deemed "anti-harrassment activists" would object, I think, to the axiom beneath my diagram, that there is a trade-off between concern about expression or safety. They would <a href="https://crookedtimber.org/2020/07/30/whats-wrong-with-cancel-culture/">argue</a> that in fact the two are complements, that suppressing harassment and hate-speech is in fact encouraging expression by all but the harassers and hate-speakers. Pretty much no one is opposed to "free expression", when you put it that way, but we have radically divergent views about what should count as free expression.</p>
   <p>Regardless of the virtue of their ultimate ends, groups in the bottom right quadrant are willing to use the law to suppress outright certain categories of speech they deem objectionable. (A bit cheekily, I've placed both "woke" and "anti-woke" in the bottom-right quadrant. The anti-woke might object, they are true <em>Free Speech Warriors!</em> but I think it's clear that people polarized on either side of this axis are glad to use the law to block "harmful" speech from the other side. <a href="https://weartv.com/news/local/florida-school-district-removes-library-book-called-pornography-by-desantis-administration-ron-broward-county-lets-talk-about-teen-guide-sex">School libraries in my state</a> are being emptied of "woke" literature, because it's "grooming" or "indoctrination".)</p>
   <p>The quadrant I think most interesting is (perhaps unsurprisingly) the one in which I place myself. I now oppose Section 230, but perceive myself as doing so in support of the same values of free expression that once led me to celebrate that law.</p>
   <p>There are two distinct cases for paring back Section 230 in the name of free expression. First is the case that those I've labeled "populists, conservatives, and fringes" most commonly make: Section 230 affirmatively protects platforms when they censor their views, and it should not.</p>
   <p>If you understand the top-right quadrant, why some 90s-era social conservatives favored Section 230, then you should understand that <em>removing</em> the ability of forum owners to moderate without liability means classes of expression that are in practice frequently moderated away under Secion 230 would become more expressable without it.</p>
   <p>Under the optimistic 1990s view of the internet, it was supposed to be incoherent to talk about even arguably valuable classes of expression "frequently moderated away", because the internet was going to be so open and diverse that any sort of expression anybody valued would have its home somewhere. And that is still true! You can find lots of "cancelled" perspectives at <a href="https://gab.com/">gab.com</a> if you want to.</p>
   <p>But that brings us to the second critique, which is mine.</p>
   <p>In the 1990s, we didn't foresee the polarization of "freedom of reach" on the internet. On the contrary, the internet was the vehicle that would give reach to voices locked out of broadcast television and respectable newspapers. Freedom of the press, they say, is worth very little unless you can afford to operate one. The internet would give each of our "home pages" the same reach as <em>The New York Times</em>, if we had something of value to say. The combination of technical availability and meriticracy was going to end concerns about media oligopoly.</p>
   <p>The consolidation of attention beneath a few large platforms has fully revived those concerns. Nazi speech would do poorly under anything I'd recognize as meritocracy, but segregating it from Twitter and onto Gab short-circuits the weighing process, and allows Nazi speakers to argue their ideas are suppressed rather than what they are, which is just dumb.</p>
   <p>It's no good to pull an Elon Musk and just let the Nazis back, because once attention is consolidated onto megaplatforms, there is no "neutral" way for speech to be present. Megaplatform algorithms amplify and suppress, and must amplify and suppress to keep feeds appealing to the eyeballs they sell. Twitter can pretend as much as it wants that its algorithm is objective and orthogonal to the perspectives offered, but in social affairs nothing is orthogonal, choices will entrain correlations, and Nazi shit can be pretty engaging in a tabloidy way. You are either with the Nazis or against them, Elon, which will it be?</p>
   <p>The better solution, I would argue, is for a much less polarized and hierarchical public square. We can't have a world with more than a handful of Twitters, Facebook, YouTube, TikToks. We should prefer a world with a whole lot of Gabs, except most of them would be full of decent and interesting people rather than aggrieved conspiracists. "Virality", the transformation of an individual's local expression to a signal with systematic effects should be hard, a result of consensus rather than mere "engagement". Amplification should be the result of decentralized human choices, not centralized attention-seeking algorithms.</p>
   <p><a href="https://joinmastodon.org/">Mastodon</a> is imperfect in a lot of ways, but it's one "social network" that begins to approach this vision. The "local-first" ethos of the <a href="https://github.com/hometown-fork/hometown">hometown</a> Mastodon fork is an even closer fit. It augurs a civil society made up of communities that are by default local and private, from which social consensus might emerge only from meaningfully independent evaluation by diverse communities small enough to be deliberative, rather than via some signal that becomes salient and systematic among individuals by virtue of salaciousness. (Read <a href="https://runyourown.social/">Darius Kazemi</a>.) We are so trained now to seek influence, each of us tiny minnows in a giant ocean hoping our next post or tweet will make us a big fish. We are rendered both pathetic and venal by this dynamic. A sane public square is a composition of diverse and sane communities, not attention-seeking atoms.</p>
   <p>So long as the internet remains hospitable to scale and driven by monetary incentives towards engagement, we won't have diverse, sane communities. We will have giant, manipulative tabloids in the sky.</p>
   <p>But, you might claim, these platforms "won the market test". Why should we pick winners and losers?</p>
   <p>We did pick winners and losers, when in the 1990s we demonetized quality of curation, leaving only attention and engagement to sell. That's what Section 230 does. Absent Section 230, good moderators are financial winners, bad moderators are financial black holes.</p>
   <p>We picked winners and losers in the 1990s when we strengthened "intellectual property law" and passed the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Digital_Millennium_Copyright_Act">Digital Millennium Copyright Act</a> both of which render a mix of scale and predatory legal creativity key to market success.</p>
   <p>There is no neutral, in law and technology. We make this stuff up. We picked winners and losers in the 1990s. We made dystopian choices. It is time to revisit them.</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div class="entry-footer">
  <div class="post-metainfo">
   <a href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/2023/02/22/four-quadrants-of-section-230ishness/index.html">draft</a> by <b>Steve Randy Waldman</b><br>[2023-02-22 @ 05:00 PM EST]
  </div>
 </div>
</article>]]>
      </content:encoded>
    </item>
    <atom:link type="application/rss+xml" rel="self" href="https://drafts.interfluidity.com/feed/index.rss"/>
  </channel>
</rss>
